[
    {
        "question": "Which statement best explains the periods of the Gupta Empire of India, the Golden Age of Greece, and the Renaissance in Italy?",
        "correct_answer": "a combination of wealth and a time of relative peace often leads to cultural achievement",
        "distractor1": "the winning of a war often inspires scientific and artistic achievement",
        "distractor2": "a dictatorship usually encourages cultural growth and development",
        "distractor3": "periods of censorship are needed for a nation to achieve cultural and scientific greatness"
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which Medieval European society, Latin American colonial society, and society in Imperial China were similar is that each",
        "correct_answer": "was organized according to a rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "placed great value on public education",
        "distractor2": "experienced a surplus of skilled labor",
        "distractor3": "de-emphasized the role of religion"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which idea did Napoleon Bonaparte, Sun Yat-Sen, and Simone Bolivar have in common?",
        "correct_answer": "nationalism",
        "distractor1": "divine right",
        "distractor2": "totalitarianism",
        "distractor3": "nonviolence"
    },
    {
        "question": "Eighteenth-century Russia and nineteenth-century Japan were similar in that both countries",
        "correct_answer": "began the process of modernization after a long period of isolation",
        "distractor1": "developed democratic governments after years under absolute monarchies",
        "distractor2": "refused to accept western technological ideas",
        "distractor3": "adopted socialist economic systems after capitalism had failed"
    },
    {
        "question": "Until the 1500 s, China and Japan were similar in that both",
        "correct_answer": "had little contact with Western European nations",
        "distractor1": "were invaded by the Mongols",
        "distractor2": "welcomed Christian Missionaries",
        "distractor3": "were developing democratic traditions"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Middle Ages, Europeans did not eat potatoes or corn because these vegetables",
        "correct_answer": "had not yet been introduced to Europe from the New World",
        "distractor1": "were forbidden by the Catholic Church for religious reasons",
        "distractor2": "were believed to be poisonous",
        "distractor3": "were too expensive to import from China"
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which Medieval European society, Latin American colonial society, and society in Imperial China were similar is that each",
        "correct_answer": "was organized according to a rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "placed great value on public education",
        "distractor2": "experienced a surplus of skilled labor",
        "distractor3": "de-emphasized the role of religion"
    },
    {
        "question": "The societies of traditional China, Feudal Japan, and Czarist Russia were all characterized by",
        "correct_answer": "a rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "much interaction with other cultures",
        "distractor2": "great economic change",
        "distractor3": "rapidly changing social values"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between the decline of the Roman Empire and the fall of the Manchu Dynasty was that both initially led to",
        "correct_answer": "political chaos and decentralization of government",
        "distractor1": "improved economic conditions",
        "distractor2": "democratically elected governments",
        "distractor3": "major accomplishments in art, science, and technology"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Japanese feudal system and the Hindu caste system are similar in that both systems",
        "correct_answer": "developed a rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "promoted social mobility",
        "distractor2": "encouraged the people to take part in government",
        "distractor3": "resulted in economic opportunities for the lower classes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Eighteenth-century Russia and nineteenth-century Japan were similar in that both countries",
        "correct_answer": "began the process of modernization after a long period of isolation",
        "distractor1": "developed democratic governments after years under absolute monarchies",
        "distractor2": "refused to accept western technological ideas",
        "distractor3": "adopted socialist economic systems after capitalism had failed"
    },
    {
        "question": "Changes in Russia under Peter the Great were most similar to changes that occurred in",
        "correct_answer": "Japan during the Meiji Restoration",
        "distractor1": "China before the Opium War",
        "distractor2": "Iran after the fall of Shah Pahlevi",
        "distractor3": "France during the feudal period"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Tamils in Sri Lanka, the Sikhs in India, and the Zulus in South Africa have all attempted to",
        "correct_answer": "achieve political separatism",
        "distractor1": "establish colonies in Asia",
        "distractor2": "practice passive resistance",
        "distractor3": "encourage mercantilism"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was characteristic of France under Napoleon s rule and Germany under Hitler s rule?",
        "correct_answer": "authoritarian control and a strong sense of nationalism prevailed",
        "distractor1": "democratic ideas and diversity were encouraged",
        "distractor2": "peaceful relations with neighboring countries wee fostered",
        "distractor3": "artistic and literary freedom flourished"
    },
    {
        "question": "A study of the French Revolution and the Russian Revolution of 1917 would lead to the conclusion that",
        "correct_answer": "control of revolutions often shifts from moderates to radicals",
        "distractor1": "revolutions only occur when a majority of citizens become directly involved",
        "distractor2": "university students are most often responsible for starting revolutions",
        "distractor3": "revolutions seldom result in long-term changes"
    },
    {
        "question": "The French Revolution, the Bolshevik Revolution in Russia, and the Communist Revolution in China were similar in that all three",
        "correct_answer": "were influenced by the peasants  desire for more land",
        "distractor1": "brought about few political changes",
        "distractor2": "were inspired by Marxism",
        "distractor3": "were supported primarily by the nobility"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ancient Greek city-state of Sparta and the Soviet Union under Stalin were similar in that both societies",
        "correct_answer": "were powerful military states",
        "distractor1": "were primarily concerned with the health of their people",
        "distractor2": "granted universal suffrage to their people",
        "distractor3": "placed great emphasis on literature and the arts"
    },
    {
        "question": "In China, the building of the Great Wall, the use of the tribute system, and the government s support of the Boxer Rebellion are examples of attempts by different dynasties to limit",
        "correct_answer": "foreign influence",
        "distractor1": "nationalism",
        "distractor2": "communist expansion",
        "distractor3": "industrialization"
    },
    {
        "question": "The French Revolution of 1789 and the Cuban Revolution of 1959 were similar in that both were caused primarily by the",
        "correct_answer": "failure of the government to meet the needs of the people",
        "distractor1": "desire of the people to be free from foreign rule",
        "distractor2": "pressure of religious leaders for government reform",
        "distractor3": "ambition of the upper class to attain wealth and property"
    },
    {
        "question": "The philosophies of Confucius and Mao Zedong both emphasized",
        "correct_answer": "group rather than individual welfare",
        "distractor1": "individual rather than cooperative gain",
        "distractor2": "industry rather than agriculture",
        "distractor3": "religious values rather than economic profits"
    },
    {
        "question": "Japan during the Meiji Restoration was similar to Japan after World War II in that during these periods Japan",
        "correct_answer": "underwent political reform and economic expansion",
        "distractor1": "pursued a foreign policy of isolationism and limited political freedoms",
        "distractor2": "reduced the powers of the Emperor and the nobility",
        "distractor3": "was ruled by dictators and the military"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since the late 1940 s, India, Northern Ireland, and Israel have faced the common problem of",
        "correct_answer": "continued violent confrontations between different religious groups",
        "distractor1": "adjusting to a post-Communist political and economic system",
        "distractor2": "economic depression as a result of rapid industrialization",
        "distractor3": "uncertainty of their acceptance by the European Community"
    },
    {
        "question": "The events that led to the overthrow of Czar Nicholas II in 1917 and to the forced resignation of Mikhail Gorbachev in 1991 show that",
        "correct_answer": "economic crises often lead to political change",
        "distractor1": "Russian absolutism continued into the 1990 s",
        "distractor2": "international conflicts often strengthen the power of leaders",
        "distractor3": "Russia is an ethnically unified nation"
    },
    {
        "question": "Events in both Eastern Europe in the early 1900 s and in the Soviet Union in the late 1980 s were mainly the result of",
        "correct_answer": "challenges by ethnic groups desiring independence",
        "distractor1": "movements toward the repression of individual rights",
        "distractor2": "declines in the use of advanced technology",
        "distractor3": "the influence of religion on government"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the late 1980 s and early 1990 s, the Soviet Union experienced ethnic tensions that were most similar to those experienced by",
        "correct_answer": "Austria-Hungary in the late 19th century",
        "distractor1": "Japan in the early 17th century",
        "distractor2": "Spain in the mid-18th century",
        "distractor3": "Cuba in the late 20th century"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Holocaust in Europe and the actions of the Khmer Rouge in Kampuchea (Cambodia) were similar in that they were examples of",
        "correct_answer": "Genocide",
        "distractor1": "Interdependence",
        "distractor2": "Segregation",
        "distractor3": "Empathy"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between Mao Zedong and Fidel Castro is that they",
        "correct_answer": "led revolutionary movements that established communist governments",
        "distractor1": "achieved their goals through the use of peaceful resistance",
        "distractor2": "worked to protect citizens  rights to freedom of expression",
        "distractor3": "considered capitalism to be the best economic system"
    },
    {
        "question": " Germany Will Make Reparations For WWI    OPEC Supports Oil Embargo Against Western Nations  ",
        "correct_answer": "economic measures are often designed to achieve political goals",
        "distractor1": "communism as an economic system has failed",
        "distractor2": "economic policies are often formulated to encourage investment",
        "distractor3": "nationalism plays a small role in economic decisionmaking"
    },
    {
        "question": "A study of the policy of  ethnic cleansing  in Bosnia and the Holocaust in Europe would suggest that",
        "correct_answer": "anti-Semitism and ethnic hatred remain powerful forces in the 20th century",
        "distractor1": "world opinion is effective in stopping genocide",
        "distractor2": "countries generally use reason and negotiation in dealing with important ethnic issues",
        "distractor3": "military leaders cannot be held responsible for acts committed during wartime"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor has most limited the development of national unity in India, Lebanon, and Bosnia-Herzegovina?",
        "correct_answer": "religious and ethnic differences",
        "distractor1": "lack of natural resources",
        "distractor2": "inability to end colonialism",
        "distractor3": "rapid growth of industry"
    },
    {
        "question": "Both the Chinese Mandate of Heaven and the Japanese belief that the Emperor descends from the Sun Goddess are similar to the",
        "correct_answer": "divine right theory of the French monarchy",
        "distractor1": " master race  theory of Adolf Hitler s Third Reich",
        "distractor2": "natural rights theory of the Age of Reason",
        "distractor3": "Marxist theory of a workers  revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which the caste system and apartheid were similar is that both",
        "correct_answer": "supported a rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "described specific religious practices and beliefs",
        "distractor2": "were created by British colonial governments",
        "distractor3": "gave power to the lower classes in their respective societies"
    },
    {
        "question": "Within their respective nations, both Ho Chi Minh and Fidel Castro achieved their goals by",
        "correct_answer": "using armed conflict to bring a communist government to power",
        "distractor1": "seeking aid and support from the European Union",
        "distractor2": "following a policy of nonalignment",
        "distractor3": "working to build a capitalist system"
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which the Meiji Restoration in Japan and the Golden Age of India are similar is that in each region these events led to",
        "correct_answer": "periods of rapid change",
        "distractor1": "the persecution of minority peoples",
        "distractor2": "the rise of feudalism as the dominant political system",
        "distractor3": "governments ruled by absolute monarchs"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Sepoy Rebellion in India and the Boxer Rebellion in China were similar in that both were",
        "correct_answer": "revolts against foreign influence",
        "distractor1": "attempts to improve foreign trade",
        "distractor2": "nonviolent resistance efforts",
        "distractor3": "revolutions against traditional monarchs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Suleiman held complete religious and political power.  Charles I stormed the English Parliament. ",
        "correct_answer": "absolutism",
        "distractor1": "scientific theory",
        "distractor2": "natural rights",
        "distractor3": "mercantilism"
    },
    {
        "question": "What would a study of the recent civil wars in Cambodia, Bosnia-Herzegovina, and Rwanda show about these conflicts?",
        "correct_answer": "Genocide was used as a political and military tactic.",
        "distractor1": "Ethnic conflict was not a factor in the late 20th century.",
        "distractor2": "The United Nations was successful in resolving these disputes.",
        "distractor3": "Civilians were not affected by these disputes."
    },
    {
        "question": "A similarity of the goals of Nelson Mandela and Mohandas Gandhi is that both leaders wanted to",
        "correct_answer": "secure political power for the majority of the people",
        "distractor1": "encourage a greater degree of industrialization",
        "distractor2": "improve the economy by expanding governmental control",
        "distractor3": "gain independence from the Soviet Union"
    },
    {
        "question": " Statement 1:   This organization is created for the purpose of realizing the national ideal:",
        "correct_answer": "Self-determination of the people is an important goal.",
        "distractor1": "War is a means of achieving national policies.",
        "distractor2": "Industrial growth is critical to a country s prosperity.",
        "distractor3": "Social class differences are the source of all conflicts."
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which Sim n Bol var, Jomo Kenyatta, and Ho Chi Minh are similar is that each leader",
        "correct_answer": "sought independence from colonial rule",
        "distractor1": "ruled during a period of peace and prosperity",
        "distractor2": "demanded human rights for all citizens",
        "distractor3": "established a totalitarian government"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which document is an example of a primary source?",
        "correct_answer": "the diary of a survivor of a Nazi death camp",
        "distractor1": "a textbook on Russian history",
        "distractor2": "an encyclopedia article on religions of the Middle East",
        "distractor3": "a novel on the Age of Exploration"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which historical events are in the correct chronological order?",
        "correct_answer": "Neolithic Revolution -> Roman Empire -> Crusades -> Renaissance",
        "distractor1": "Crusades -> Renaissance -> Neolithic Revolution -> Roman Empire",
        "distractor2": "Roman Empire -> Neolithic Revolution -> Crusades -> Renaissance",
        "distractor3": "Renaissance ->Neolithic Revolution -> Crusades -> Roman Empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "  The United Nations Declaration of Human Rights",
        "correct_answer": "primary sources",
        "distractor1": "secondary sources",
        "distractor2": "examples of oral traditions",
        "distractor3": "statements of different religious beliefs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best explains why most of the population of the people s Republic of China live in the eastern third of the nation?  ",
        "correct_answer": "best agricultural land is in the East",
        "distractor1": "largest forests are in the East",
        "distractor2": "best fishing areas are off the eastern coast",
        "distractor3": "largest oil deposits are in the East"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is an accurate statement about Japan s natural resources?",
        "correct_answer": "Japan has extensively used the seas for fishing",
        "distractor1": "large reserves of petroleum are located in the northern part of Japan",
        "distractor2": "Japan has large fertile plains suitable for growing grain",
        "distractor3": "large coal and iron-ore deposits are located in the mountain region"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Japan, a major economic problem has been the lack of",
        "correct_answer": "natural resources",
        "distractor1": "investment capital",
        "distractor2": "skilled labor",
        "distractor3": "experienced management"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes an effect that geography has had on Japan?",
        "correct_answer": "the lack of important natural resources has led Japan to depend on trade with other nations",
        "distractor1": "Japan s smooth coastline has prevented the development of a fishing industry",
        "distractor2": "Japan s large plains have made wheat growing a primary industry",
        "distractor3": "the location of Japan has encouraged great ethnic diversity within the nation"
    },
    {
        "question": "Both Japan and Indonesia are made up of a chain of islands called",
        "correct_answer": "an archipelago",
        "distractor1": "a peninsula",
        "distractor2": "a delta",
        "distractor3": "an atoll"
    },
    {
        "question": "The term  Latin America  most accurately refers to the",
        "correct_answer": "areas of the Western Hemisphere south of the United States",
        "distractor1": "countries that belong to the Organization of American States",
        "distractor2": "continents of North and South America",
        "distractor3": "countries that have close economic ties with Spain"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which generalization about geography of Latin America is accurate?",
        "correct_answer": "great variations in latitude and landforms resulted in a diversity of climates",
        "distractor1": "geographic features prevented foreign imperialism",
        "distractor2": "harsh climatic conditions have prevented the development of large-scale agriculture",
        "distractor3": "the lack of geographic barriers facilitated the development of transportation and communication systems"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which geographic factor has had the most influence on Poland's historical and cultural development?",
        "correct_answer": "location on the great European Plain",
        "distractor1": "a severe climate",
        "distractor2": "vast deposits of oil",
        "distractor3": "a rugged coastline"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these nations is located closet to the Philippines, Malaysia, and Indonesia?",
        "correct_answer": "Vietnam",
        "distractor1": "Korea",
        "distractor2": "Somalia",
        "distractor3": "Pakistan"
    },
    {
        "question": "One effect that mountain ranges, rain forests, and river systems have had on Latin America has been to",
        "correct_answer": "limit the development of transportation and communication systems",
        "distractor1": "encourage cultural diffusion",
        "distractor2": "permit the nations of the area to use a single form of government",
        "distractor3": "allow the development of large amounts of arable land"
    },
    {
        "question": "In addition to providing water for Indian agriculture, the Ganges River remains important to India because it is",
        "correct_answer": "a sacred river for the Hindu population",
        "distractor1": "the only source of Indian hydroelectric power",
        "distractor2": "the birthplace of Hindu culture",
        "distractor3": "an unofficial boundary between the Hindus and Muslims"
    },
    {
        "question": "An effect of a mountainous topography on Inca and Chinese civilizations was the development of",
        "correct_answer": "terrace farming",
        "distractor1": "industrialization",
        "distractor2": "single-crop economy",
        "distractor3": "desalinization projects"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major effect of geography on Japan is that the",
        "correct_answer": "scarcity of natural resources has forced Japan to obtain raw materials from other nations",
        "distractor1": "export of oil has helped Japan maintain a favorable balance of trade",
        "distractor2": "fertile plains have enabled Japan to keep food prices low",
        "distractor3": "mountains have prevented invasions obey foreign nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which geographic factor has most strongly influenced Russia s foreign policies and economic development?",
        "correct_answer": "limited access to warm-water ports",
        "distractor1": "lack of natural resources",
        "distractor2": "vast desert regions",
        "distractor3": "extensive mountain ranges"
    },
    {
        "question": "Many people in Southeast Asia hope for the timely arrival of the summer monsoons each year because",
        "correct_answer": "little rain has fallen for many months",
        "distractor1": "floods are the only way to water their farmlands",
        "distractor2": "daily temperatures often reach 100 degrees Fahrenheit",
        "distractor3": "oases provide water for nomadic herders"
    },
    {
        "question": "A topographical map would most likely be used to",
        "correct_answer": "estimate the elevation of Bangkok, Thailand",
        "distractor1": "identify the major agricultural products of Egypt",
        "distractor2": "determine the population of Beijing, China",
        "distractor3": "count the number of provinces in India"
    },
    {
        "question": "On a map of the world, Asia is to Japan as Europe is to",
        "correct_answer": "Great Britain",
        "distractor1": "the Netherlands",
        "distractor2": "Austria",
        "distractor3": "Italy"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Russian steppe is most similar in topography to the",
        "correct_answer": "savannas in Africa",
        "distractor1": "mountains in Switzerland",
        "distractor2": "deserts in the Middle East",
        "distractor3": "rainforests in South America"
    },
    {
        "question": "Areas of Africa and parts of Siberia in Russia are often said to be gems-in-the-rough because they have",
        "correct_answer": "many undeveloped natural resources",
        "distractor1": "extensive tracts of permanently frozen land",
        "distractor2": "well-developed coastal fishing industries",
        "distractor3": "decreasing populations"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Africa, an effect of topography and climate has been to",
        "correct_answer": "promote the growth of diverse societies",
        "distractor1": "encourage rapid industrialization of the interior",
        "distractor2": "prevent the development of kingdoms",
        "distractor3": "promote large-scale trade between African and Asia"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Suez Canal, the Strait of Hormuz, and the Strait of Gibraltar are important because they",
        "correct_answer": "control access to vital trade routes",
        "distractor1": "prevent attacks on bordering nations",
        "distractor2": "limit Russian access to warm-water points",
        "distractor3": "prohibit the movement of ships carrying nuclear weapons"
    },
    {
        "question": "Geographic diversity in the Middle East has contributed to",
        "correct_answer": "unequal standards of living",
        "distractor1": "a common economic system",
        "distractor2": "similar political systems",
        "distractor3": "military alliances with Japan"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Suez Canal, the Panama Canal, and the Straits of the Dardanelles are similar because they",
        "correct_answer": "are strategic waterways that have been the center of conflicts",
        "distractor1": "was part of the French colonial empire",
        "distractor2": "are located in regions that are rich in natural resources",
        "distractor3": "prohibit the movement of ships carrying nuclear weapons"
    },
    {
        "question": "The map shows that the",
        "correct_answer": "distribution of income in China is unequal",
        "distractor1": "economies of all the regions of China are developing at the same rate",
        "distractor2": "economies of the interior provinces of China are developing faster than those of the coastal provinces",
        "distractor3": "economic development in China is dependent upon the cash crops of Xinjiang and Tibet"
    },
    {
        "question": "One factor that accounted for Chinese influence on traditional Japanese culture was the",
        "correct_answer": "geographic location of the countries",
        "distractor1": "continuous warfare between the countries",
        "distractor2": "refusal of western nations to trade with Japan",
        "distractor3": "annexation of Japan into the Chinese Empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "Throughout the 1800 s, Russia was interested in acquiring Turkey mainly because Russia wanted",
        "correct_answer": "access to the Mediterranean Sea",
        "distractor1": "to maintain peace in the Middle East",
        "distractor2": "to reestablish the Byzantine Empire",
        "distractor3": "the rich farmland of the Anatolian Plateau"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which geographic factor has contributed most to the economic growth of Japan, Egypt, and Great Britain?",
        "correct_answer": "access to important waterways",
        "distractor1": "variety of natural resources",
        "distractor2": "reliable amount of rainfall",
        "distractor3": "abundance of arable land"
    },
    {
        "question": "In which way have the Andes Mountains and the Amazon rain forest affected the development of Latin America?",
        "correct_answer": "increasing cultural diversity",
        "distractor1": "promoting international unity",
        "distractor2": "encouraging trade agreements",
        "distractor3": "strengthening political alliances"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which geographic factor has helped China remain isolated for many centuries?",
        "correct_answer": "northern and western mountain ranges",
        "distractor1": "many natural harbors",
        "distractor2": "navigable river systems",
        "distractor3": "severe climate"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes an impact of topography on eastern Europe?",
        "correct_answer": "Many different languages, religions, and customs developed.",
        "distractor1": "A Russian czar ruled the area as a single empire.",
        "distractor2": "An extensive single-crop agricultural system emerged.",
        "distractor3": "Neighbors who were more powerful could not invade the region."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which geographic factor was most important to the development of the early river valley civilizations?",
        "correct_answer": "fertile soils",
        "distractor1": "high mountains",
        "distractor2": "vast deserts",
        "distractor3": "smooth coastlines"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor contributes most to the recurring food shortages in Africa?",
        "correct_answer": "poor distribution of agricultural products",
        "distractor1": "extensive river systems",
        "distractor2": "location between two major oceans",
        "distractor3": "rainforest environment"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which condition is a major obstacle to economic development in the Middle East and Northern Africa",
        "correct_answer": "scarcity of water resources",
        "distractor1": "use of strip mining to obtain minerals",
        "distractor2": "reliance on capitalist economic systems",
        "distractor3": "lack of access to world markets"
    },
    {
        "question": "Singapore and Hong Kong have become major economic powers by taking advantage of their",
        "correct_answer": "favorable location on international trade routes",
        "distractor1": "abundant mineral resources",
        "distractor2": "imported cheap labor from Japan",
        "distractor3": "profits from agricultural surpluses"
    },
    {
        "question": "Throughout the 1800 s, Russia was interested in acquiring Turkey mainly because Russia wanted",
        "correct_answer": "access to the Mediterranean Sea",
        "distractor1": "to maintain peace in the Middle East",
        "distractor2": "to reestablish the Byzantine Empire",
        "distractor3": "the rich farmland of the Anatolian Plateau"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which conclusion can be drawn from the information in the chart?",
        "correct_answer": "The nations with relatively low birthrates have relatively high per capita incomes.",
        "distractor1": "Developing countries are instituting programs to limit the growth of their populations.",
        "distractor2": "Infant mortality is a greater problem in Africa than in Asia.",
        "distractor3": "The national birthrate is determined by many different factors."
    },
    {
        "question": "A comparison of Japan s policies before 1945 with the policies in effect after 1945 indicates that",
        "correct_answer": "territorial aggression is not necessary to secure national economic goals",
        "distractor1": "reduction in spending on military goods leads to economic depression",
        "distractor2": "dependence on foreign trade usually leads to a weakened national economy",
        "distractor3": "democratic institutions hinder economic growth"
    },
    {
        "question": "A study of Japan s economy since World War II would lead to the conclusion that",
        "correct_answer": "a. government support of technological advances can improve a nation s economic position",
        "distractor1": "a. imperialism is necessary form the economic development of a nation",
        "distractor2": "a. a communist system leads to economic prosperity",
        "distractor3": "a. the feudal system is more economically productive than the market system"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which situation has contributed most to recent Japanese economic growth?",
        "correct_answer": "The Japanese government and Japanese businesses have cooperated with each other.",
        "distractor1": "The Japanese government has place limits on Japanese exports.",
        "distractor2": "Japanese industries spend very little on the research and development of new products.",
        "distractor3": "Japanese citizens save less of their incomes than the citizens of other industrialized nation do."
    },
    {
        "question": "The emergence of Japan as a world economic power has been based mostly on Japan s",
        "correct_answer": "business enterprise and organization",
        "distractor1": "development of nuclear power",
        "distractor2": "abundance of fossil fuels",
        "distractor3": "strong traditional of military rule"
    },
    {
        "question": "In recent years, which factor has been a major reason for the economic tensions between the United States and Japan?",
        "correct_answer": "the United States imported more from Japan than it exported to Japan",
        "distractor1": "Japan s trade deficit with the United States was very high",
        "distractor2": "the United States refused to place quotas on Japanese goods",
        "distractor3": "Japan lowered tariffs on goods imported from the United States"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since World War II, people in both Africa and Latin America have moved from rural to urban areas.  The major cause of this movement has been the",
        "correct_answer": "expectation of improved economic opportunities",
        "distractor1": "rejection of traditional custom",
        "distractor2": "guarantee of better housing",
        "distractor3": "fear of civil war"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor best accounts for the existence of cash-crop production as a major form of agriculture in many Central American nations today?",
        "correct_answer": "demand of world markets for such crops",
        "distractor1": "lack of modern agricultural technology",
        "distractor2": "inadequate supply of water and other natural resources",
        "distractor3": "peasant ownership of most farmlands"
    },
    {
        "question": "Economic development in Japan after World War II and in Communist China since the 1980 s is similar in that both nations have sought to",
        "correct_answer": "nationalize most major industries and restrict competition",
        "distractor1": "end foreign investment",
        "distractor2": "develop their vast natural resources to achieve economic growth",
        "distractor3": "utilize the concepts of capitalism to improve their economies"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980 s and 1990 s, the economic policies of China, supported by Deng Xiaoping, have led directly to",
        "correct_answer": "an increase in trade with the West",
        "distractor1": "an expansion of China s colonial empire",
        "distractor2": "a return to a strict command economy",
        "distractor3": "the success of the commune system"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best explains China s economic shift toward capitalism in the 1980 s and early 1990 s?",
        "correct_answer": "communist economic policies were not meeting the needs of the society",
        "distractor1": "China s economic policies were directly influenced by the success of the Soviet economic system",
        "distractor2": "the Tiananmen Square massacre resulted in major economic reforms in China",
        "distractor3": "the success of the Cultural Revolution resulted in the increased westernization of China"
    },
    {
        "question": "One principle in the theory of mercantilism is that colonies should be",
        "correct_answer": "acquired as markets and sources of raw materials",
        "distractor1": "granted independence as soon as possible",
        "distractor2": "considered an economic burden for the colonial power",
        "distractor3": "encouraged to develop their own industries"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes how a command economy functioned in the Soviet Union?",
        "correct_answer": "A central authority determined the type and quantity of goods to be produced.",
        "distractor1": "The laws of supply and demand controlled the economy.",
        "distractor2": "Trade policies mandated that imports exceed exports.",
        "distractor3": "The success of the agricultural sector controlled the price of manufactured goods."
    },
    {
        "question": "To maintain its economic position, Japan has often limited the number of cars or the quantity of farm products that the United States can sell in Japan. Japan has imposed these limits to develop",
        "correct_answer": "a favorable balance of trade",
        "distractor1": "an equality-of-trade position",
        "distractor2": "a more open market",
        "distractor3": "a belief system"
    },
    {
        "question": "The economic policy of mercantilism first developed during the",
        "correct_answer": "Age of Exploration",
        "distractor1": "Enlightenment",
        "distractor2": "Cold War",
        "distractor3": "Green Revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "  Statement A:   The might of a country consists of gaining surpluses of gold and silver.",
        "correct_answer": "mercantile",
        "distractor1": "traditional",
        "distractor2": "feudal",
        "distractor3": "command"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which generalization about democracy is most valid?",
        "correct_answer": "democratic governments protect basic civil liberties",
        "distractor1": "democratic political systems require a highly industrialized society",
        "distractor2": "democratic governments first evolved in North America",
        "distractor3": "democratic governments prevent their citizens from traveling abroad"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor is necessary for the development of democratic institutions?",
        "correct_answer": "respect for individual rights",
        "distractor1": "strong military forces",
        "distractor2": "a one-party system",
        "distractor3": "an agricultural economy"
    },
    {
        "question": " Power tends to corrupt; absolute power corrupts absolutely. ",
        "correct_answer": "representative democracy",
        "distractor1": "dictatorship",
        "distractor2": "absolute monarchy",
        "distractor3": "totalitarian state"
    },
    {
        "question": "Democracy in modern Japan resulted primarily from",
        "correct_answer": "reforms imposed by the United States after World War II",
        "distractor1": "Shinto and Buddhist beliefs about equality and justice",
        "distractor2": "a history of imperial justice under the constitution of the Emperor",
        "distractor3": "the diffusion of ideas and practices from China and Korea"
    },
    {
        "question": "After the breakup of the Austro-Hungarian Empire and the Soviet Union, new nations were formed.  Which generalization accurately reflects the effect of the breakup on these new nations?",
        "correct_answer": "national and ethnic differences often lead to instability and violence in new nations",
        "distractor1": "new nations are generally too poor and weak to become active members of the United Nations",
        "distractor2": "new nations rarely use their limited resources to wage war",
        "distractor3": "self-determination generally leads to democratic forms of government in new nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement describes a characteristic of the British parliamentary system today?",
        "correct_answer": "the Prime Minister is elected by the majority party in Parliament",
        "distractor1": "the monarch serves as a strong head of state",
        "distractor2": "the members of the House of Commons are appointed for life",
        "distractor3": "the minority party has no vote in the Parliament"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which political system is the basis of Japan s government today?",
        "correct_answer": "parliamentary democracy",
        "distractor1": "military dictatorship",
        "distractor2": "absolute monarchy",
        "distractor3": "national socialism"
    },
    {
        "question": " A constitution? What for? The Koran is the oldest and most efficient constitution in the world.  --King Faisal of Saudi Arabia (1966)  ",
        "correct_answer": "the laws of Islam can be used to govern a country",
        "distractor1": "every country needs elected leaders",
        "distractor2": "Muslims believe in a weak central government",
        "distractor3": "religion should be separated from government"
    },
    {
        "question": " Cavour Provokes War Against Austria    Mazzini Establishes Young Italy  ",
        "correct_answer": "nationalism",
        "distractor1": "isolationism",
        "distractor2": "imperialism",
        "distractor3": "totalitarianism"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels believe would be the result when communism finally emerged as the dominant political and economic system?",
        "correct_answer": "All the evils of industrial society would disappear.",
        "distractor1": "Only two classes would exist in society.",
        "distractor2": "The Soviet Union would become the world s only superpower.",
        "distractor3": "Citizens would own their individual homes and farms."
    },
    {
        "question": "A similarity of the rule of the ancient Mongols and the ancient Greeks is that both",
        "correct_answer": "established vast empires and spread their cultures to the people they conquered",
        "distractor1": "protected the human rights of the peoples they controlled",
        "distractor2": "destroyed the civilizations they defeated",
        "distractor3": "remained isolated and peaceful for centuries"
    },
    {
        "question": "The code of Hammurabi is an example of",
        "correct_answer": "written rules for legal procedures",
        "distractor1": "the power of strong kings to control trade",
        "distractor2": "regulations on the way to conduct wars against neighboring nations",
        "distractor3": "the power of a legislature to veto laws passed by absolute monarchs"
    },
    {
        "question": " . . . suspending laws . . . , by regal [royal] authority without consent of Parliament is illegal. ",
        "correct_answer": "limited monarchy",
        "distractor1": "dynastic rule",
        "distractor2": "totalitarian",
        "distractor3": "theocracy"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Magna Carta, the Glorious Revolution, and the writings of John Locke all contributed to Great Britain s development of",
        "correct_answer": "parliamentary democracy",
        "distractor1": "absolute monarchy",
        "distractor2": "ethnic rivalries",
        "distractor3": "imperialist policies"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Soviet Union, Joseph Stalin governed by means of secret police, censorship, and purges.",
        "correct_answer": "totalitarian",
        "distractor1": "democracy",
        "distractor2": "limited monarchy",
        "distractor3": "theocracy"
    },
    {
        "question": "  Speaker A:   The gods approached Vishnu, the lord of creatures, and said:  Indicate to us that one person among mortals who alone is worthy of the highest rank . . .  Vishnu reflected, and brought forth a glorious son who became the first king.  ",
        "correct_answer": "A and D",
        "distractor1": "B and C",
        "distractor2": "A and C",
        "distractor3": "B and D"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which aspect of a nation s culture is most directly influenced by the physical geography of that nation?",
        "correct_answer": "population distribution",
        "distractor1": "form of government",
        "distractor2": "religious beliefs",
        "distractor3": "social class system"
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason the cultures of North Africa developed differently from the cultures of the rest of Africa was that these areas of Africa were separated by the",
        "correct_answer": "Sahara Desert",
        "distractor1": "Congo River Basin",
        "distractor2": "Great Rift Valley",
        "distractor3": "Arabian Sea"
    },
    {
        "question": "In China, the development of ethnocentrism was most influenced by",
        "correct_answer": "its geographic isolation",
        "distractor1": "its historic reliance on foreign nations",
        "distractor2": "a long history of democratic government",
        "distractor3": "a strong belief in Christianity"
    },
    {
        "question": "In most societies, works of art and architecture generally serve to",
        "correct_answer": "reflect the values of that society",
        "distractor1": "satisfy the needs of the leaders",
        "distractor2": "limit the influence of religion",
        "distractor3": "express opposition to the government in power"
    },
    {
        "question": "In modern African nations, the continued strength of the tribe or ethnic group is a reflection of the continuing influence of",
        "correct_answer": "traditional cultures",
        "distractor1": "European imperialism",
        "distractor2": "urban growth",
        "distractor3": "the slave trade"
    },
    {
        "question": "Traditional African art has had the greatest influence on",
        "correct_answer": "20th century sculpture and painting",
        "distractor1": "classical Roman mosaics and pottery",
        "distractor2": "Renaissance painting",
        "distractor3": "Medieval European architecture"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which generalization is characteristic of most traditional societies?",
        "correct_answer": "sons learn the same trades as their fathers",
        "distractor1": "people move from city to city seeking new jobs",
        "distractor2": "a high degree of social mobility exists",
        "distractor3": "all people have the same economic opportunities"
    },
    {
        "question": "Recent archeological studies suggest the theory that",
        "correct_answer": "the earliest humans evolved in the Rift Valley in Africa",
        "distractor1": "farming societies developed before hunting and gathering societies",
        "distractor2": "all the continents were settled at about the same time",
        "distractor3": "the wheel was used by all ancient societies"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor has contributed most to the social and cultural identity of the Middle East?",
        "correct_answer": "strong influence of Islam on the region",
        "distractor1": "political stability of the region",
        "distractor2": "ability of the region to export oil",
        "distractor3": "lack of foreign involvement in the region"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Chinese called their land  Middle Kingdom.   Europeans often used the term  backward  to refer to China.  These statements best illustrate",
        "correct_answer": "attitudes of ethnocentrism in both cultures",
        "distractor1": "the failure of geographers to establish a universal terminology",
        "distractor2": "the importance of East Asia in world history",
        "distractor3": "the adoption of policies of nonalignment"
    },
    {
        "question": "Geographic isolation of a people frequently reinforces",
        "correct_answer": "a traditional way of life",
        "distractor1": "the development of scientific investigation",
        "distractor2": "the need for higher education",
        "distractor3": "a process of cultural diffusion"
    },
    {
        "question": "In  most societies, urbanization has",
        "correct_answer": "weakened traditional values and life patterns",
        "distractor1": "strengthened the influence of the extended family system",
        "distractor2": "discouraged economic growth",
        "distractor3": "promoted population growth"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement cites an example of cultural diffusion?",
        "correct_answer": "young people dance to rock music in Russia",
        "distractor1": "Venezuela has large reserves of oil",
        "distractor2": "students in China learn calligraphy in school",
        "distractor3": "the Caste system is an important part of life in India"
    },
    {
        "question": "In most traditional societies, the teaching of values is mainly the responsibility of the",
        "correct_answer": "family",
        "distractor1": "judicial system",
        "distractor2": "government",
        "distractor3": "educational system"
    },
    {
        "question": "The study of culture primarily involves",
        "correct_answer": "learning why various peoples live as they do",
        "distractor1": "observing the physical environment of people",
        "distractor2": "understanding the technology of modern machinery",
        "distractor3": "analyzing the personalities of children in the same family"
    },
    {
        "question": "Extended families and limited social mobility are characteristic of",
        "correct_answer": "traditional societies",
        "distractor1": "constitutional monarchies",
        "distractor2": "polytheistic religions",
        "distractor3": "socialist economies"
    },
    {
        "question": "People in both Japan and India eat very little meat.  A study of these cultures would show that",
        "correct_answer": "although these cultures have similar practices, the reasons for these practices differ",
        "distractor1": "the raising of cattle in both nations is very difficult due to the extreme climate",
        "distractor2": "neither culture is concerned with health issues",
        "distractor3": "the governments of both nations enforce strict dietary laws"
    },
    {
        "question": "The dominance of the Spanish language in Latin America and continued use of the French language in Senegal are examples of",
        "correct_answer": "cultural diffusion",
        "distractor1": "social mobility",
        "distractor2": "humanism",
        "distractor3": "Marxism"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which activity is the best example of cultural diffusion in Africa?",
        "correct_answer": "practicing of Islam in Nigeria",
        "distractor1": "weaving kente cloth in Ghana",
        "distractor2": "using masks in traditional African ceremonies",
        "distractor3": "discovering bronze sculptures from Benin"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about India is a fact rather than an opinion?",
        "correct_answer": "The Mongols ruled India for more that 100 years",
        "distractor1": "most Indians are happy with the Hindu practice of arranged marriages",
        "distractor2": "India is fortunate to have a multiparty system of government",
        "distractor3": "the partition of British India in 1947 helped India prosper"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which reference would be used to find the most recent information about the gross domestic product (GDP) of a nation?",
        "correct_answer": "world almanac",
        "distractor1": "historical atlas",
        "distractor2": "thesaurus",
        "distractor3": "dictionary"
    },
    {
        "question": "Culture is sometimes referred to as  a blueprint for living  because it",
        "correct_answer": "includes all the things that contribute to a society s development",
        "distractor1": "flourished best in traditional societies",
        "distractor2": "is determined by genetics",
        "distractor3": "determines the types of jobs offered to the members of a society"
    },
    {
        "question": "In many African nations, a major result of migration from rural to urban areas has been",
        "correct_answer": "a weakening of ancestral lines and kinship bonds",
        "distractor1": "a strengthening of traditional values",
        "distractor2": "a decline in employment opportunities for educated Africans",
        "distractor3": "increased agricultural productivity"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about Japan is a fact rather than an opinion?",
        "correct_answer": "many of Japan s cultural traditions were borrowed from China",
        "distractor1": "Japanese family values have declined with modernization",
        "distractor2": "rapid industrialization has caused few problems for the Japanese people",
        "distractor3": "traditional farming techniques in Japan were better than modern ones"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between the culture of traditional China under dynastic rule and the culture of modern China under communism is that both stress",
        "correct_answer": "loyalty to the authority of leaders",
        "distractor1": "a state-supported religion",
        "distractor2": "the importance of a matriarchal society",
        "distractor3": "limits on population growth"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ancient Chinese expression  Middle Kingdom  and the European terms  Near East  and  Far East  best reflect",
        "correct_answer": "the influence of ethnocentrism on geographic perspective",
        "distractor1": "the impact of the Enlightenment on global thinking",
        "distractor2": "an improved knowledge of world geography",
        "distractor3": "an objective view of the world s cultures"
    },
    {
        "question": "The accusations of witchcraft in 17th century England and the practice of foot-binding in 19th century China are examples of the",
        "correct_answer": "discrimination against women in various cultures",
        "distractor1": "negative aspects of a matriarchal society",
        "distractor2": "gradual improvement of women s rights around the world",
        "distractor3": "respect give to mothers in traditional cultures"
    },
    {
        "question": "Buildings such as the Gothic cathedrals in Western Europe and the Parthenon in ancient Greece reflect each society s",
        "correct_answer": "cultural values",
        "distractor1": "imperialistic attitudes",
        "distractor2": "belief in democracy",
        "distractor3": "rigid social structure"
    },
    {
        "question": "Before towns and cities can develop in a society, the society needs to establish",
        "correct_answer": "an agricultural surplus",
        "distractor1": "an educational system",
        "distractor2": "a writing system",
        "distractor3": "a democratic government"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best supports the idea that cultural diffusion has greatly affected Southeast Asia?",
        "correct_answer": "Buddhism, Hinduism, and Islam are practiced throughout Southeast Asia",
        "distractor1": "the population of Southeast Asia is concentrated in rural areas",
        "distractor2": "monsoon climates affect food production in Indonesia",
        "distractor3": "a reliance on subsistence agriculture remains a problem for many Southeast Asian economies"
    },
    {
        "question": "In India, which aspect of society has been most heavily influenced by religious beliefs, tradition, and the division of labor?",
        "correct_answer": "caste system",
        "distractor1": "policy of neutrality",
        "distractor2": "urbanization",
        "distractor3": "parliamentary government"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between the cultures of traditional China and traditional Japan was that",
        "correct_answer": "the educated class was held in high esteem",
        "distractor1": "religion played a minor role in society",
        "distractor2": "social mobility was encouraged",
        "distractor3": "the people elected the political leaders"
    },
    {
        "question": "The invention of writing systems and the growth of cities occurred only in civilizations that",
        "correct_answer": "developed complex institutions",
        "distractor1": "originated in south Asia",
        "distractor2": "developed matriarchal leadership",
        "distractor3": "borrowed heavily from the Greeks and Romans"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sociologist interested in Indian culture would most likely focus on the study of",
        "correct_answer": "Hinduism and its influence on life in India",
        "distractor1": "India s development of nuclear weapons",
        "distractor2": "the parliamentary government of India",
        "distractor3": "the influence of agricultural production on India s Gross national Product (GNP)"
    },
    {
        "question": "In India, the Caste System determined a person s occupation, personal associations, and marriage partner.  This situation shows that the Caste system",
        "correct_answer": "has been a way of life as well as an element of religion",
        "distractor1": "has helped eliminate ethnic and religious rivalries",
        "distractor2": "has promoted social mobility within Indian society",
        "distractor3": "has been stronger in urban areas that in rural areas"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the centuries of dynastic rule, the Chinese rejected other cultures as inferior to their own.  This situation illustrates the concept of",
        "correct_answer": "ethnocentrism",
        "distractor1": "imperialism",
        "distractor2": "social mobility",
        "distractor3": "cultural diffusion"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the status of women in most traditional Asian societies?",
        "correct_answer": "women were expected to dedicate their lives to their families",
        "distractor1": "women were encouraged to obtain an education",
        "distractor2": "women were expected to run for political office",
        "distractor3": "women were encouraged to work outside the home"
    },
    {
        "question": "One result of the Neolithic Revolution was",
        "correct_answer": "the establishment of villages and the rise of governments",
        "distractor1": "an increase in the number of nomadic tribes",
        "distractor2": "a reliance on hunting and gathering for food",
        "distractor3": "a decrease in trade between cultural groups"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Japanese feudal system and the Hindu caste system are similar in that both systems",
        "correct_answer": "developed a rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "promoted social mobility",
        "distractor2": "encouraged the people to take part in government",
        "distractor3": "resulted in economic opportunities for the lower classes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which situation best illustrates a traditional practice of women in Masai society?",
        "correct_answer": "a young woman marrying and her husband giving cattle to her family as a wedding gift",
        "distractor1": "a young woman leaving her village to attend a university in the capital city",
        "distractor2": "an educated woman returning to her village to become leader of her tribe",
        "distractor3": "a young mother discouraging her children from practicing animism"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Japanese feudal system and the Hindu caste system are similar in that both systems",
        "correct_answer": "developed a rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "promoted social mobility",
        "distractor2": "encouraged the people to take part in government",
        "distractor3": "resulted in economic opportunities for the lower classes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement concerning modern Japan is most accurate?",
        "correct_answer": "Japan has modernized while maintaining some elements of its traditional culture",
        "distractor1": "Japan has become a leader in global peacekeeping efforts",
        "distractor2": "Japan has shown little concern for its natural environment",
        "distractor3": "Japan has severed all traditional ties in favor of western values"
    },
    {
        "question": "The introduction of Buddhism into China and of Islam into Indonesia are examples of",
        "correct_answer": "cultural diffusion",
        "distractor1": "social mobility",
        "distractor2": "ethnocentrism",
        "distractor3": "interdependence"
    },
    {
        "question": "In a traditional society, the influence of an extended family decreases when that society is",
        "correct_answer": "experiencing rapid urbanization and industrialization",
        "distractor1": "being governed by a council of elders",
        "distractor2": "faced with a decreasing population",
        "distractor3": "raising only enough crops to feed its people"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor has been most responsible for the common culture found in Japan?",
        "correct_answer": "ethnic homogeneity",
        "distractor1": "religious diversity",
        "distractor2": "success of democracy",
        "distractor3": "political instability"
    },
    {
        "question": " From a little spark may burst a mighty flame.   --Dante  ",
        "correct_answer": "People from different cultures often view situations in similar ways.",
        "distractor1": "All cultures are concerned with transportation and conservation.",
        "distractor2": "In all cultures, people make excuses for their mistakes.",
        "distractor3": "Geography is important to the development of all cultures."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Church of the Holy Sepulchre, the Dome of the Rock, and the Western (Wailing) Wall are religious sites in Jerusalem. These sites symbolize the",
        "correct_answer": "cultural diversity of the Middle East",
        "distractor1": "Roman domination of the Mediterranean region in the 1st century",
        "distractor2": "limited architectural skills of builders in the Middle East",
        "distractor3": "geographic isolation of the city"
    },
    {
        "question": "Throughout much of history, both China and Japan held a common view that other nations were",
        "correct_answer": "barbarians not worthy of their attention",
        "distractor1": "valued sources of worthwhile knowledge",
        "distractor2": "envoys of an advanced civilization",
        "distractor3": "sources of cheap labor and goods"
    },
    {
        "question": "Historians are interested in studying Maya ruins in Mexico, the haiku poetry of Japan, and the music of Chopin because such cultural and intellectual developments",
        "correct_answer": "reflect the values of that society",
        "distractor1": "illustrate the economic status of individuals in that society",
        "distractor2": "help to explain the role of geography in that society",
        "distractor3": "reveal the political structure of that society"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which term is used to describe the spread of Buddhism from India through Southeast Asia?",
        "correct_answer": "cultural diffusion",
        "distractor1": "ethnocentrism",
        "distractor2": "isolation",
        "distractor3": "imperialism"
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason for the development of an early civilization in the Tigris-Euphrates river valleys was that",
        "correct_answer": "periodic flooding left rich soil, which was ideal for farming",
        "distractor1": "the location protected the people from land invasion",
        "distractor2": "these rivers provided a direct trade route between Europe and Asia",
        "distractor3": "these rivers flowed into the Mediterranean Sea"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which characteristic did the early civilizations that developed along the Nile, the Tigris-Euphrates and the Huang He (Yellow River) have in common?",
        "correct_answer": "transportation and communication were promoted by a mild climate, fertile soil, and natural waterways",
        "distractor1": "each society s religious beliefs were based on monotheism",
        "distractor2": "urban communities were built using iron and steel tools",
        "distractor3": "the form of government in each community was based on male suffrage"
    },
    {
        "question": "The early civilizations of the Nile River Valley, Mesopotamia, and the Yellow River Valley were similar because they were",
        "correct_answer": "dependent on fertile land",
        "distractor1": "industrialized societies",
        "distractor2": "monotheistic",
        "distractor3": "dependent on each other for trade"
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which the civilizations of the Sumerians, the Phoenicians, and the Maya were similar is that each",
        "correct_answer": "developed extensive writing systems",
        "distractor1": "emphasized equality in education",
        "distractor2": "established monotheistic religions",
        "distractor3": "encouraged democratic participation in government"
    },
    {
        "question": " If a seignior (noble) has knocked out the tooth of a seignior of his own rank, they shall knock out his tooth.  But if he has knocked out a commoner s tooth, he shall pay one-third mina of silver.   -Code of Hammurabi",
        "correct_answer": "divisions existed between social classes",
        "distractor1": "all men were equal under the law",
        "distractor2": "fines were preferable to corporal punishment",
        "distractor3": "violence was always punished with violence"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ancient civilizations of Mesopotamia and Egypt were similar in that both cultures",
        "correct_answer": "developed along rivers",
        "distractor1": "used the ziggurat form for their temples",
        "distractor2": "established trade routes to China",
        "distractor3": "used a hieroglyphic writing system"
    },
    {
        "question": "Notre Dame Cathedral in Paris, the Dome of the Rock in Jerusalem and the Great Pyramid in Egypt are examples of",
        "correct_answer": "architectural accomplishments that reflect religious beliefs",
        "distractor1": "the influence of Buddhist architecture on conquered nations",
        "distractor2": "ancient architectural monuments no longer in use",
        "distractor3": "the influence of cultural diffusion on contemporary architecture"
    },
    {
        "question": "Judaism, Islam, and Christianity share a belief in",
        "correct_answer": "monotheism and ethical conduct",
        "distractor1": "the central authority of the Pope",
        "distractor2": "a prohibition of the consumption of port",
        "distractor3": "reincarnation and the Four Noble Truths"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is a valid statement about the history of South Asia?",
        "correct_answer": "Religious beliefs have both unified and divided the people of the region.",
        "distractor1": "Little cultural diffusion has occurred in this region.",
        "distractor2": "Urbanization has strengthened the traditional beliefs and lifestyles of the people of the region.",
        "distractor3": "Superpower involvement has brought peace and economic prosperity to the region."
    },
    {
        "question": " When I go to the office, I put on my shirt and I take off my caste; when I come home, I take off my shirt and I put on my caste. ",
        "correct_answer": "the caste system continues to influence Indian society",
        "distractor1": "the caste system has been reflected by most Indians",
        "distractor2": "successful urban workers in India belong the same Caste",
        "distractor3": "the Indian government officially supports the Caste system"
    },
    {
        "question": "According the teachings of Confucius, the key to the successful organization of society is that",
        "correct_answer": "individuals should know and do what is expected of them",
        "distractor1": "the ruler should be chosen democratically",
        "distractor2": "the evil in humans must be eliminated",
        "distractor3": "ancestor worship should be discontinued"
    },
    {
        "question": "In traditional Chinese culture, which philosophy had the greatest influence on the development of social order and political organization?",
        "correct_answer": "Confucianism",
        "distractor1": "Taoism",
        "distractor2": "Shintoism",
        "distractor3": "Marxism"
    },
    {
        "question": "The teachings of Confucius encouraged people to",
        "correct_answer": "follow a code of moral conduct",
        "distractor1": "put their own interests first",
        "distractor2": "reject government authority",
        "distractor3": "believe in reincarnation"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Japan, the martial arts, the tea ceremony, and flower arranging best reflect the influences of",
        "correct_answer": "Buddhism and Shintoism",
        "distractor1": "imperialism and militarism",
        "distractor2": "capitalism",
        "distractor3": "mercantilism"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person who practices the Shinto faith would be most likely to",
        "correct_answer": "visit a shrine placed on the shore of a lake",
        "distractor1": "pray five times a day",
        "distractor2": "bathe in the Ganges River",
        "distractor3": "make a pilgrimage to Jerusalem"
    },
    {
        "question": "Taoism and Shintoism are similar in that both religions stress",
        "correct_answer": "developing harmony between humans and nature",
        "distractor1": "adhering to the five Confucian relationships",
        "distractor2": "following the Eightfold Path",
        "distractor3": "believing in one God"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between the Five Pillars of Islam and the Ten Commandments is that both",
        "correct_answer": "provide a guide to proper ethical and moral behavior",
        "distractor1": "support a belief in reincarnation",
        "distractor2": "promote learning as a means to salvation",
        "distractor3": "encourage the use of statues to symbolize God"
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which Eastern Orthodoxy, Roman Catholicism, and Protestantism are similar is that each",
        "correct_answer": "is a branch of Christianity",
        "distractor1": "accepts the supreme authority of the Pope",
        "distractor2": "rejects the Old Testament as part of the Bible",
        "distractor3": "was once the official religion of the Byzantine Empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Koran, jihad, and the hegira are most closely associated with the practice of",
        "correct_answer": "Islam",
        "distractor1": "Judaism",
        "distractor2": "Shinto",
        "distractor3": "Buddhism"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Buddhist religion teaches that salvation is earned by",
        "correct_answer": "learning to give up selfish desire",
        "distractor1": "following the Ten Commandments",
        "distractor2": "worshiping Allah as the one true god",
        "distractor3": "being baptized and confirmed"
    },
    {
        "question": "Confucianism in traditional China served to",
        "correct_answer": "maintain social order",
        "distractor1": "create ethnic unrest",
        "distractor2": "emphasize material wealth",
        "distractor3": "support democratic government"
    },
    {
        "question": "Traditional animistic beliefs in Africa, Asia, and Latin America are based on",
        "correct_answer": "an appreciation for the forces of nature",
        "distractor1": "a desire for wealth",
        "distractor2": "a written tradition",
        "distractor3": "a willingness to accept Christianity"
    },
    {
        "question": "Jewish religions and cultural identity has been greatly influenced by",
        "correct_answer": "the Torah and the Diaspora",
        "distractor1": "Ramadan and the concept of reincarnation",
        "distractor2": "the New Testament and the Four Noble Truths",
        "distractor3": "the Koran and the code of bushido"
    },
    {
        "question": "In India, the Caste system determined a person s occupation, personal associations, and marriage partner.  This situation shows that the Caste system",
        "correct_answer": "has been a way of life as well as an element of religion",
        "distractor1": "has helped eliminate ethnic and religious rivalries",
        "distractor2": "has promoted social mobility within Indian society",
        "distractor3": "has been stronger in urban areas that in rural areas"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mansa Musa s journey to Mecca in the 1300 s is evidence that",
        "correct_answer": "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire",
        "distractor1": "the Crusades had a great influence on western Africa",
        "distractor2": "most African leaders were educated in the Middle East",
        "distractor3": "European culture was superior to the cultures of western Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": " From as early as I can remember, the Emperor was an important presence even in our remote home.  He was a descendant of the gods from thousands of years before, never to be looked at or listened to by mere mortals, a presence to be revered and protected and obeyed Finally , my family and neighbors gathered around the radio and listened in stunned silence to the voice that had never before been heard, saying he was only human after all.  Everyone was crying.  I was sad and confused   ",
        "correct_answer": "Shintoism",
        "distractor1": "Christianity",
        "distractor2": "Islam",
        "distractor3": "Judaism"
    },
    {
        "question": " Beginning with childhood, all of man s study is centered on one aim alone   to emerge successfully from the three days  examination   and all he has in his mind is what success can bring to him in terms of power, influence, and prestige. ",
        "correct_answer": "civil service system",
        "distractor1": "social welfare system",
        "distractor2": "contemplation of nature",
        "distractor3": "religious practices"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Eightfold Path, the Four Noble Truths, and the concept of nirvana are associated with the religion of",
        "correct_answer": "Buddhism",
        "distractor1": "Islam",
        "distractor2": "Jainism",
        "distractor3": "Shinto"
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which the Vedas, the Bible, and the Koran are similar is that these religious books",
        "correct_answer": "provide guidelines to govern the behavior of believers",
        "distractor1": "deny the existence of a supreme being who rules the universe",
        "distractor2": "encourage strife between segments of believers",
        "distractor3": "support political rebellions to overthrow existing governments"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which values are most closely associated with the fundamental principles of Buddhism?",
        "correct_answer": "practicing nonviolence and giving up worldly desires",
        "distractor1": "competition and financial success",
        "distractor2": "maintaining the caste system and providing education for all people",
        "distractor3": "self-determination and democracy"
    },
    {
        "question": "A belief of animism is that",
        "correct_answer": "spirits of nature inhabit all living and nonliving objects",
        "distractor1": "after death the soul is reborn in another human form",
        "distractor2": "holy wars must be fought to gain entry into heaven",
        "distractor3": "meditation leads followers to nirvana"
    },
    {
        "question": " The Analects :    In his [the leader] personal conduct, he was respectful.",
        "correct_answer": "law",
        "distractor1": "anarchy",
        "distractor2": "trade",
        "distractor3": "architecture"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major impact of Ancient Greece and Rome on Western Civilization was that",
        "correct_answer": "Greek sculpture and Roman architecture were much admired and copied in the 18th and 19th centuries",
        "distractor1": "the Greeks and Romans succeeded in achieving a classless society, which was later copied in Western Europe",
        "distractor2": "Greece and Rome transmitted Islamic philosophy to the areas they conquered",
        "distractor3": "Greek and Latin are still widely spoken in universities throughout the West"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Ancient Romans  most significant contribution to Europe has been in the area of",
        "correct_answer": "law",
        "distractor1": "economics",
        "distractor2": "poetry",
        "distractor3": "drama"
    },
    {
        "question": "An immediate result of the fall of the Roman Empire was",
        "correct_answer": "a period of disorder and weak central government",
        "distractor1": "a renewed interest in education and the arts",
        "distractor2": "an increase in trade and manufacturing",
        "distractor3": "the growth of cities and dominance by the middle class"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Ancient Athenians are credited with",
        "correct_answer": "establishing governments that had democratic elements",
        "distractor1": "inventing and using the wheel",
        "distractor2": "eliminating slavery",
        "distractor3": "inventing the printing press"
    },
    {
        "question": "Both the Ancient Romans and the Ancient Chinese viewed foreigners as barbarians.  This is an example of",
        "correct_answer": "ethnocentrism",
        "distractor1": "cultural diffusion",
        "distractor2": "materialism",
        "distractor3": "imperialism"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major contribution of the Roman Republic to Western European culture was the",
        "correct_answer": "concept of government by laws",
        "distractor1": "belief that political power should be controlled by the military",
        "distractor2": "establishment of agricultural communes",
        "distractor3": "rejection of the concept of slavery"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which ancient civilization established the basis of western democracy?",
        "correct_answer": "Greek",
        "distractor1": "Phoenician",
        "distractor2": "Egyptian",
        "distractor3": "Sumerian"
    },
    {
        "question": "The political system of the Ancient Roman Empire was characterized by",
        "correct_answer": "a strong central government",
        "distractor1": "rule by a coalition of emperors and religious leaders",
        "distractor2": "universal suffrage in national elections",
        "distractor3": "a strict adherence to constitutional principles"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which societal condition was basic to the development of Greek philosophy?",
        "correct_answer": "mass education",
        "distractor1": "rigid social classes",
        "distractor2": "emphasis on individualism",
        "distractor3": "religious uniformity"
    },
    {
        "question": "Important long-term contributions of Ancient Greek and Roman civilizations are primarily found in the area of",
        "correct_answer": "government and law",
        "distractor1": "military technology",
        "distractor2": "religious doctrine",
        "distractor3": "economic policy and planning"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Ancient Greek city-state of Sparta",
        "correct_answer": "was a powerful military state",
        "distractor1": "was primarily concerned with the health of their people",
        "distractor2": "granted universal suffrage to their people",
        "distractor3": "placed great emphasis on literature and the arts"
    },
    {
        "question": "An immediate result of the fall of the Roman Empire was",
        "correct_answer": "a period of disorder and weak central government",
        "distractor1": "a renewed interest in education and the arts",
        "distractor2": "an increase in trade and manufacturing",
        "distractor3": "the growth of cities and dominance by the middle class"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which societal condition was basic to the development of Greek philosophy and Renaissance art?",
        "correct_answer": "emphasis on individualism",
        "distractor1": "rigid social classes",
        "distractor2": "religious uniformity",
        "distractor3": "mass education"
    },
    {
        "question": "An influence that spread from the Byzantine Empire to Early Russia was the",
        "correct_answer": "Orthodox Christian religion",
        "distractor1": "use of the Latin alphabet",
        "distractor2": "beginning of democracy",
        "distractor3": "factory system"
    },
    {
        "question": "The adoption of the Eastern Orthodox religion and the Cyrillic alphabet by the Russian people occurred as a result of",
        "correct_answer": "contact with Byzantine culture in the 10th century",
        "distractor1": "territorial expansion during the reign of Catherine the Great",
        "distractor2": "the westernization policies of Peter the Great",
        "distractor3": "the influence of the Crusaders during the Middle Ages"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between Axum, Kush, and Nubia was that they were",
        "correct_answer": "early civilizations in Africa",
        "distractor1": "military leaders in the Neolithic Age",
        "distractor2": "rivers along which early trade developed",
        "distractor3": "writers of epic poems about Greek cities"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between the decline of the Roman Empire and the fall of the Manchu Dynasty was that both initially led to",
        "correct_answer": "political chaos and decentralization of government",
        "distractor1": "improved economic conditions",
        "distractor2": "democratically elected governments",
        "distractor3": "major accomplishments in art, science, and technology"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major contribution of the Roman Empire to Western society was the development of",
        "correct_answer": "an effective legal system",
        "distractor1": "gunpowder",
        "distractor2": "the principles of revolutionary socialism",
        "distractor3": "monotheism"
    },
    {
        "question": "After the fall of Rome, the eastern portion of the Roman Empire became known as the",
        "correct_answer": "Byzantine Empire",
        "distractor1": "Persian Empire",
        "distractor2": "Mongol Empire",
        "distractor3": "Gupta Empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which conclusion can be drawn from a study of the early civilizations of Axum, Kush, Mali and Songhai?",
        "correct_answer": "these societies had a long and rich history before their first contact with Europeans",
        "distractor1": "these African societies flourished at the same time",
        "distractor2": "farming was more extensive in the Nile River Valley than it was in the Fertile Crescent",
        "distractor3": "the Neolithic Revolution occurred in Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major effect of the decline of the Roman Empire was that Western Europe",
        "correct_answer": "entered a period of chaos and disorder",
        "distractor1": "came under the control of the Muslims",
        "distractor2": "was absorbed by the Byzantine Empire",
        "distractor3": "returned to a republican form of government"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which characteristic was common to the Golden Age of Greece and the Italian Renaissance?",
        "correct_answer": "prosperity led to the creation of many works of art",
        "distractor1": "a strong military led to national unity",
        "distractor2": "written constitutions led to the establishment of democratic governments",
        "distractor3": "political instability led directly to the formation of unified nation-states"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the centuries of dynastic rule, the Chinese rejected other cultures as inferior to their own.  This situation illustrates the concept of",
        "correct_answer": "ethnocentrism",
        "distractor1": "imperialism",
        "distractor2": "social mobility",
        "distractor3": "cultural diffusion"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alexander the Great s conquests of Greece, Asia Minor, Egypt, and Persia led to the",
        "correct_answer": "spread of Hellenic culture",
        "distractor1": "adoption of a feudal system",
        "distractor2": "establishment of representative democracy",
        "distractor3": "spread of Islamic culture throughout Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between the Ancient African kingdoms of Egypt, Ghana, Mali and Songhai is that all of these kingdoms were located",
        "correct_answer": "on major trading routes",
        "distractor1": "in mountainous terrain",
        "distractor2": "in coastal areas",
        "distractor3": "in rain forest areas"
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason the ancient kingdoms in western Africa prospered was that they",
        "correct_answer": "developed extensive trade in gold, ivory, and salt",
        "distractor1": "were located along the Tigris and Euphrates rivers",
        "distractor2": "had no contact with the rest of the world",
        "distractor3": "followed the Hindu beliefs of their rulers"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mansa Musa s journey to Mecca in the 1300 s is evidence that",
        "correct_answer": "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire",
        "distractor1": "the Crusades had a great influence on western Africa",
        "distractor2": "most African leaders were educated in the Middle East",
        "distractor3": "European culture was superior to the cultures of western Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "The contributions of the ancient civilizations of Ghana, Axum, Kush, and Mali demonstrate that",
        "correct_answer": "advanced societies developed in Africa before Europeans colonized this region",
        "distractor1": "industrial technology was needed for African civilizations to develop",
        "distractor2": "many African civilizations developed in southern Africa",
        "distractor3": "most of the African Continent was unified under a single political system"
    },
    {
        "question": "A similarity between the ancient western African kingdoms of Mali, Ghana, and Songhai is that these kingdoms ",
        "correct_answer": "established economies based on trade",
        "distractor1": "limited the power of their rulers",
        "distractor2": "practiced Christianity",
        "distractor3": "isolated themselves from contact with other cultures"
    },
    {
        "question": " Western Europe owed a debt of gratitude to the Empire that for almost a thousand years ensured the survival of Christianity during a time when Europe was too weak to accomplish the task. ",
        "correct_answer": "Byzantine",
        "distractor1": "Hellenistic",
        "distractor2": "Mongol",
        "distractor3": "Ottoman"
    },
    {
        "question": "An influence that spread from the Byzantine Empire to Early Russia was the",
        "correct_answer": "Orthodox Christian religion",
        "distractor1": "use of the Latin alphabet",
        "distractor2": "beginning of democracy",
        "distractor3": "factory system"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which empire introduced the Eastern Orthodox Church and the Cyrillic alphabet to Russia? ",
        "correct_answer": "Byzantine",
        "distractor1": "Mongol",
        "distractor2": "British",
        "distractor3": "Gupta"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major feature of the Golden Age of Moslem culture was the",
        "correct_answer": "development of the foundations of modern science and mathematics",
        "distractor1": "political and economic isolation of the Arab world",
        "distractor2": "adoption of democratic government",
        "distractor3": "persecution of Jews and Christians"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor helps explain the scientific and literary achievements of the Muslims during their Golden Age (A.D. 800-1300)?",
        "correct_answer": "cultural diversity accepted by many Islamic governments",
        "distractor1": "expansion of trans-Atlantic trade",
        "distractor2": "innovations introduced by the Europeans during the Renaissance",
        "distractor3": "legal equality of all people in the Islamic empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mansa Musa s journey to Mecca in the 1300 s is evidence that",
        "correct_answer": "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire",
        "distractor1": "the Crusades had a great influence on western Africa",
        "distractor2": "most African leaders were educated in the Middle East",
        "distractor3": "European culture was superior to the cultures of western Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which activity occurred during the Golden Age of Muslim culture?",
        "correct_answer": "major discoveries in mathematics and science",
        "distractor1": "destruction of books containing Greek and Roman ideas",
        "distractor2": "beginning of pilgrimages to Mecca",
        "distractor3": "opposition to freedom of thought and to foreign ideas by rulers"
    },
    {
        "question": "The contributions of the Golden Age of Islamic civilization include",
        "correct_answer": "advances in mathematics",
        "distractor1": "irrigation systems",
        "distractor2": "polytheistic beliefs",
        "distractor3": "gunpowder and guns"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Europe during the Middle Ages, increases in trade and commerce resulted in",
        "correct_answer": "development of towns and cities",
        "distractor1": "lower living standards for industrial workers",
        "distractor2": "decreased economic rivalry between kings",
        "distractor3": "increased political power for the clergy"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Middle Ages, Europeans did not eat potatoes or corn because these vegetables",
        "correct_answer": "had not yet been introduced to Europe from the New World",
        "distractor1": "were forbidden by the Catholic Church for religious reasons",
        "distractor2": "were believed to be poisonous",
        "distractor3": "were too expensive to import from China"
    },
    {
        "question": " All things were under its domain...its power was such that no one could hope to escape its scrutiny. ",
        "correct_answer": "the Church",
        "distractor1": "the Guild",
        "distractor2": "Knighthood",
        "distractor3": "the nation-state"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Middle Ages in Western Europe was characterized by",
        "correct_answer": "the manor system and the importance of land ownership",
        "distractor1": "absolute monarchies and strong central governments",
        "distractor2": "decreased emphasis on religion in daily life",
        "distractor3": "extensive trade with Asia and the Middle East"
    },
    {
        "question": "Feudal societies are generally characterized by",
        "correct_answer": "an emphasis on social order",
        "distractor1": "a representative government",
        "distractor2": "many economic opportunities",
        "distractor3": "the protection of political rights"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Europe, a long-term effect of the Crusades was",
        "correct_answer": "an increased demand for goods from the East",
        "distractor1": "the strengthening of the feudal system",
        "distractor2": "the adoption of Islamic religious practices",
        "distractor3": "increased European isolation"
    },
    {
        "question": "The art, music, and philosophy of the medieval period in Europe generally dealt with",
        "correct_answer": "religious themes",
        "distractor1": "human scientific achievements",
        "distractor2": "materialism",
        "distractor3": "classic Greek and Roman subjects"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the result of the Crusades?",
        "correct_answer": "trade between Europe and the Middle East was expanded",
        "distractor1": "Europeans maintained a lasting control over much of the Middle East",
        "distractor2": "Islamic influence dominated Europe",
        "distractor3": "Europeans developed tolerance of Non-Christian religions"
    },
    {
        "question": "What were two indirect results of the Crusades?",
        "correct_answer": "trade and commerce increased and the feudal system was weakened",
        "distractor1": "trade and commerce increased and the feudal system was strengthened",
        "distractor2": "trade and commerce declined and the feudal system was strengthened",
        "distractor3": "trade and commerce declined and the feudal system was weakened"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Europe during the Middle Ages, the force that provided unification and stability was the",
        "correct_answer": "Roman Catholic Church",
        "distractor1": "central government in Rome",
        "distractor2": "military alliance between France and Germany",
        "distractor3": "federation of the craft guilds"
    },
    {
        "question": "Feudalism in Western Europe was similar to feudalism in Japan in that",
        "correct_answer": "power was based on class relationships",
        "distractor1": "equality among the social classes",
        "distractor2": "direct democracy",
        "distractor3": "monotheism"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is a characteristic of a feudal society?",
        "correct_answer": "rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "rapid social change",
        "distractor2": "high literacy rate",
        "distractor3": "industrial-based economy"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Europe, the Crusades resulted in",
        "correct_answer": "an increased demand for goods from the Middle East and Asia",
        "distractor1": "greater isolation of the region from the world",
        "distractor2": "the adoption of Islam as the official religion of many European nations",
        "distractor3": "the strengthening of the feudal system"
    },
    {
        "question": "One important effect of the Crusades on Western Europe was that they",
        "correct_answer": "furthered cultural diffusion throughout Western Europe",
        "distractor1": "led to a decline in the importance of the church in Western Europe",
        "distractor2": "introduced the Industrial Revolution to Western Europe",
        "distractor3": "ended the western European quest for an overseas empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "In European feudal society, an individual s social status was generally determined by",
        "correct_answer": "birth",
        "distractor1": "education and training",
        "distractor2": "individual abilities",
        "distractor3": "marriage"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which economic system existed in Europe during the early Middle Ages?",
        "correct_answer": "manorialism",
        "distractor1": "free market",
        "distractor2": "socialism",
        "distractor3": "command"
    },
    {
        "question": "One major result of the Crusades was the",
        "correct_answer": "spread of Middle Eastern culture and technology to Europe",
        "distractor1": "permanent occupation of the Holy Land by the Europeans",
        "distractor2": "long-term decrease in European trade",
        "distractor3": "conversion of most Muslims to Christianity"
    },
    {
        "question": "The growth of feudalism in Europe during the Middle Ages was primarily caused by the",
        "correct_answer": "collapse of a strong central government",
        "distractor1": "rivalry between the colonial empires",
        "distractor2": "suppression of internationalism",
        "distractor3": "decline of the Roman Catholic Church"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Crusades have been called  history s most successful failures.     Which statement best explains this expression?",
        "correct_answer": "The Crusades did not achieve their original goals, but they brought about many desirable changes in Europe.",
        "distractor1": "Although the Crusaders captured the Holy Land, they were unable to bring about democratic reforms.",
        "distractor2": "The Crusades helped bring about the fall of the Roman Empire",
        "distractor3": "The Crusaders prevented the Turks from capturing Constantinople for many centuries"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Roman Catholic Church during the Middle Ages in Europe can best be described as a church that",
        "correct_answer": "was a stabilizing influence during a period of weak central governments",
        "distractor1": "favored separation from secular governments",
        "distractor2": "avoided involvement in social and educational matters",
        "distractor3": "was a strong force that divided many people"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major goal of the Christian Church during the Crusades (1096 1291) was to",
        "correct_answer": "capture the Holy Land from Islamic rulers",
        "distractor1": "establish Christianity in western Europe",
        "distractor2": "unite warring Arab peoples",
        "distractor3": "strengthen English dominance in the Arab world"
    },
    {
        "question": "Korea greatly influenced the development of early Japan by",
        "correct_answer": "acting as a bridge for ideas from China",
        "distractor1": "providing Japan with the technology for industrialization",
        "distractor2": "serving as a barrier against Chinese aggression",
        "distractor3": "protecting Japan from early European exploration"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Japan between 1603 and 1868, the most notable action taken by the Tokugawa Shogunate was the",
        "correct_answer": "virtual isolation of the country from the outside world",
        "distractor1": "military conquest of China",
        "distractor2": "development of extensive trade with the Americas",
        "distractor3": "formation of cultural links with Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "The code of bushido of the Japanese samurai is most similar to",
        "correct_answer": "practice of chivalry by European knights",
        "distractor1": "belief in reincarnation and karma of Hindus",
        "distractor2": "teachings of Judaism",
        "distractor3": "theory of natural rights of the Enlightenment writers"
    },
    {
        "question": "Feudal societies are generally characterized by",
        "correct_answer": "an emphasis on social order",
        "distractor1": "a representative government",
        "distractor2": "many economic opportunities",
        "distractor3": "the protection of political rights"
    },
    {
        "question": "Feudalism in Western Europe was similar to feudalism in Japan in that",
        "correct_answer": "power was based on class relationships",
        "distractor1": "equality among the social classes",
        "distractor2": "direct democracy",
        "distractor3": "monotheism"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is a characteristic of a feudal society?",
        "correct_answer": "rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "rapid social change",
        "distractor2": "high literacy rate",
        "distractor3": "industrial-based economy"
    },
    {
        "question": "The diagram illustrates the social structure of feudal Japan.",
        "correct_answer": "a well-defined class system",
        "distractor1": "a classless society",
        "distractor2": "a growing middle class",
        "distractor3": "high social mobility"
    },
    {
        "question": "A valid generalization about early Japanese culture is that Japan",
        "correct_answer": "maintained a uniquely individual culture while borrowing much from other cultures",
        "distractor1": "had a strong influence on the development of culture in Korea",
        "distractor2": "spread Shinto throughout Asia",
        "distractor3": "imported almost all of its cultural ideas from China, resulting in nearly identical cultures"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Mongols played a significant role in Russian history by",
        "correct_answer": "isolating Russia from Western Europe during the early Renaissance",
        "distractor1": "supporting Czar Nicholas II during the Russian Revolution",
        "distractor2": "supporting the rule of Ivan the Terrible",
        "distractor3": "ending the reign of Catherine the Great"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Europe, a major characteristic of humanism was",
        "correct_answer": "an appreciation for the basic worth of individual achievement",
        "distractor1": "a belief in the supremacy of the state in relation to individual rights",
        "distractor2": "a rejection of ancient civilizations and their cultures",
        "distractor3": "an emphasis on social control and obedience to national rulers"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes a characteristic of the Renaissance in Europe?",
        "correct_answer": "creativity in the arts was encouraged",
        "distractor1": "the social structure became very rigid",
        "distractor2": "the political structure was similar to that of the Roman Empire",
        "distractor3": "humanism decreased in importance"
    },
    {
        "question": "  Europe is waking out of a long, deep sleep time was when learning was only found in the religious orders learning has passed to secular princes and peers.  ",
        "correct_answer": "Renaissance",
        "distractor1": "decline of the Roman Empire",
        "distractor2": "Crusades",
        "distractor3": "rise of Christianity"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a major characteristic of the Renaissance?",
        "correct_answer": "humanism",
        "distractor1": "conformity",
        "distractor2": "mysticism",
        "distractor3": "obedience"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement describes a direct effect of the Renaissance on Western Europe?",
        "correct_answer": "the philosophy of humanism brought about a decrease in the power of the Roman Catholic Church",
        "distractor1": "art began to reflect an increased emphasis on religious themes",
        "distractor2": "nationalistic movements among the minority ethnic groups in the region declines",
        "distractor3": "the feudal system was developed to provide stability in a decentralized political structure"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Renaissance and the Protestant Reformation were similar in that both were",
        "correct_answer": "stimulated by a spirit of inquiry",
        "distractor1": "supported by the working class",
        "distractor2": "limited to Italy, France, and Germany",
        "distractor3": "encouraged by the successes of the French Revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes a change that occurred during both the Renaissance and the Enlightenment?",
        "correct_answer": "a new questioning spirit and attitude emerged",
        "distractor1": "feudalism became the dominant political system",
        "distractor2": "the use of reason and logic were discouraged",
        "distractor3": "technology and science were considered unimportant"
    },
    {
        "question": "One factor that enabled the Renaissance to flourish in Northern Italy was that the region had",
        "correct_answer": "a wealthy class that invested in the arts",
        "distractor1": "a socialist for of government",
        "distractor2": "limited contact with the Byzantine Empire",
        "distractor3": "a shrinking middle class"
    },
    {
        "question": "European society during the Renaissance differed from European society during the Middle Ages in that during the Renaissance",
        "correct_answer": "the emphasis on individual worth increased",
        "distractor1": "the Church was no longer influential",
        "distractor2": "economic activity declined",
        "distractor3": "art no longer contained religious themes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which societal condition was basic to the development of Greek philosophy and Renaissance art?",
        "correct_answer": "emphasis on individualism",
        "distractor1": "rigid social classes",
        "distractor2": "religious uniformity",
        "distractor3": "mass education"
    },
    {
        "question": "The humanists of the Renaissance differed from the traditional medieval philosophers in the humanists ",
        "correct_answer": "emphasis on the importance of the individual",
        "distractor1": "interest in the spiritual life of people",
        "distractor2": "lack of interest in Ancient Greek and Roman culture",
        "distractor3": "rejection of Christian principles"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which characteristic was common to the Golden Age of Greece and the Italian Renaissance?",
        "correct_answer": "prosperity led to the creation of many works of art",
        "distractor1": "a strong military led to national unity",
        "distractor2": "written constitutions led to the establishment of democratic governments",
        "distractor3": "political instability led directly to the formation of unified nation-states"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which idea about leadership would Niccolo Machiavelli most likely support?",
        "correct_answer": "leaders should do whatever is necessary to achieve their goals",
        "distractor1": "leaders should fight against discrimination and intolerance",
        "distractor2": "leaders should listen to the desires of the people",
        "distractor3": "elected leaders should be fair and good"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Renaissance period, which factor was emphasized by the philosophy of humanism?",
        "correct_answer": "value of the individual",
        "distractor1": "superiority of medieval thought",
        "distractor2": "devotion to religion",
        "distractor3": "obedience to government officials"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement concerning the Renaissance in Europe is based on opinion rather than on fact?",
        "correct_answer": "The art of the Northern Renaissance was superior to that of the Italian Renaissance.",
        "distractor1": "Literature began to appear in languages other than Latin.",
        "distractor2": "Art reflected the ideas of humanism and individualism.",
        "distractor3": "Art produced during the Renaissance had religious as well as secular themes."
    },
    {
        "question": "Martin Luther s Ninety-Five Theses were a call for",
        "correct_answer": "reforms within the Roman Catholic Church",
        "distractor1": "religious revolt against the German princes",
        "distractor2": "greater papal authority",
        "distractor3": "crusades to spread Christianity"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Western Europe, a major immediate effect of the Reformation was a",
        "correct_answer": "decline in religious unity and in the power of the Catholic Church",
        "distractor1": "renewed domination of the Catholic Church over the German states",
        "distractor2": "greater tolerance of religions other than Christianity",
        "distractor3": "decrease in educational opportunities for the middle class"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Renaissance, which development contributed most to the Protestant Reformation?",
        "correct_answer": "questioning of traditional authority",
        "distractor1": "interest in Ancient Greece and Rome",
        "distractor2": "advances in mathematics and science",
        "distractor3": "attention to realism and detail"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a result of the Protestant Reformation in Europe?",
        "correct_answer": "the power of the Catholic Church in Europe was weakened",
        "distractor1": "the Catholic Church accepted the dominance of the new Protestant religions in Italy, France, and Germany",
        "distractor2": "Spain became a predominately Protestant nation",
        "distractor3": "Catholic Church leaders refused to make any changes in church practices"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a major result of the Reformation?",
        "correct_answer": "new Christian denominations emerged",
        "distractor1": "religious teachings were no longer allowed in the universities",
        "distractor2": "the Crusades were organized",
        "distractor3": "the power of the Pope was strengthened"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor helped most to bring about the Protestant Reformation?",
        "correct_answer": "kings and princes in Northern Europe resented the power of the Catholic Church",
        "distractor1": "the Catholic clergy had lost faith in their religion",
        "distractor2": "Islam was attracting many converts in Western Europe",
        "distractor3": "the exploration of the Americas led to the introduction of new religious ideas"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Protestant Reformation and the European Renaissance were similar in that both",
        "correct_answer": "encouraged people to question tradition",
        "distractor1": "discouraged the growth of strong monarchs",
        "distractor2": "were led by the military",
        "distractor3": "supported the return of the Roman Empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Protestant Reformation represents a turning point in European history because it",
        "correct_answer": "ended religious unity in Western Europe",
        "distractor1": "allowed religious reformers to escape persecution",
        "distractor2": "standardized all religious writings",
        "distractor3": "forced most of Europe s monarchs to become Protestants"
    },
    {
        "question": " Christians should be taught that he who gives to a poor man or lends to a needy man does better than if he used the money to buy an indulgence. ",
        "correct_answer": "Protestant Reformation",
        "distractor1": "Commercial Revolution",
        "distractor2": "Industrial Revolution",
        "distractor3": "Renaissance"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Renaissance and the Protestant Reformation were similar in that both were",
        "correct_answer": "stimulated by a spirit of inquiry",
        "distractor1": "supported by the working class",
        "distractor2": "limited to Italy, France, and Germany",
        "distractor3": "encouraged by the successes of the French Revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "One major influence the Renaissance had on the Protestant Reformation was that the philosophers of the Renaissance",
        "correct_answer": "encouraged a questioning attitude",
        "distractor1": "supported democratic forms of government",
        "distractor2": "stressed the importance of life after death",
        "distractor3": "denied the existence of God"
    },
    {
        "question": " Unless I am convinced by Scripture and plain reason... my conscience is captive to the Word of God. I cannot and I will hot recant anything, for to go against conscience is neither right nor safe. Here I stand, I cannot do otherwise.    Martin Luther, Diet of Worms (1517)   ",
        "correct_answer": "the supremacy of the Bible over Church policies",
        "distractor1": "imprisoning those who disagreed with Church teachings",
        "distractor2": "maintaining the unity of the Church",
        "distractor3": "the need for nepotism"
    },
    {
        "question": "Martin Luther s posting of the Ninety-Five Theses is considered by many to be a turning point in history because ",
        "correct_answer": "the power of the Roman Catholic Church was lessened and royal power grew",
        "distractor1": "the Pope s right to sell indulgences was strengthened",
        "distractor2": "Luther soon became the leader of Germany",
        "distractor3": "the Roman Catholic Church unified the German states"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Spain, an effect of the Inquisition during the 16th century was to",
        "correct_answer": "prevent the introduction of Protestant religions",
        "distractor1": "reintroduce Moorish culture to the Iberian Peninsula",
        "distractor2": "encourage the development of the Industrial Revolution",
        "distractor3": "implement the ideas of the Renaissance in major cities"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Latin America, the Maya and the Aztec civilizations were similar in that they",
        "correct_answer": "developed complex mathematical and calendar systems",
        "distractor1": "showed little evidence of urbanization",
        "distractor2": "lacked a strong central government",
        "distractor3": "used military weapons superior to those of Europeans"
    },
    {
        "question": "A study of Mayas, Aztecs, and Incas would show that these ancient American civilizations",
        "correct_answer": "rivaled the accomplishments of early Middle Eastern cultures",
        "distractor1": "produced few cultural achievements",
        "distractor2": "lived at peace with their neighbors",
        "distractor3": "welcomed the new technology brought by European explorers"
    },
    {
        "question": "A study of the Maya, Aztec, and Inca civilizations of Latin America would show that these civilizations",
        "correct_answer": "developed advanced and complex societies before the arrival of the Europeans",
        "distractor1": "established extensive trade with Pacific Rim nations",
        "distractor2": "were strongly influenced by their contact with Asian and African civilizations",
        "distractor3": "were relatively large, but not well organized"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a result of the Commercial Revolution",
        "correct_answer": "expansion of European influence overseas",
        "distractor1": "decline in population growth in Europe",
        "distractor2": "shift of power from Western Europe to Eastern Europe",
        "distractor3": "spread of feudalism throughout Western Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was an immediate result of the European Age of Exploration?",
        "correct_answer": "European influence spread to the Western hemisphere",
        "distractor1": "Islamic culture spread across Africa and Asia",
        "distractor2": "independence movements developed in Asia and Africa",
        "distractor3": "military dictatorships were established throughout Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major result of the Age of Exploration was",
        "correct_answer": "the end of regional isolation and the beginning of a period of European global domination",
        "distractor1": "a long period of peace and prosperity for the nations of Western Europe",
        "distractor2": "extensive migration of people from the Western Hemisphere to Europe and Asia",
        "distractor3": "the fall of European national monarchies and the end of the power of the Catholic Church"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Commercial Revolution in Western Europe led directly to the",
        "correct_answer": "expansion of world trade",
        "distractor1": "development of a socialist economy",
        "distractor2": "establishment of the Guild System",
        "distractor3": "weakening of the power of the middle class"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which system developed as a result of the Commercial Revolution",
        "correct_answer": "market economy",
        "distractor1": "manorialism",
        "distractor2": "communism",
        "distractor3": "bartering"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these events during the Age of Exploration was a cause of the other three?",
        "correct_answer": "advances in learning and technology made long ocean voyages possible",
        "distractor1": "Europeans brought food, animals, and ideas from one continent to another",
        "distractor2": "European diseases had an adverse effect on the native populations of new territories",
        "distractor3": "warfare increased as European nations competed for land and power"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Native American population of Mexico in 1492 has been estimated at 25 million; the population in 1608 has been estimated at 1.7 million.  This decrease in population was mainly a result of",
        "correct_answer": "diseases introduced by the Spanish",
        "distractor1": "crop failures brought on by poor weather conditions",
        "distractor2": "emigration of Native Americans to Europe and Africa",
        "distractor3": "wars between various native groups"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Latin America during the early period of Spanish colonialism, the deaths of large numbers of the native people led to",
        "correct_answer": "the importation of slaves from Africa",
        "distractor1": "a decline in Spanish immigration to the Americas",
        "distractor2": "the removal of most Spanish troops from the Americas",
        "distractor3": "improved health care in the colonies"
    },
    {
        "question": "Both Japan and China decided to limit trade with Europe during much of the 16th and 17th centuries because the Japanese and the Chinese",
        "correct_answer": "believed they would receive no benefit from increased contact with the Europeans",
        "distractor1": "had few products to sell to the Europeans",
        "distractor2": "held religious beliefs that prohibited contact with foreigners",
        "distractor3": "thought European technology would hinder any effort to modernize"
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason the Spanish conquistadors were able to conquer the Aztec and Inca Empires rapid is that",
        "correct_answer": "the Spanish had better weapons than the Aztecs and Incas did",
        "distractor1": "these empires had no standing armies",
        "distractor2": "the Spanish greatly outnumbered the Aztecs and Incas",
        "distractor3": "the Aztecs and Incas joined together to fight the Spanish"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which conclusion can be drawn from a study of the early civilizations of Axum, Kush, Mali and Songhai?",
        "correct_answer": "these societies had a long and rich history before their first contact with Europeans",
        "distractor1": "these African societies flourished at the same time",
        "distractor2": "farming was more extensive in the Nile River Valley than it was in the Fertile Crescent",
        "distractor3": "the Neolithic Revolution occurred in Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a characteristic of the policy of mercantilism followed by Spanish colonial rulers in Latin America?",
        "correct_answer": "the colonies were required to provide raw materials to Spain and to purchase Spanish manufactured goods",
        "distractor1": "the colonies were forced to develop local industries to support themselves",
        "distractor2": "Spain sought trade agreements between its colonies and the English colonies in North America",
        "distractor3": "Spain encouraged the colonies to develop new political systems to meet colonial needs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes a result of the scarcity of native Indian labor in Latin America during the colonial period?",
        "correct_answer": "large numbers of African slaves were imported",
        "distractor1": "unskilled laborers were imported from Asia",
        "distractor2": "many people from Spain and Portugal immigrated to the region",
        "distractor3": "Native American Indians from the British colonies went south to work"
    },
    {
        "question": "The influence of African culture on some areas of Latin America was largely a result of the",
        "correct_answer": "Atlantic slave trade",
        "distractor1": "American Revolution",
        "distractor2": "building of the Panama Canal",
        "distractor3": "success of Communist Revolutions"
    },
    {
        "question": "In many Latin American nations, a major effect of colonial rule has been the",
        "correct_answer": "concentration of power in a small group of landowners",
        "distractor1": "minor political role of the military",
        "distractor2": "equal distribution of wealth among social classes",
        "distractor3": "economic control held by the Indian population"
    },
    {
        "question": "Spain s colonial policy of mercantilism affected the development of Latin American nations by promoting",
        "correct_answer": "the production of raw material and cash crops",
        "distractor1": "free and rapid trade with Asia and Africa",
        "distractor2": "respect for the rights of indigenous people",
        "distractor3": "isolationism as a response to international political issues"
    },
    {
        "question": "One result of the European conquest of Latin America was that in Latin America",
        "correct_answer": "Spanish became the major spoken language",
        "distractor1": "Native American cultures flourished",
        "distractor2": "the Aztec religion spread",
        "distractor3": "many parliamentary democracies were established"
    },
    {
        "question": "In colonial Latin America, the main purpose of the encomienda system was to",
        "correct_answer": "provide a steady labor supply for early colonists",
        "distractor1": "insure that the Indians were humanely treated",
        "distractor2": "prevent slaver in Spain s New World colonies",
        "distractor3": "build and maintain forts to repel foreign invaders"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to the theory of mercantilism, colonies should be",
        "correct_answer": "acquired as markets and sources of raw materials",
        "distractor1": "considered an economic burden for the colonial power",
        "distractor2": "grated independence as soon as possible",
        "distractor3": "encouraged to develop their own industries"
    },
    {
        "question": " He once sent fifty horsemen with pikes (spears) to destroy an entire province.  Not a single human being survived that massacre, neither women nor children nor aged infirm This terrible massacre was punishment for a trifling offense: some Indians had not responded to a summons promptly enough when the tyrant had commanded that they bring him a load of maize (corn) , or else had asked for more Indians to be assigned to serve him or his comrades.  And there was no place where the Indians could take refuge  ",
        "correct_answer": "encourage the colonial government to change its policies toward native peoples",
        "distractor1": "explain the problems associated with using native laborers",
        "distractor2": "justify the need for the harsh treatment of the native people",
        "distractor3": "show support for the governor s policy toward native peoples"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Treaty of Tordesillas (1494), concerning Latin America, and the Berlin Conference (1884-1885), concerning Africa, were similar in that each agreement",
        "correct_answer": "divided each area into European-controlled segments",
        "distractor1": "provided for self-government by the native peoples",
        "distractor2": "declared that in these areas monarchs rule by divine right",
        "distractor3": "suppressed revolts by native peoples against European imperialists"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best illustrates the contradictory actions of the Catholic Church in colonial Latin America?",
        "correct_answer": "the Church expressed concern over the mistreatment of Native Americans, but supported the encomienda system",
        "distractor1": "the Jesuits destroyed the temples of the Native Americans, but allowed them to continue their religious rituals",
        "distractor2": "the Church moved many Native Americas from Spanish territory to Portuguese territory, but encouraged the importation of African slaves",
        "distractor3": "the Pope endorsed the Treaty of Tordesillas, but outlawed further exploration"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Crusades indirectly contributed to the discovery of the New World by",
        "correct_answer": "stimulating European demand for goods from the East",
        "distractor1": "forcing the religious conversion of the Muslim population",
        "distractor2": "forcing the Turks to flee from Constantinople",
        "distractor3": "increasing the power of the feudal lords"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 1600 s, the interest of Europeans in Africa was based mainly on Europe s need to",
        "correct_answer": "obtain workers for its colonies in the Americas",
        "distractor1": "market its surplus agricultural products",
        "distractor2": "establish collective security arrangements",
        "distractor3": "settle its surplus population on new lands"
    },
    {
        "question": "The printing press, the astrolabe, and the Mercator projection were technological advances that contributed to the",
        "correct_answer": "exploration and overseas expansion of the colonial empires",
        "distractor1": "unification of Germany and Italy in the late 1800 s",
        "distractor2": "growth of industry in Latin America during the late 1900 s",
        "distractor3": "spread of Islam in the 700 s and 800 s"
    },
    {
        "question": "Peter the Great and Catherine the Great changed Russia by",
        "correct_answer": "introducing western ideas and customs",
        "distractor1": "abolishing all social class distinctions",
        "distractor2": "becoming constitutional monarchs",
        "distractor3": "preventing wars with neighboring nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Changes in Russia under Peter the Great were most similar to changes that occurred in",
        "correct_answer": "Japan during the Meiji Restoration",
        "distractor1": "China before the Opium War",
        "distractor2": "Iran after the fall of Shah Pahlevi",
        "distractor3": "France during the feudal period"
    },
    {
        "question": "Westernization in Russia came about largely through the",
        "correct_answer": "efforts of Peter the Great and his successors",
        "distractor1": "invasion of Russia by Sweden",
        "distractor2": "desire of the United States to seek new markets",
        "distractor3": "acceptance of the policies of the Eastern Orthodox Church"
    },
    {
        "question": " God hath power to create or destroy, make or unmake, at his pleasure; to give life or send death; to judge and to be judged (by) none And the like power have kings;  ",
        "correct_answer": "theory of divine right",
        "distractor1": "enlightened despotism",
        "distractor2": "Social Darwinism",
        "distractor3": "constitutional monarchy"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which type of government is shown in the cartoon?",
        "correct_answer": "an absolute monarchy",
        "distractor1": "a socialist republic",
        "distractor2": "a communist dictatorship",
        "distractor3": "a democracy"
    },
    {
        "question": " . . .The person of the King is sacred, and to attack him in any way is an attack on religion itself. Kings represent the divine majesty and have been appointed by Him to carry out His purposes. Serving God and respecting kings are bound together.    Bishop Jacques Bossuet   ",
        "correct_answer": "Age of Absolutism",
        "distractor1": "existed during the",
        "distractor2": "Renaissance",
        "distractor3": "Industrial Revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": " . . .The person of the King is sacred, and to attack him in any way is an attack on religion itself. Kings represent the divine majesty and have been appointed by Him to carry out His purposes. Serving God and respecting kings are bound together.    Bishop Jacques Bossuet   ",
        "correct_answer": "Louis XIV",
        "distractor1": "John Locke",
        "distractor2": "Karl Marx",
        "distractor3": "Elizabeth II"
    },
    {
        "question": "Francis Bacon, Galileo, and Isaac Newton promoted the idea that knowledge should be based on",
        "correct_answer": "experimentation and observation",
        "distractor1": "the experiences of past civilizations",
        "distractor2": "emotions and feelings",
        "distractor3": "the teachings of the Catholic Church"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Scientific Revolution and the Enlightenment, one similarity in the work of many scientists and philosophers was that they",
        "correct_answer": "examined natural laws governing the universe",
        "distractor1": "relied heavily on the ideas of medieval thinkers",
        "distractor2": "favored an absolute monarchy as a way of improving economic conditions",
        "distractor3": "received support from the Catholic Church"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the effects of the works of Nicolaus Copernicus, Galileo Galilei, Sir",
        "correct_answer": "The scientific method was used to solve problems.",
        "distractor1": "The acceptance of traditional authority was strengthened.",
        "distractor2": "Funding to education was increased by the English government.",
        "distractor3": "Interest in Greek and Roman drama was renewed."
    },
    {
        "question": "  Speaker A  : Good government stresses the importance of the nation and accepts the rights of the individual only if the interests of the individual are the same as those of the nation.",
        "correct_answer": "C",
        "distractor1": "A",
        "distractor2": "B",
        "distractor3": "D"
    },
    {
        "question": "  Speaker A  :  The story of history is the story of class struggles.  Revolution is necessary to overthrow the ruling class and eventually create a classless society in which no one will be exploited.",
        "correct_answer": "D",
        "distractor1": "A",
        "distractor2": "B",
        "distractor3": "C"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is a valid generalization about the immediate results of the French Revolution of 1789?",
        "correct_answer": "the French middle class gained more power",
        "distractor1": "the Roman Catholic Church increased its power and wealth",
        "distractor2": "the revolution achieved its goal of establishing peace, democracy, and justice for all",
        "distractor3": "the revolution had little impact outside France"
    },
    {
        "question": "In France, which was a major result of the French Revolution?",
        "correct_answer": "the middle class gained political influence",
        "distractor1": "the king was restored to unlimited power",
        "distractor2": "the clergy dominated government",
        "distractor3": "the tax burden was carried by the lower class"
    },
    {
        "question": "A study of revolutions would most likely lead to the conclusion that pre-Revolutionary governments",
        "correct_answer": "fail to meet the political and economic needs of their people",
        "distractor1": "are more concerned about human rights than the governments that replace them",
        "distractor2": "refuse to modernize their armed forces with advanced technology",
        "distractor3": "attempt to bring about the separation of government from religion"
    },
    {
        "question": " Congress of Vienna Restores Monarchy to France    Czar Nicholas I Limits Freedom of the Russian Press  ",
        "correct_answer": "reactions to the French Revolution",
        "distractor1": "movements to unify all of western Europe",
        "distractor2": "efforts to improve the conditions of factory workers",
        "distractor3": "attempts to promote trade between European nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "The French people supported Napoleon Bonaparte because they hoped he would ",
        "correct_answer": "provide stability for the nation",
        "distractor1": "adopt the ideas of the Protestant Reformation",
        "distractor2": "restore Louis XVI to power",
        "distractor3": "end British control of France"
    },
    {
        "question": "Simon Bolivar and Miguel Hidalgo, leaders of Latin American independence movements, were inspired by successful revolutions in",
        "correct_answer": "the Untied States and France",
        "distractor1": "the Soviet Union and China",
        "distractor2": "Cuba and Costa Rica",
        "distractor3": "Egypt and Kenya"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the early 1800 s, which was a major influence on the struggle for political independence in Latin America?",
        "correct_answer": "the American and French Revolutions",
        "distractor1": "poor conditions in urban centers in Latin America",
        "distractor2": "the desire of the Roman Catholic Church in Latin America to escape European control",
        "distractor3": "demands by Latin American workers to own their own factories"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity in the leadership of Latin Americas Jose de San Martin, Toussaint l Ouverture, Bernanrdo O Higgins, and Pedro I was that each leader",
        "correct_answer": "led a struggle to gain freedom for the people of his nation",
        "distractor1": "opposed United States intervention in Haiti",
        "distractor2": "opposed membership of his nation in the League of Nations",
        "distractor3": "established an absolute monarchy in his nation"
    },
    {
        "question": " I will never allow my hands to be idle nor my soul to rest until I have broken the chains laid upon us by Spain. ",
        "correct_answer": "a Latin American nationalist",
        "distractor1": "a Portuguese explorer",
        "distractor2": "a Roman Catholic bishop",
        "distractor3": "a Spanish conquistador"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these situations was the direct result of the other three?",
        "correct_answer": "nations of Latin America won independence",
        "distractor1": "revolutions occurred in North America and France",
        "distractor2": "the Napoleonic wars weakened Spain s power",
        "distractor3": "creoles and mestizos became discontented with Spanish rule"
    },
    {
        "question": "The 19th-century independence movements in Latin America were influenced by",
        "correct_answer": "the American and the French Revolutions",
        "distractor1": "Marxist ideology",
        "distractor2": "the Aztec wars against Hernando Cortez",
        "distractor3": "liberation theology"
    },
    {
        "question": "Simon Bolivar, Toussaint L Overture, and Bernardo O Higgins were Latin American leaders of",
        "correct_answer": "independence movements",
        "distractor1": "economic development",
        "distractor2": "educational reforms",
        "distractor3": "colonial expansion"
    },
    {
        "question": "In which region of the world did the American Revolution and the French Revolution have the greatest influence during the 1800 s?",
        "correct_answer": "Latin America",
        "distractor1": "Southeast Asia",
        "distractor2": "South Asia",
        "distractor3": "sub-Saharan Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sim n Bol var, Jos  de San Mart n, and Toussaint l Ouverture are important in Latin American history because they were",
        "correct_answer": "leaders of liberation movements",
        "distractor1": "20th-century caudillos",
        "distractor2": "members of the Organization of American States (OAS)",
        "distractor3": "winners of the Nobel Peace Prize"
    },
    {
        "question": " A country is not merely a geographic territory.  A country is also the idea given birth by the geographic territory.  A country is a sense of love that unites, as one, all the sons and daughters of that geographic territory  ",
        "correct_answer": "nationalism",
        "distractor1": "totalitarian rule",
        "distractor2": "absolute monarchy",
        "distractor3": "mercantilism"
    },
    {
        "question": "In a number of European countries in the 1800 s, which situation occurred as a result of the influence of the French Revolution?",
        "correct_answer": "rise of nationalistic movements",
        "distractor1": "increase in religious conflict",
        "distractor2": "decentralization of governmental power",
        "distractor3": "economic depression"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which quotation best reflects a feeling of nationalism?",
        "correct_answer": " For God, King, and Country ",
        "distractor1": " An eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth ",
        "distractor2": " A person s greatest social obligation is loyalty to the family ",
        "distractor3": " Opposition to evil is as much a duty as is cooperation with good "
    },
    {
        "question": "Nationalism is most likely to develop in an area that has",
        "correct_answer": "common customs, language, and history",
        "distractor1": "land suited to agriculture",
        "distractor2": "adequate industry to supply consumer demands",
        "distractor3": "a moderate climate with rivers for irrigation"
    },
    {
        "question": "Nationalism is best defined as",
        "correct_answer": "the loyalty of a people to their values, traditions, and a geographic region",
        "distractor1": "the achievement of world peace and global understanding",
        "distractor2": "the desire to take over other societies by force",
        "distractor3": "a method of solving basic economic problems of the society"
    },
    {
        "question": "The best example of the success of nationalism in Europe is the",
        "correct_answer": "unification of Germany",
        "distractor1": "development of socialism in France",
        "distractor2": "Industrial Revolution in Great Britain",
        "distractor3": "establishment of the Common Market"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which condition is most necessary to the process of industrialization in a society?",
        "correct_answer": "availability of investment capital",
        "distractor1": "dependence on subsistence agriculture",
        "distractor2": "creation of a one-crop economy",
        "distractor3": "capture of foreign lands"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Karl Marx, history is the record of the",
        "correct_answer": "struggle between classes in society",
        "distractor1": "granting of more political liberties to all people",
        "distractor2": "wars and conflicts between national leaders",
        "distractor3": "increasing prosperity brought about by industrialization"
    },
    {
        "question": "A main idea of Karl Marx and Friedrich Engles  Communist Manifesto is that the proletariat",
        "correct_answer": "must unite to overthrow the capitalist class",
        "distractor1": "would need foreign help to achieve its revolutionary ends",
        "distractor2": "had to cooperate with the capitalists to gain economic rewards",
        "distractor3": "should allow the capitalists to control the means of production"
    },
    {
        "question": " Revolution will occur more and more frequently in the industrialized nations as the proletariat struggles to overcome the abuses of the capitalist system. ",
        "correct_answer": "Karl Marx",
        "distractor1": "Charles Darwin",
        "distractor2": "Niccolo Machiavelli",
        "distractor3": "John Locke"
    },
    {
        "question": " The proletarians have nothing to lose but their chains Workers of the world, unite! ",
        "correct_answer": "Industrial Revolution",
        "distractor1": "Protestant Reformation",
        "distractor2": "Counter-Reformation",
        "distractor3": "Commercial Revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "Before a nation can begin to industrialize, that nation must first develop",
        "correct_answer": "an adequate food supply",
        "distractor1": "a democratic government",
        "distractor2": "a rigid class structure",
        "distractor3": "a strong religious foundation"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major result of the Industrial Revolution was the",
        "correct_answer": "concentration of workers in urban areas",
        "distractor1": "increased desire of the wealthy class to share its power",
        "distractor2": "formation of powerful craft guilds",
        "distractor3": "control of agricultural production by governments"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to the theories of Karl Marx, history can be viewed as a",
        "correct_answer": "continuous struggle between economic classes",
        "distractor1": "succession of famines that result in the destruction of civilizations",
        "distractor2": "repeating cycle of imperialism and colonialism",
        "distractor3": "listing of the accomplishments of the ruling classes"
    },
    {
        "question": "-Europeans sought new markets for their goods.  -Many Europeans migrated to the cities in search of jobs. ",
        "correct_answer": "Industrial Revolution",
        "distractor1": "rise of feudalism",
        "distractor2": "Congress of Vienna",
        "distractor3": "French Revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which revolution inspired Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels to express their ideas in The Communist Manifesto? ",
        "correct_answer": "Industrial",
        "distractor1": "Scientific",
        "distractor2": "Glorious",
        "distractor3": "Neolithic"
    },
    {
        "question": "Before Commodore Matthew Perry s expedition to Japan in 1853, Japan was most influenced by",
        "correct_answer": "China s religion, art, and writing",
        "distractor1": "Russia s need for warm water ports",
        "distractor2": "the introduction of advanced technology from the United States",
        "distractor3": "France s quest for new colonies"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Japan, the Meiji Restoration resulted in the",
        "correct_answer": "modernization of the nation s industry",
        "distractor1": "division of the nation between the European powers",
        "distractor2": "abolition of the position of emperor",
        "distractor3": "government being controlled by the samurai"
    },
    {
        "question": "An immediate result of Commodore Matthew Perry s visit to Japan in 1853 was",
        "correct_answer": "the development of trade between Japan and the West",
        "distractor1": "an alliance between Japan and Russia",
        "distractor2": "a war between Japan and the United States",
        "distractor3": "the continued isolation of Japan"
    },
    {
        "question": "The arrival of Commodore Matthew Perry in Japan in 1853 signaled the end of Japanese",
        "correct_answer": "policies of isolationism",
        "distractor1": "cultural contacts with the West",
        "distractor2": "militarism in Southeast Asia",
        "distractor3": "trade relations with the United States"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major goal of the Meiji government in Japan was to",
        "correct_answer": "establish Japan as an industrial power",
        "distractor1": "isolate Japan from other nations",
        "distractor2": "achieve political union with China",
        "distractor3": "encourage colonization of Asia by Western nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "The modernization of Japan during the Meiji Restoration resulted in",
        "correct_answer": "the rise of Japan as an imperialistic nation",
        "distractor1": "a return to a feudal system of government",
        "distractor2": "an alliance between China, Korea, Russia, and Japan",
        "distractor3": "a strengthening of Japan s isolationist policies"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes events in Japan during the period of the Meiji Restoration?",
        "correct_answer": "Rapid industrialization and economic growth occurred.",
        "distractor1": "Japan sought to isolate itself from world affairs.",
        "distractor2": "Local lords increased their power over the Japanese emperor.",
        "distractor3": "Agriculture was taken over by the government."
    },
    {
        "question": "A primary purpose for building the Suez Canal was to",
        "correct_answer": "increase trade between the Middle East, Europe and Asia",
        "distractor1": "encourage Jewish settlement in nearby Palestine",
        "distractor2": "reduce the time needed for travel between the Atlantic Ocean and the Caribbean Sea",
        "distractor3": "allow Indian merchants to reach the east coast of Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is an accurate statement about the partitioning of Africa by European imperialist nations during the 1800 s?",
        "correct_answer": "the cultural and ethnic diversity of the African people was disregarded",
        "distractor1": "new nations were based on old tribal boundaries",
        "distractor2": "the continent was divided equally among the colonial powers",
        "distractor3": "African unity was encouraged"
    },
    {
        "question": "After 1880, European nations sought colonies in Africa primarily because the Europeans were",
        "correct_answer": "competing of raw materials and markets",
        "distractor1": "in need of land for their surplus populations",
        "distractor2": "determined to bring Christianity to the Moslem world",
        "distractor3": "interested in completing their geographic knowledge of the world"
    },
    {
        "question": "The 19th century term  White Man s Burden  reflects the idea that",
        "correct_answer": "Europeans had a responsibility to improve the lives of the colonial peoples",
        "distractor1": "Asians and Africans were equal to Europeans",
        "distractor2": "Asians and Africans would be grateful for European help",
        "distractor3": "imperialism was opposed by most Europeans"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Sepoy Mutiny in India, the Boxer Rebellion in China, and the Islamic Revolution in Iran were similar in that they",
        "correct_answer": "resisted foreign influence in these countries",
        "distractor1": "restored power to the hereditary monarchies",
        "distractor2": "attempted to reject the traditional cultures in these countries",
        "distractor3": "reestablished the power of religious leaders"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 19th century, Europeans were able to divide China in Spheres of Influence mainly because the",
        "correct_answer": "Europeans had technologically superior military forces",
        "distractor1": "Chinese were eager to adopt western culture",
        "distractor2": "Europeans were willing to adopt Chinese customs",
        "distractor3": "Chinese lacked raw materials and resources"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Boxer Rebellion of the early 20th century was an attempt to",
        "correct_answer": "remove foreign influences from China",
        "distractor1": "eliminate poverty among the Chinese peasants",
        "distractor2": "bring western-style democracy to China",
        "distractor3": "restore trade between China and European nations"
    },
    {
        "question": " Yesterday, your ambassador petitioned my ministers regarding your trade with China our Celestial Empire possesses all things in great abundance and lacks no product within its own borders.  There is, therefore, no need to import any product manufactured by outside barbarians in exchange for our own goods. ",
        "correct_answer": "maintaining economic isolation",
        "distractor1": "expanding foreign trade",
        "distractor2": "increasing international interdependence",
        "distractor3": "developing into a colonial power"
    },
    {
        "question": "British control over South Africa, French control over Indochina, and Spanish control over Mexico are examples of",
        "correct_answer": "imperialism",
        "distractor1": "isolationism",
        "distractor2": "appeasement",
        "distractor3": "nonalignment"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the past, European nations have conquered other lands, made them into colonies, and controlled their economies.",
        "correct_answer": "imperialism",
        "distractor1": "socialism",
        "distractor2": "isolationism",
        "distractor3": "monotheism"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the past, European nations have conquered other lands, made them into colonies, and controlled their economies.",
        "correct_answer": "industrialization of Europe and the need for raw materials",
        "distractor1": "desire of Europeans to spread communism throughout the world",
        "distractor2": "European belief in human rights for all people",
        "distractor3": "requests of developing nations for modern machines and technology"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1840 s, China signed  unequal treaties  with Western nations mainly because",
        "correct_answer": "Western nations had superior military technology",
        "distractor1": "China had won the Opium War",
        "distractor2": "leaders in China favored expansion",
        "distractor3": "China had requested economic assistance from the West"
    },
    {
        "question": "Throughout the 1800 s, an increased need for both raw materials and new markets for manufactured goods led various European nations to pursue policies of",
        "correct_answer": "imperialism",
        "distractor1": "socialism",
        "distractor2": "isolationism",
        "distractor3": "communism"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 18th and 19th centuries, increased contact between European and the continents of Africa, Asia, and South America resulted in",
        "correct_answer": "the exploitation of the labor and resources of these continents",
        "distractor1": "closer cultural cooperation between Europe and these continents",
        "distractor2": "a return to the political and economic systems of feudal Europe",
        "distractor3": "preservation of the rights of the indigenous peoples"
    },
    {
        "question": "Take up the White Man s burden ",
        "correct_answer": "negative attitude of Europeans toward peoples of the non-Western world",
        "distractor1": "advantages Europeans would gain by colonizing Africa, Asia, and Latin America",
        "distractor2": "positive role of the Roman Catholic Church in Africa and Asia",
        "distractor3": "challenges non-Europeans faced when trading with the Europeans"
    },
    {
        "question": "Both the French and the British were interested in controlling Egypt in the mid-19th century because Egypt had",
        "correct_answer": "a strategic location",
        "distractor1": "control of the spice trade",
        "distractor2": "an industrial-based economy",
        "distractor3": "vital mineral resources"
    },
    {
        "question": " , you, Africa, suffered like a beast  Your ashes strewn to the wind that roams the desert, ",
        "correct_answer": "imperialism",
        "distractor1": "communism",
        "distractor2": "nationalism",
        "distractor3": "regionalism"
    },
    {
        "question": "The results of the Opium War (1839-1842) indicate that China was",
        "correct_answer": "not strong enough to resist Western demands",
        "distractor1": "still a major military power",
        "distractor2": "rapidly building a modern industrial economy",
        "distractor3": "accepting Western nations as equal trading partners"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 18th and 19th centuries, Europeans improved roads and bridges and built railroads in their colonies primarily to",
        "correct_answer": "obtain raw materials needed for industrialization",
        "distractor1": "provide jobs for the colonists",
        "distractor2": "impress the colonists with their technological knowledge",
        "distractor3": "help missionaries spread Christianity"
    },
    {
        "question": " Compared to other peoples of the world we have the greatest (largest) population and our civilization is four thousand years old Today we are the poorest and weakest nation in the world and occupy the lowest position in international affairs.  Other men are the carving knife and serving dish, we are the fish and the meat.  As a consequence we are being transformed everywhere into a colony of the foreign powers. ",
        "correct_answer": "Opium War and Boxer Rebellion",
        "distractor1": "Mau Mau uprising and adoption of apartheid",
        "distractor2": "Sepoy Mutiny and the Salt March",
        "distractor3": "Haitian Revolution and Cortes  march on Mexico City"
    },
    {
        "question": "One result of British colonialism in India was that India",
        "correct_answer": "adopted a parliamentary system of government",
        "distractor1": "developed religious unity",
        "distractor2": "supported Western foreign policies in the United Nations",
        "distractor3": "created programs to increase its population"
    },
    {
        "question": " The Ashanti and Ijebu... strongly resisted missionary incursion [interference]-for a time at least . . . Both groups grudgingly [reluctantly] accepted missionaries and their schools only after military defeat by imperial forces.       Edward H. Berman",
        "correct_answer": "opposed giving up their religious and cultural heritage",
        "distractor1": "returned to the worship of their traditional gods after the defeat of the missionaries",
        "distractor2": "cooperated with the missionaries for economic gain",
        "distractor3": "feared that missionaries would refuse to teach their children"
    },
    {
        "question": "In 19th-century China, the Opium War resulted in",
        "correct_answer": "an increase in European spheres of influence in China",
        "distractor1": "the control of Hong Kong being returned to China",
        "distractor2": "the removal of all British naval forces from China",
        "distractor3": "the rejection of Buddhism by the Chinese people"
    },
    {
        "question": "The borders that were established for many African nations during the late 1800 s were based primarily on",
        "correct_answer": "territorial claims of colonial rulers",
        "distractor1": "natural geographic barriers",
        "distractor2": "easy access to natural resources",
        "distractor3": "cultural differences between ethnic groups"
    },
    {
        "question": "An analysis of the Russo-Japanese War and the Boer War shows that one reason nations go to war is to ",
        "correct_answer": "satisfy imperialist goals",
        "distractor1": "assist oppressed people",
        "distractor2": "spread religious beliefs",
        "distractor3": "honor provisions of a treaty"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best expresses the motive for 19th-century European imperialism?",
        "correct_answer": "Imperialism would benefit the economies of the colonial powers.",
        "distractor1": "Living space was needed for the excess population in western Europe.",
        "distractor2": "European leaders believed imperialism was an effective method of reducing the number of wars.",
        "distractor3": "European nations would benefit from some aspects of the conquered nation s culture."
    },
    {
        "question": "In 1917, Bolshevik leaders in Russia sought peace with Germany because the new Russian government",
        "correct_answer": "wanted to retain power and avoid German occupation",
        "distractor1": "decided to join forces with Germany and the Central Powers",
        "distractor2": "needed to concentrate its troops and resources on its war with Turkey",
        "distractor3": "needed to control the Baltic Sea and wanted a warm water port"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Eastern Europe after World War I, the greatest obstacle to national unity in many nation-states was the",
        "correct_answer": "great ethnic diversity found in the region",
        "distractor1": "economic dependence of Eastern Europe on Japan",
        "distractor2": "acceptance of democratic traditions by most Eastern Europeans",
        "distractor3": "expansion of United States influence in the region"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the relationship between World War I and the Russian Revolution?",
        "correct_answer": "World War I created conditions within Russia that helped trigger a revolution",
        "distractor1": "World War I postponed the Russian Revolution by restoring confidence in the Czar",
        "distractor2": "the Russian Revolution inspired the Russian people to win World War I",
        "distractor3": "World War I gave the Czar s army the needed experience to suppress the Russian Revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major cause of World War I was",
        "correct_answer": "the existence of opposing alliances",
        "distractor1": "a decline in the policy of imperialism",
        "distractor2": "an increase in acts of aggression by England",
        "distractor3": "the spread of communism throughout Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why was the Balkan region referred to as the  Powder Keg of Europe  prior to World War I?",
        "correct_answer": "Nationalistic and imperialistic rivalries were increasing.",
        "distractor1": "The aggression of the Ottoman Empire was disrupting the balance of power.",
        "distractor2": "Yugoslavia was invading its neighboring countries.",
        "distractor3": "The area was the leading supplier of military equipment to the rest of the world."
    },
    {
        "question": "The major impact of the Treaty of Versailles on Germany was that the treaty led to",
        "correct_answer": "an increase in Germany s desire to regain its power and prestige",
        "distractor1": "an era of peace and international good will in Germany",
        "distractor2": "a stable Germany that was both democratic and strong",
        "distractor3": "a leadership position for Germany in the League of Nations"
    },
    {
        "question": " Archduke Franz Ferdinand Assassinated!    Germany Declares War on Russia and France!  ",
        "correct_answer": "World War I",
        "distractor1": "Franco-Prussian War",
        "distractor2": "Crimean War",
        "distractor3": "Cold War"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is generally a characteristic of a communist economy?",
        "correct_answer": "government agencies are involved in production planning",
        "distractor1": "investment is encouraged by the promise of large profits",
        "distractor2": "the role of government in the economy is restricted by law",
        "distractor3": "entrepreneurs sell shares in their companies to the government"
    },
    {
        "question": " A group of planners makes all economic decisions. The group assigns natural, human, and capital resources to the production of those goods and services it wants. The group decides how to produce them and to whom to distribute them ",
        "correct_answer": "command economy of the Soviet Union",
        "distractor1": "manorial economy of feudal Europe",
        "distractor2": "mercantile economy of 18th century Europe",
        "distractor3": "market economy of the United States"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which situation resulted from the Russo-Japanese War of 1905?",
        "correct_answer": "dissident groups challenged the power of the Russian Czar",
        "distractor1": "Japan lost its status as a world power",
        "distractor2": "the Japanese Emperor encouraged reforms in Russia",
        "distractor3": "Russia gained control of China and Japan"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stalin s Five-Year Plans and his decision to form collectives are examples of",
        "correct_answer": "strategies to modernize the economy of the Soviet Union through forced communism",
        "distractor1": "a more friendly foreign policy toward China",
        "distractor2": "methods of dealing with the United States during the Cold War",
        "distractor3": "programs to westernize, educate, and enlighten the population"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major cause of the Russian Revolution of 1917 was the",
        "correct_answer": "existence of sharp economic differences between social classes",
        "distractor1": "defeat of Germany in the Russian campaign",
        "distractor2": "marriage of Czar Nicholas II to a German princess",
        "distractor3": "appeal of Marxism to the Russian nobility"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is an accurate statement about the Soviet economy under the leadership of Joseph Stalin?",
        "correct_answer": "the Soviet Union increased its industrial output by developing heavy industry",
        "distractor1": "a large selection of consumer goods became available",
        "distractor2": "private farmers were encouraged to sell their surplus produce in an open market",
        "distractor3": "the government reduced its role in planning industrial production"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major effect of Josef Stalin s policy of Collectivization on Soviet agriculture was",
        "correct_answer": "a widespread food shortage throughout the nation",
        "distractor1": "an increase in the export of agricultural products",
        "distractor2": "a surplus of agricultural goods",
        "distractor3": "the immediate creation of many small private farms"
    },
    {
        "question": "One action taken by both V.I. Lenin and Joseph Stalin was",
        "correct_answer": "jailing or murdering potential opponents",
        "distractor1": "attempting to bring democracy to Russia",
        "distractor2": "supporting the Russian Orthodox Church",
        "distractor3": "providing economic aid to Japan after World War I and World War II"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Russian peasants supported the Bolsheviks in the 1917 Revolutions mainly because the Bolsheviks promised to",
        "correct_answer": "redistribute the land owned by the nobility",
        "distractor1": "establish collective farms",
        "distractor2": "maintain the agricultural price-support system",
        "distractor3": "bring modern technology to Russian farms"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the political situation in the Soviet Union immediately after Lenin s death in 1924?",
        "correct_answer": "a power struggle developed among Communist Party leaders",
        "distractor1": "the nation adopted a constitutional monarchy",
        "distractor2": "Trotsky and his followers assumed full control of the Communist Party",
        "distractor3": "popular elections were held to choose a new general secretary"
    },
    {
        "question": "The term that best describes the position of Jews in Czarist Russia is",
        "correct_answer": "persecuted minority",
        "distractor1": "political elite",
        "distractor2": "landed gentry",
        "distractor3": "military leaders"
    },
    {
        "question": "  the organizations of the revolutionaries must consist first, foremost, and mainly of people who make revolutionary activity their profession such an organization must of necessity be not too extensive and as secret as possible  ",
        "correct_answer": "overthrow the Russian government",
        "distractor1": "defeat Germany in World War I",
        "distractor2": "establish democracy in Russia",
        "distractor3": "maintain communist power in Western Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "The 1917 victory of the communists in Russia was a contradiction of Marxist theory because Russia was",
        "correct_answer": "mainly an agricultural society",
        "distractor1": "already ruled by a socialist government",
        "distractor2": "involved in World War I",
        "distractor3": "not considered to be a military power"
    },
    {
        "question": "Josef Stalin s leadership of the Soviet Union can best be characterized as a period of",
        "correct_answer": "censorship and terror",
        "distractor1": "democratic reform and nationalism",
        "distractor2": "humanism and democracy",
        "distractor3": "religious freedom and tolerance"
    },
    {
        "question": "The political reorganization of Russia after the Communist Revolution of 1917 resulted in",
        "correct_answer": "a federation of socialist republics",
        "distractor1": "the establishment of a two-party political system",
        "distractor2": "increased political power for ethnic minorities",
        "distractor3": "a limited monarchy with the czar as a figurehead"
    },
    {
        "question": "Under Josef Stalin, the Soviet Union emphasized centralized economic planning and Five-Year Plans primarily to",
        "correct_answer": "develop heavy industry",
        "distractor1": "produce more consumer goods",
        "distractor2": "expand exports",
        "distractor3": "create a demand for high-quality imports"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which characteristic was common to both Russia under the Czars and the Soviet Union under Josef Stalin?",
        "correct_answer": "persecution of political dissenters",
        "distractor1": "a lack of concern about territorial expansion",
        "distractor2": "support of artistic and literary freedom",
        "distractor3": "encouragement of free enterprise"
    },
    {
        "question": "Under Joseph Stalin, life in the Soviet Union was characterized by",
        "correct_answer": "the use of censorship and the secret police",
        "distractor1": "an abundance of consumer goods",
        "distractor2": "political instability and numerous civil wars",
        "distractor3": "support for small family-run farms"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which slogan expressed the ideals of the Bolshevik Revolution of 1917?",
        "correct_answer": "Bread, Land, and Peace",
        "distractor1": "Liberty, Equality, and Fraternity",
        "distractor2": "Land and Liberty",
        "distractor3": "Nationalism, Democracy, and the People s Livelihood"
    },
    {
        "question": "Russian peasants supported the Bolsheviks in 1917 primarily because the Bolsheviks pledged to",
        "correct_answer": "redistribute land and make peace",
        "distractor1": "establish and maintain collective farms",
        "distractor2": "keep crop yields low",
        "distractor3": "limit the income of the nobility"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes a relationship between World War I and the Bolshevik Revolution?",
        "correct_answer": "World War I created conditions in Russia that helped trigger a revolution.",
        "distractor1": "World War I postponed the revolution in Russia by restoring confidence in the Czar.",
        "distractor2": "Opposing Russian forces cooperated to fight the foreign invaders.",
        "distractor3": "World War I gave the Czar s army the needed experience to suppress the revolution."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Kirghiz with whom we stopped was very well off. . . . After some tea our host asked me,  Where is the Ak Padsha now, the White Tsar Nikolai?    He and all his family, the Tsaritsa, their daughters and son, have been killed by the Bolsheviks,  I answered. ",
        "correct_answer": "after the Russian Revolution",
        "distractor1": "during the Napoleonic Wars",
        "distractor2": "after Mao Zedong came to power",
        "distractor3": "during World War II"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 1920 s and 1930 s, the rise of totalitarian governments in Germany, Italy, and Spain was largely the result of",
        "correct_answer": "severe economic and social problems that arose in Europe after World War I",
        "distractor1": "the success of the Communists in establishing a command economy in the Soviet Union",
        "distractor2": "the active support of the United States",
        "distractor3": "movements demanding the return of the old monarchies"
    },
    {
        "question": "The harsh conditions imposed by the Treaty of Versailles after World War I helped lay the foundation for the",
        "correct_answer": "rise of fascism Germany",
        "distractor1": "uprisings during the French Revolution",
        "distractor2": "division of Korea along the 38th parallel",
        "distractor3": "Bolshevik Revolution in Russia"
    },
    {
        "question": "Between the Meiji Restoration and World War II, Japan tried to solve the problem of its scarcity of natural resources by",
        "correct_answer": "establishing a policy of imperialism",
        "distractor1": "exporting agricultural products in exchange for new technology",
        "distractor2": "building nuclear power plants",
        "distractor3": "cooperating with the Soviet Union to gain needed resources"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which idea was included in the provisions of the Treaty of Versailles to show the intent of the Allies to punish the Central Powers for their role in World War II?",
        "correct_answer": "Germany will accept full responsibility for causing the war",
        "distractor1": "all nations shall maintain open covenants of peace",
        "distractor2": "freedom of the seas will be maintained",
        "distractor3": "territorial settlements shall be made along clearly recognizable lines of nationality"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fascism in Europe during the 1920 s and 1930 s is best described as a",
        "correct_answer": "form of totalitarianism that glorified the state above the individual",
        "distractor1": "demonstration of laissez-faire capitalism that promoted free enterprise",
        "distractor2": "type of economic system that stressed a classless society",
        "distractor3": "set of humanist ideas that emphasized the dignity and worth of the individual"
    },
    {
        "question": "Censorship, mass arrests, and a secret police force are most characteristic of",
        "correct_answer": "totalitarian regimes",
        "distractor1": "parliamentary democracies",
        "distractor2": "republics",
        "distractor3": "constitutional monarchies"
    },
    {
        "question": "After World War I, Japan attempted to solve some of its economic problems by",
        "correct_answer": "expanding its influence in Asia",
        "distractor1": "establishing extensive trade with the Soviet Union",
        "distractor2": "practicing the principles of Marxism",
        "distractor3": "refusing to rely on Western technology"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which policy shows that appeasement does not always prevent war?",
        "correct_answer": "British policy toward Germany in Munich during the 1930 s",
        "distractor1": "French policy in Indochina in the 1950 s",
        "distractor2": "United States policy toward Cuba in the early 1960 s",
        "distractor3": "Iraqi policy toward Iran in the 1980 s"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 1930 s, the Japanese government followed a policy of imperialism primarily to",
        "correct_answer": "acquire new sources of raw materials",
        "distractor1": "spread Zen Buddhism throughout Asia",
        "distractor2": "sell more consumer goods to European nations",
        "distractor3": "spread the ideas of bushido"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was one reason the Nazi programs and policies of the early 1930 s appealed to many people in Germany?",
        "correct_answer": "the people were frustrated with their current economic and political situation",
        "distractor1": "Germany had been denied membership in the United Nations",
        "distractor2": "a coup d etat had forced communism on the German people",
        "distractor3": "the German people feared that the French of the British would soon gain control of the Polish corridor"
    },
    {
        "question": "The imperialist policies followed by Japan after World War I were based on a desire to",
        "correct_answer": "obtain natural resources for manufacturing",
        "distractor1": "convert people to Shinto",
        "distractor2": "acquire markets for its oil industry",
        "distractor3": "compete with Chinese trade policies"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the mid-1930 s, which characteristic was common to Fascist Italy, Nazi Germany, and Communist Russia?",
        "correct_answer": "one-party system that denied basic human rights",
        "distractor1": "government ownership of the means of production and distribution",
        "distractor2": "encouragement of individual freedom of expression in the arts",
        "distractor3": "emphasis on consumer goods rather than on weapons"
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason the Fascist governments of Benito Mussolini and Adolf Hitler came to power in Italy",
        "correct_answer": "faced economic and political difficulties",
        "distractor1": "were threatened by the United States",
        "distractor2": "supported civil liberties for all",
        "distractor3": "failed to join the League of Nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a characteristic of Germany under Adolf Hitler and the Soviet Union under Josef Stalin?",
        "correct_answer": "governmental control of the media",
        "distractor1": "an official foreign policy of isolationism",
        "distractor2": "public ownership of business and industry",
        "distractor3": "the absence of a written constitution"
    },
    {
        "question": "World War II is often considered to be a turning point in history because",
        "correct_answer": "European domination of the world began to weaken as nationalism in colonies increased",
        "distractor1": "the League of nations demonstrated that an international organization could maintain world peace",
        "distractor2": "the war brought an end to dictatorships as a form of government",
        "distractor3": "religious and ethnic differences were no longer a source of conflict between nations"
    },
    {
        "question": " From as early as I can remember, the Emperor was an important presence even in our remote home.  He was a descendant of the gods from thousands of years before, never to be looked at or listened to by mere mortals, a presence to be revered and protected and obeyed Finally , my family and neighbors gathered around the radio and listened in stunned silence to the voice that had never before been heard, saying he was only human after all.  Everyone was crying.  I was sad and confused  ",
        "correct_answer": "defeat of the Japanese in World War II",
        "distractor1": "his overthrow by communist forces",
        "distractor2": "signing of the Versailles Treaty",
        "distractor3": "conclusion of the Russo-Japanese War"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which reform took place in Japan after World War II?",
        "correct_answer": "Japan became a representative democracy",
        "distractor1": "Japan s industrial capability was greatly reduced",
        "distractor2": "the Emperor s position was abolished",
        "distractor3": "labor unions were declared illegal"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major factor in the economic recoveries of Japan and West Germany after World War II was their",
        "correct_answer": "need to replace destroyed factories",
        "distractor1": "desire to avoid an invasion from China",
        "distractor2": "acceptance into the United Nations",
        "distractor3": "ability to produce nuclear weapons"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor most enabled Japan to rebuild and modernize rapidly after World War II?",
        "correct_answer": "a well-trained workforce",
        "distractor1": "vast mineral reserves",
        "distractor2": "large amounts of fertile land",
        "distractor3": "a strong military"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is one major reason the Holocaust is considered a unique event in modern European history?",
        "correct_answer": "The genocide was planned in great detail and required the cooperation of many people.",
        "distractor1": "Jews of Europe have seldom been victims of persecution.",
        "distractor2": "Civilians rarely were killed during air raids on Great Britain.",
        "distractor3": "Adolf Hitler concealed his anti-Jewish feelings until after he came to power."
    },
    {
        "question": "The economic policies of the Soviet Union traditionally emphasized the production of",
        "correct_answer": "heavy industrial goods",
        "distractor1": "automobiles for export",
        "distractor2": "building materials for luxury housing",
        "distractor3": "consumer goods"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is generally a characteristic of a communist economy?",
        "correct_answer": "government agencies are involved in production planning",
        "distractor1": "investment is encouraged by the promise of large profits",
        "distractor2": "the role of government in the economy is restricted by law",
        "distractor3": "entrepreneurs sell shares in their companies to the government"
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason the Soviet Union formed the Warsaw Pact was to",
        "correct_answer": "limit the threat of invasion from Western Europe",
        "distractor1": "ease the transition to democracy",
        "distractor2": "help institute capitalism in Eastern Europe",
        "distractor3": "challenge the economic successes of the Common Market"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes most Eastern European countries immediately after World War II?  They",
        "correct_answer": "became satellite states of the Soviet Union",
        "distractor1": "adopted democratic reforms in their political systems",
        "distractor2": "became dependent on aid provided by the Marshall Plan",
        "distractor3": "emerged as world economic powers"
    },
    {
        "question": "Communist governments were established in most nations of Eastern Europe shortly after World War II because",
        "correct_answer": "the Soviet Union used military and diplomatic pressures to install their governments",
        "distractor1": "the region had a long tradition of strong communist parties",
        "distractor2": "communist governments were able to significantly increase agricultural productivity",
        "distractor3": "members of the Communist party won free elections in these nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Cold War Era (1945-1990), the United States and the Soviet Union were reluctant to become involved in direct military conflict mainly because of",
        "correct_answer": "the potential for global nuclear destruction",
        "distractor1": "the peacekeeping role of the United Nations",
        "distractor2": "pressure from nonaligned nations",
        "distractor3": "increased tensions in the Middle East"
    },
    {
        "question": "After World War II, the Soviet Union established satellites in Eastern Europe to",
        "correct_answer": "expand its power and control over Eastern Europe",
        "distractor1": "support the remaining Fascist governments in Eastern Europe",
        "distractor2": "preserve capitalism in Eastern Europe",
        "distractor3": "establish democratic governments in Eastern European nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Soviet Union, a negative aspect of the Cold War Era was the",
        "correct_answer": "high cost of maintaining the arms race",
        "distractor1": "attempt to preserve democratic ideals",
        "distractor2": "development of peaceful uses for modern technology",
        "distractor3": "development of effective means of international cooperation"
    },
    {
        "question": " From Stetin in the Baltic to Trieste in the Adriatic, an Iron Curtain has descended across the continent. Behind that line lie all the capitals of the ancient states of Central and Eastern Europe. Warsaw, Berlin, Prague, Vienna, Budapest, Belgrade, Bucharest and Sofia, all these famous cities and the populations around them lie in what I might call the Soviet Sphere, and all are subject, in one form or another, not only to Soviet influence, but to very high, and in some cases increasing measure of control from Moscow.\"",
        "correct_answer": "The Soviet Union has expanded its influence throughout Eastern Europe",
        "distractor1": "The Soviet Union has helped the nations of Eastern Europe improve their standard of living",
        "distractor2": "The democratic nations of Western Europe have stopped the expansion of Soviet influence in the world",
        "distractor3": "The Soviet Union will support communist revolutions in Southeast Asia"
    },
    {
        "question": "Prior to the 1980 s, the emphasis of the Five-Year Plans in the Soviet Union was on heavy industry.  One result was the",
        "correct_answer": "scarcity of consumer goods",
        "distractor1": "abundance of manufactured goods",
        "distractor2": "rejection of agricultural planning",
        "distractor3": "decline in military spending"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Soviet Union s reaction to the 1968 revolt in Czechoslovakia was to",
        "correct_answer": "send Soviet troops to occupy Czechoslovakia",
        "distractor1": "permit limited political and economic reforms in Czechoslovakia",
        "distractor2": "withdraw Soviet troops from Eastern Europe",
        "distractor3": "bring the matter to the attention of the United Nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a major reason for the success of Soviet domination in Eastern Europe after World War II?",
        "correct_answer": "the Soviet Union had military forces in Eastern Europe as a result of World War II",
        "distractor1": "Eastern Europeans accepted the doctrine of Pan-Slavism",
        "distractor2": "the democracies of Western Europe needed greater security",
        "distractor3": "Western Europeans feared that Nazism would be rekindled in Eastern Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "The events that took place in Hungary in the 1950 s and in Czechoslovakia in the 1960 s demonstrated the Soviet Union s",
        "correct_answer": "determination to maintain political control over Eastern Europe at that time",
        "distractor1": "support of nationalism among satellite nations",
        "distractor2": "influence on the economies of developing nations",
        "distractor3": "attempts to promote its artistic and literary achievements in Western Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "The expansion of communism into Eastern Europe was a direct result of",
        "correct_answer": "World War II",
        "distractor1": "the Crimean war",
        "distractor2": "the Napoleonic Wars",
        "distractor3": "World War I"
    },
    {
        "question": "United States involvement in the Vietnam War and the Soviet Union s involvement in Afghanistan were motivated mainly by a desire to",
        "correct_answer": "support governments that would remain strong allies",
        "distractor1": "exploit the mineral resources of the regions",
        "distractor2": "stop the expansion of Japan into the Middle East",
        "distractor3": "establish independent nation-states in the regions"
    },
    {
        "question": " Warsaw Pact Tanks Invade Budapest\"",
        "correct_answer": "attempts by the Soviet Union to strengthen communist control",
        "distractor1": "Mikhail Gorbachev s introduction of the policy of Glasnost",
        "distractor2": "Adolf Hitler s efforts to promote national socialism",
        "distractor3": "the Soviet Union s acceptance of capitalism"
    },
    {
        "question": "The invasion of Hungary in 1956 by the Soviet Union and the building of the Berlin Wall in 1961 are examples of",
        "correct_answer": "Truman Doctrine failures",
        "distractor1": "United Nations Security Council resolutions",
        "distractor2": "Marshall Plan effects",
        "distractor3": "Cold War Era conflicts"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Cold War Era, many Asian and African nations followed a policy of nonalignment because they",
        "correct_answer": "wished to receive aid from the Soviet Union and the United States",
        "distractor1": "had the same goals and needs as the Soviet Union",
        "distractor2": "needed the natural resources of Western European nations",
        "distractor3": "were afraid of losing their vote in the United Nations"
    },
    {
        "question": " We believe in nonaggression and noninterference by one country in the affairs of another and the growth of tolerance between them and the capacity for peaceful coexistence.  We, therefore, endeavor to maintain friendly relations with all countries, even though we may disagree with them in their policies. ",
        "correct_answer": "nonalignment",
        "distractor1": "imperialism",
        "distractor2": "mercantilism",
        "distractor3": "isolationism"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is a major reason Cuban and Nicaraguan revolutionary movements were attracted to communism?",
        "correct_answer": "communist groups promised economic reform and better living standards",
        "distractor1": "business owners and the military were supported by communist groups",
        "distractor2": "the goal of communism was to encourage religion",
        "distractor3": "communist leaders promised to reduce Spanish colonialism in the Western Hemisphere"
    },
    {
        "question": "The main reason the United Nations sent troops to Korea in 1950 was to",
        "correct_answer": "prevent North Korea from conquering the people of South Korea",
        "distractor1": "ensure that food reached areas of the Korean Peninsula affected by famine",
        "distractor2": "force the inspection of nuclear weapons plants in North Korea",
        "distractor3": "restore peace between warring factions of Buddhism and Shinto"
    },
    {
        "question": "The conflict between Israel and the Arab nations since 1948 was often considered part of the Cold War primarily because",
        "correct_answer": "the United States supported Israel and the Soviet Union supported several Arab nations",
        "distractor1": "the policy of detente evolved from this conflict",
        "distractor2": "communist governments were established in many Arab nations",
        "distractor3": "the leadership of Joseph Stalin strongly influenced the policies of Saddam Hussein"
    },
    {
        "question": "-Berlin Blockade (1948-1949)",
        "correct_answer": "the level of tension between the United States and the Soviet Union varied",
        "distractor1": "throughout the period, the United States and the Soviet Union were reluctant to solve conflicts",
        "distractor2": "economics played a key role in causing conflict between the United States and the Soviet Union",
        "distractor3": "the United Nations was instrumental in reducing tensions between the United States and the Soviet Union"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement would be consistent with the views of Fidel Castro?",
        "correct_answer": "Progress and justice in Latin America can only be achieved through revolutionary socialism",
        "distractor1": "The spread of communism is the greatest danger facing Latin America",
        "distractor2": "An American military presence is the key to the defense of Latin America",
        "distractor3": "Introducing a free-market system will improve the economies of Latin American nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "From the perspective of the North Vietnamese, the war in Vietnam in the 1960 s was a battle between",
        "correct_answer": "nationalism and imperialism",
        "distractor1": "fascism and liberalism",
        "distractor2": "republicanism and totalitarianism",
        "distractor3": "theocracy and monarchy"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which headline concerning the Soviet Union refers to a Cold War event?",
        "correct_answer": " Warsaw Pact Formed ",
        "distractor1": " Yeltsin Assumes Power ",
        "distractor2": " Trotsky Forms Red Army",
        "distractor3": " Germany Invades USSR "
    },
    {
        "question": "A major development in relations between the Soviet Union and the United States occurred in the late 1980 s when the two nations agreed to",
        "correct_answer": "eliminate a group of nuclear missiles",
        "distractor1": "purchase all their oil from Mexico",
        "distractor2": "withdraw from the United Nations",
        "distractor3": "ban arms sales to developing nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980 s, the Soviet Union experimented with modifications of its command economy by",
        "correct_answer": "introducing some market economy strategies",
        "distractor1": "eliminating central planning",
        "distractor2": "allowing private ownership of major industries",
        "distractor3": "legalizing independent trade unions"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 30 years after World War II, which area was most influenced by the Soviet Union?",
        "correct_answer": "Eastern Europe",
        "distractor1": "Southeast Asia",
        "distractor2": "North Africa",
        "distractor3": "Central America"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the political situation in Eastern Europe during the 1980 s?",
        "correct_answer": "nationalism has often been a strong force for change",
        "distractor1": "communist governments have gained power through democratic elections",
        "distractor2": "ethnic rivalries have been eliminated throughout the region",
        "distractor3": "United States influence has been used to keep communist governments in power"
    },
    {
        "question": "The withdrawal of France from Indochina, the involvement of the Soviet Union in Cuba, and the United States support of the Contras in Nicaragua illustrate that nations",
        "correct_answer": "tend to base foreign policy decisions on what they believe to be their self-interests",
        "distractor1": "consistently discard traditional foreign policy goals after changes in administration",
        "distractor2": "no longer use warfare as a means to resolve international conflict",
        "distractor3": "tend to refer foreign policy conflicts to the United Nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is a valid statement about the Soviet Union from the time of the Bolshevik Revolution through 1991?",
        "correct_answer": "Demand for consumer goods has exceeded production",
        "distractor1": "Education has been limited to the communist party elite",
        "distractor2": "Military expenditures have been low",
        "distractor3": "Industrialization has not occurred"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Soviet Union, Vladimir Lenin s New Economic Policy (NEP) and Mikhail Gorbachev s policy of Perestroika both sought to",
        "correct_answer": "increase production through individual enterprise",
        "distractor1": "increase spending of nuclear weapons",
        "distractor2": "strengthen central planning",
        "distractor3": "reduce the influence of middle-class farmers"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980 s in the Soviet Union, a major element of the economic policy of Perestroika was",
        "correct_answer": "more reliance on local and regional decision making",
        "distractor1": "increased collectivization of farms",
        "distractor2": "the expanded use of national Five-Year plans",
        "distractor3": "an emphasis on the redistribution of wealth"
    },
    {
        "question": "  Blockade of Berlin    Operation of the Berlin Airlift ",
        "correct_answer": "situations that increased tensions between communist and democratic nations in Europe",
        "distractor1": "efforts to prevent military conflict between the superpowers",
        "distractor2": "attempts to weaken the Soviet Union s control of its Eastern European allies",
        "distractor3": "policies of peaceful coexistence and d tente"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Eastern Europe during the 1950 s and 1960 s, the Soviet Union responded to challenges to its control by",
        "correct_answer": "imposing prompt and severe repression",
        "distractor1": "allowing free elections, when necessary",
        "distractor2": "obtaining United Nations assistance",
        "distractor3": "granting independence to its satellite nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the People s Republic of China, which factor best reflects Marxism?",
        "correct_answer": "communal work teams on farms",
        "distractor1": "ownership of small farms by individuals",
        "distractor2": "small family-owned businesses in villages",
        "distractor3": "foreign influence on the economy"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Great Leap Forward in China and the five-year plans in the Soviet Union were attempts to increase",
        "correct_answer": "industrial productivity",
        "distractor1": "private capital investment",
        "distractor2": "religious tolerance",
        "distractor3": "individual ownership of land"
    },
    {
        "question": "In China and the former Soviet Union, the communist governments discouraged organized religion because religions",
        "correct_answer": "compete for the loyalties of the people",
        "distractor1": "support the principles of laissez-faire",
        "distractor2": "favor anarchy over organized government",
        "distractor3": "stress economic rather than political values"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major goal of the Cultural Revolution in China during the 1960 s was to",
        "correct_answer": "eliminate opposition to Mao Zedong",
        "distractor1": "restore China to the glory of the Han Dynasty",
        "distractor2": "reemphasize Confucian traditional values",
        "distractor3": "weaken communist ideas"
    },
    {
        "question": "After World War II, the Chinese Communists were successful in their revolution mainly because the",
        "correct_answer": "communists had the support of the peasants",
        "distractor1": "United States refused to support the Nationalists",
        "distractor2": "communists had more technologically advanced weapons",
        "distractor3": "nationalist had been defeated by Japan"
    },
    {
        "question": "An immediate result of the Cultural Revolution in China was that it",
        "correct_answer": "disrupted China s economic and educational systems",
        "distractor1": "helped to establish democracy in urban centers in China",
        "distractor2": "led to economic cooperation with Japan and South Korea",
        "distractor3": "strengthened political ties with the United States"
    },
    {
        "question": "The main reason the Chinese Communists gained control of mainland China in 1949 was that",
        "correct_answer": "the dynamic leadership of Mao Zedong had the support of the peasant class",
        "distractor1": "they were supported by many warlords and upper class Chinese",
        "distractor2": "the United States had supported the Chinese Communist Party during World War II",
        "distractor3": "they had superior financial resources and were supported by Japan"
    },
    {
        "question": "In China, the Great Leap Forward was an attempt to",
        "correct_answer": "increase agricultural and industrial production",
        "distractor1": "promote democratic reform",
        "distractor2": "end the private ownership of land",
        "distractor3": "strengthen economic ties with Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "Deng Xioaping s economic reforms in China differ from the previous economic policies of Mao Zedong in that Deng s reforms",
        "correct_answer": "include elements of capitalism",
        "distractor1": "discourage private ownership of businesses",
        "distractor2": "promote further collectivization",
        "distractor3": "decrease trade with the United States"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Confucian view of government and the Chinese Communist view of government were similar in that both stressed",
        "correct_answer": "loyalty to the government",
        "distractor1": "the need for filial piety",
        "distractor2": "a civil service system",
        "distractor3": "equality of men and women"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major reason for the success of the Communist revolution in China was that the Communists",
        "correct_answer": "promised land and power to the peasant class",
        "distractor1": "stressed Buddhism in their military training",
        "distractor2": "included important businessmen in their ranks",
        "distractor3": "fought successfully against the United States during World War II"
    },
    {
        "question": "In China, the Great Leap Forward and the Cultural Revolution promoted by Mao Zedong were similar in that both plans",
        "correct_answer": "disrupted industrial development",
        "distractor1": "ended dynastic rule",
        "distractor2": "encouraged capitalism",
        "distractor3": "guaranteed human rights"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980 s, the Chinese government adopted policies designed to",
        "correct_answer": "increase industrial productivity",
        "distractor1": "reestablish Confucian traditions and values",
        "distractor2": "gain colonies throughout East Asia",
        "distractor3": "maintain its isolation from world events"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about the economy of China in the 1980 s is most accurate?",
        "correct_answer": "China increased its industrial capacity and foreign trade",
        "distractor1": "China surpassed the Soviet Union in steel production",
        "distractor2": "China s economy slowed down because of a lack of natural resources",
        "distractor3": "China s economy suffered from overproduction of consumer goods"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sun Yat-sen s  Three Principles of the People  (1911) and the demonstrations in Tiananmen Square (1989) were similar in that they both demanded that the Chinese government",
        "correct_answer": "introduce democratic reforms",
        "distractor1": "achieve global interdependence",
        "distractor2": "restore dynastic rule",
        "distractor3": "end foreign influences in China"
    },
    {
        "question": "The goal of Mao Zedong s policy known as the Great Leap Forward was to",
        "correct_answer": "modernize China s economic system by dividing China into communes",
        "distractor1": "develop foreign export industries in China s coastal urban centers",
        "distractor2": "eliminate state-owned industries in rural China",
        "distractor3": "introduce capitalism to the Chinese economy"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about reforms in China during the 1980 s and 1990 s is most accurate?",
        "correct_answer": "Economic reforms were more successful than political reforms.",
        "distractor1": "Political reforms resulted in the overthrow of communism.",
        "distractor2": "Political reforms increased individual rights.",
        "distractor3": "Economic reforms forced China to return to a policy of isolationism."
    },
    {
        "question": " A wind has been blowing from the West; now it will begin to blow from the East.   \tMao Zedong, 1949",
        "correct_answer": "European power will decline as a new center of power emerges in Asia.",
        "distractor1": "The monsoons will soon shift and bring destruction to the mainland of Asia.",
        "distractor2": "Chinese culture will no longer influence the people of Asia.",
        "distractor3": "The Asian people have much to learn from the Western Europeans."
    },
    {
        "question": " When I go to the office, I put on my shirt and I take off my Caste; when I come home, I take off my shirt and I put on my Caste. ",
        "correct_answer": "the Caste system continues to influence Indian society",
        "distractor1": "the Caste system has been reflected by most Indians",
        "distractor2": "successful urban workers in India belong the same Caste",
        "distractor3": "the Indian government officially supports the Caste system"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor most limited the development of African nationalism?",
        "correct_answer": "political boundaries imposed by Europeans that had little relationship to African tribal boundaries",
        "distractor1": "European support of an educational system based on local traditions and language",
        "distractor2": "the prior experience of Africans with economic self-sufficiency",
        "distractor3": "the European practice of making decisions based on local customs"
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which Kwame Nkurmah, Jomo Kenyatta, and Kenneth Kaunda are similar is that they all",
        "correct_answer": "played a major role in independence movements in Africa",
        "distractor1": "supported the United Nations military action in the Persian Gulf War",
        "distractor2": "rejected financial aid from the World Bank",
        "distractor3": "opposed the Pan-African movement"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the political situation in Africa after World War II?",
        "correct_answer": "increased nationalism led to independence for many African nations",
        "distractor1": "France and West Germany sought to establish colonies in Africa",
        "distractor2": "European nations increased their control over their African colonies",
        "distractor3": "the United Nations opposed the idea of self-determination for African nations"
    },
    {
        "question": " If we are to remain free, if we are to enjoy the full benefits of Africa s enormous wealth, we must unite to plan for the full exploitation of our human and material resources in the interest of all our people ",
        "correct_answer": "Pan-Africanism",
        "distractor1": "colonialism",
        "distractor2": "imperialism",
        "distractor3": "urbanization"
    },
    {
        "question": "After World War II, which action was taken by many African territories?",
        "correct_answer": "demanding independence from their colonial rulers",
        "distractor1": "refusing to join international organizations",
        "distractor2": "rejecting most of the technology offered by western nations",
        "distractor3": "creating a strong, united Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mohandas Gandhi is best known for his",
        "correct_answer": "use of passive resistance to achieve Indian independence",
        "distractor1": "desire to establish and Islamic nations",
        "distractor2": "opposition to Hindus holding political office",
        "distractor3": "encouragement of violence to end British rule"
    },
    {
        "question": "The primary goal of the Indian National Congress (1855-1947) was to",
        "correct_answer": "gain independence from Great Britain",
        "distractor1": "reform the Hindu religion",
        "distractor2": "partition India between Muslims and Hindus",
        "distractor3": "create a socialist economy"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rise of independent states in Asia and Africa after World War II demonstrates the",
        "correct_answer": "decline of European colonial empires",
        "distractor1": "failure of nationalist movements",
        "distractor2": "influence of socialism",
        "distractor3": "success of United Nations peacekeeping forces"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which action best illustrates Mohandas Gandhi s concept of civil disobedience?",
        "correct_answer": "citizens in the United States went to jail for violation segregation laws",
        "distractor1": "a British army outpost was bombed as a protest against the British presence in Northern Ireland",
        "distractor2": "French citizens wrote letters to their government to oppose arms sale to Iraq",
        "distractor3": "supporters of Ferdinand Marcos attempted a coup d etat against the Philippine government"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which has been a characteristic of many Southeast Asian countries since World War II?",
        "correct_answer": "internal struggles for power that lead to political instability",
        "distractor1": "isolation from the influence of the superpowers",
        "distractor2": "democratic governments based on the principles of the French Revolution",
        "distractor3": "fundamentalist Islamic governments supported by Iran"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which event was used by Mohandas Gandhi to bring world attention to the injustices of British colonialism?",
        "correct_answer": "salt march",
        "distractor1": "partition of India",
        "distractor2": "Sepoy Mutiny",
        "distractor3": "formation of the Indian parliament"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since the 1950 s, India has experienced conflict with both Pakistan and China over",
        "correct_answer": "borders and related territorial issues",
        "distractor1": "United Nations peacekeeping efforts in the region",
        "distractor2": "India s increasing trade with Korea",
        "distractor3": "the interpretation of common religious works"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best reflects a belief of Mohandas Gandhi?",
        "correct_answer": "India must achieve independence, but not at the expense of further dividing the Indian people",
        "distractor1": "Muslims and Hindus must be separated if true peace is to come to India",
        "distractor2": "India must adopt the British factory system",
        "distractor3": "The caste system must remain an important cornerstone of Hindu society"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since India s independence in 1947, the government has had the greatest success in",
        "correct_answer": "increasing overall food production",
        "distractor1": "reducing the population",
        "distractor2": "eliminating religious conflict",
        "distractor3": "controlling industrial pollution"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Canal was dug by Egypt s sons and 120,000 of them died while working.  The Suez Canal Company in Paris is an imposter company.  It usurped our concessions  Therefore, I have signed today the following law which has been approved by the Cabinet: Article 1 of the decree reads,  The Universal Company of the Suez Maritime Canal Egyptian Joint-Stock Company   is hereby nationalized. All its assets, rights and obligations are hereby transferred to the Nation. ",
        "correct_answer": "take control of the Suez Canal",
        "distractor1": "end trade with Mediterranean countries",
        "distractor2": "stop building canals",
        "distractor3": "sell the Suez Canal to France"
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason India gained its independence from Great Britain in 1947 was that",
        "correct_answer": "Great Britain did not have the resources to maintain an empire after World War II",
        "distractor1": "Great Britain was defeated in World War II",
        "distractor2": "the Treaty of Versailles required Great Britain to give up its colonies",
        "distractor3": "India had supported the Axis Powers during World War II"
    },
    {
        "question": "One important similarity between Indira Gandhi of India and Benazir Bhutto of Pakistan is that both",
        "correct_answer": "became important national leaders in nations in which women have not traditionally had equal opportunities",
        "distractor1": "are Hindu leaders of Islamic nations",
        "distractor2": "came into power as a result of the breakup of the Soviet Union",
        "distractor3": "became leaders of the Asian bloc of nations at the United Nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between the Sepoys in India, the Boxers in China, and the Mau Mau in Kenya is that these groups",
        "correct_answer": "tried to drive Europeans out of their countries",
        "distractor1": "depended on Western support for their success",
        "distractor2": "adopted Marxist economic and political principles",
        "distractor3": "sought independence through nonviolence"
    },
    {
        "question": "The  homespun movement  and the Salt March promoted by Mohandas Gandhi in India are examples of his policy of",
        "correct_answer": "nonviolent protest",
        "distractor1": "industrialization",
        "distractor2": "isolationism",
        "distractor3": "nonalignment"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best explains why India was partitioned in 1947?",
        "correct_answer": "religious differences led to political division",
        "distractor1": "the British feared a united India",
        "distractor2": "one region wanted to remain under British control",
        "distractor3": "communist supporters wanted a separate state"
    },
    {
        "question": "During India s independence movement, Mohandas Gandhi s boycott of British-made products was effective because the British considered India a major",
        "correct_answer": "market for manufactured goods",
        "distractor1": "shipping center",
        "distractor2": "industrial center",
        "distractor3": "source of mineral resources"
    },
    {
        "question": "The stability of many African nations continues to be threatened by the",
        "correct_answer": "ethnic and tribal loyalties of the people",
        "distractor1": "spread of Animism among the people",
        "distractor2": "use of command economies",
        "distractor3": "establishment of labor unions"
    },
    {
        "question": "The war between India and Pakistan in Kashmir in 1965, the sending of Indian troops to Sir Lanka in 1987, and the assassination of Rajiv Gandhi in 1991 all demonstrate that in South Asia",
        "correct_answer": "b. regional and ethnic rivalries remain strong",
        "distractor1": "a. the Shino religion is a significant force",
        "distractor2": "a. United Nations peacekeeping forces are ineffective",
        "distractor3": "c. nations are vulnerable to a communist takeover"
    },
    {
        "question": "In India today, the continued discrimination based on caste illustrates",
        "correct_answer": "b. the gap between law and tradition",
        "distractor1": "a. a commitment to a capitalist economic system",
        "distractor2": "c. the influence of the Cold War on India",
        "distractor3": "c. the declining role of religion in modern society"
    },
    {
        "question": "India has developed a mixed economy that",
        "correct_answer": "c. blends free enterprise with socialism",
        "distractor1": "a. guarantees government control over the economy",
        "distractor2": "b. provides open competition without government interference",
        "distractor3": "d. relies on the traditional barter system"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980 s, national unity in India was hindered by",
        "correct_answer": "c. conflicts between Sikhs, Hindus, and Muslims",
        "distractor1": "a. a foreign policy of nonalignment",
        "distractor2": "b. continued fear of attack from the Soviet Union",
        "distractor3": "c. political interference from China"
    },
    {
        "question": "With which nation are Pol Pot, the Khmer Rouge, and genocide associated?",
        "correct_answer": "Cambodia (Kampuchea)",
        "distractor1": "Korea",
        "distractor2": "Japan",
        "distractor3": "Myanmar (Burma)"
    },
    {
        "question": "--Rebellion in the Congo during the 1960 s  --Civil war in Nigeria from 1967 to 1970 ",
        "correct_answer": "ethnic rivalries",
        "distractor1": "poor food distribution systems",
        "distractor2": "communist interference",
        "distractor3": "demands for land reform"
    },
    {
        "question": "In some African nations today, ethnic rivalries erupt when",
        "correct_answer": "political differences are motivated by ancient resentments",
        "distractor1": "trading companies hire nonunion workers",
        "distractor2": "scarce funds halt the exploration for mineral resources",
        "distractor3": "groups share a common heritage"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is most accurate about many African societies today?",
        "correct_answer": "new attitudes and values often clash with traditional tribal practices",
        "distractor1": "modern medicines have been ineffective in decreasing infant mortality throughout Africa",
        "distractor2": "agriculture is no longer the most important economic activity in Africa",
        "distractor3": "European influence no longer exists in the former colonial territories"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which situation would best encourage economic development in most African nations today?",
        "correct_answer": "b. attracting investment capital",
        "distractor1": "a. increasing the population growth rate",
        "distractor2": "c. reducing the number of skilled workers",
        "distractor3": "d. depleting their natural resources"
    },
    {
        "question": "The caste system is still practiced in India today primarily because it is",
        "correct_answer": "encouraged by village customs and traditions",
        "distractor1": "enforced by the military",
        "distractor2": "supported by Christian and Muslim teachings",
        "distractor3": "mandated by law"
    },
    {
        "question": "In 1991, Pakistan amended its constitution and made the Koran the basis of all its laws.  Which group was responsible for this action?",
        "correct_answer": "Islamic fundamentalists",
        "distractor1": "Kashmir separatists",
        "distractor2": "Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO)",
        "distractor3": "Buddhist monks"
    },
    {
        "question": "In India, the people have resisted changing their attitudes toward the caste system because",
        "correct_answer": "the Hindu beliefs of karma and dharma reinforce the caste system",
        "distractor1": "national Muslim leaders have supported the caste system",
        "distractor2": "the government is unwilling to end the caste system",
        "distractor3": "continued religious conflict prevents changes in the caste system"
    },
    {
        "question": " Today you won t find a single African head of state who stands on a podium and declares:  I am a Marxist.  Instead all the talk is about currency, private enterprise, and getting hold of capital.    --Tei Mante of Ghana   ",
        "correct_answer": "African nations are more concerned with obtaining investment capital than with discussing political philosophies",
        "distractor1": "African nations remain heavily dependent on China and North Korea for trade, capital, and food",
        "distractor2": "African nations realize they must cooperate",
        "distractor3": "the failure of capitalism in Africa has helped the communists grow in strength"
    },
    {
        "question": "The actions of Jomo Kenyatta, Kwame Nkrumah, Leopold Senghor, and Julius Nyerere were most closely associated with",
        "correct_answer": "a rise in nationalism in several African countries",
        "distractor1": "the end of apartheid in South Africa",
        "distractor2": "a resurgence of colonialism in east Africa",
        "distractor3": "the revival of Islam in northern Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "The wars that took place in the Democratic Republic of the Congo and Nigeria in the 1960 s and in Rwanda and Somalia in the early 1990 s are similar in that these wars were caused in part by disputes",
        "correct_answer": "between ethnic groups",
        "distractor1": "over water sources",
        "distractor2": "over oil and mineral rights",
        "distractor3": "between communist and noncommunist forces"
    },
    {
        "question": " Indian National Congress Refuses To Support British War Effort    Indians Answer Call for the Production of Homespun Cloth  ",
        "correct_answer": "attempts by the native people to gain Indian independence",
        "distractor1": "political reorganization in the British colonia empire",
        "distractor2": "programs to increase India s standard of living",
        "distractor3": "the benefits of economic interdependence between Britain and India"
    },
    {
        "question": "After World War II, the conflict between Hindus and Muslims in India resulted in the",
        "correct_answer": "creation of the Muslim state of Pakistan",
        "distractor1": "near genocide of the Hindu population",
        "distractor2": "forced removal of most Hindus from northern and western India",
        "distractor3": "decision of Mohandas Gandhi to seek election as Prime Minister of India"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is valid about the history of Southeast Asia?",
        "correct_answer": "Religious beliefs have both unified and divided the people of the region.",
        "distractor1": "Industrialization has strengthened the traditional beliefs and lifestyles of the people.",
        "distractor2": "The area has experienced little European contact.",
        "distractor3": "Superpower influence has brought peace and prosperity to the region."
    },
    {
        "question": "Since Nigeria s independence in 1960, its government has frequently shifted between democracy and military dictatorship. This situation suggests that",
        "correct_answer": "democracy is often difficult to establish in nations where little democratic tradition exists",
        "distractor1": "some Nigerians support British colonialism",
        "distractor2": "international problems are more easily solved by military governments",
        "distractor3": "economic prosperity is frequently achieved by military governments"
    },
    {
        "question": "The desire for self-determination in African nations became a powerful force for change immediately after",
        "correct_answer": "World War II",
        "distractor1": "the Boer War",
        "distractor2": "revolutions in Russia and France",
        "distractor3": "the end of the Cold War"
    },
    {
        "question": " Rhodesia Becomes Zimbabwe    Gold Coast Becomes Ghana   ",
        "correct_answer": "reflect traditional cultures",
        "distractor1": "avoid military overthrow",
        "distractor2": "reinforce colonial influences",
        "distractor3": "increase foreign investments"
    },
    {
        "question": "In India today, a major reason the caste system remains strongest in rural areas is that",
        "correct_answer": "tradition remains a strong influence in small villages",
        "distractor1": "economic change occurs rapidly in villages",
        "distractor2": "village laws have resulted in immediate social change",
        "distractor3": "Islam is the dominant religion"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Cold War period, India s foreign policy was committed to",
        "correct_answer": "nonalignment with the world powers",
        "distractor1": "supporting communism in Asia",
        "distractor2": "rejecting democracy in Pakistan",
        "distractor3": "isolationism in international commerce"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since the end of World War II, military rearmament in Japan has been limited by",
        "correct_answer": "specific restrictions in Japan s constitution",
        "distractor1": "Japan s refusal to sign a nuclear nonproliferation treaty",
        "distractor2": "the United Nations refusal to sell weapons to the Japanese",
        "distractor3": "a scarcity of technology and resources in Japan"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sense of national unity has been difficult to maintain in India because of",
        "correct_answer": "the desire of religious groups for greater autonomy",
        "distractor1": "its reliance on foreign aid",
        "distractor2": "the emergence of a mixed economic system",
        "distractor3": "the continuing influence of militarism"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about the problems of Indian independence is a fact rather than an opinion? ",
        "correct_answer": "Muslim leaders wanted their own separate Muslim state.",
        "distractor1": "Stronger government leadership would have prevented bloodshed.",
        "distractor2": "Control of India by Great Britain brought more benefits than difficulties.",
        "distractor3": "India would have been more prosperous if it had remained a colony."
    },
    {
        "question": " East Africa is changing. . . . When my children go . . . with us to visit my parents",
        "correct_answer": "conflict between tradition and modernization",
        "distractor1": "political problems of developing nations",
        "distractor2": "ethnic conflicts",
        "distractor3": "prejudice against elderly family members"
    },
    {
        "question": "The main course of the Arab-Israeli conflicts from 1948 to 1973 was the clash between",
        "correct_answer": "Arab nationalism and Jewish nationalism",
        "distractor1": "Islamic Fundamentalism and Orthodox Judaism",
        "distractor2": "Arab socialism and Israeli capitalism",
        "distractor3": "Israeli technology and Saudi Arabian economic goals"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Iran, the Revolution of 1979 and the rise of Islamic fundamentalism resulted in",
        "correct_answer": "a return to many traditional customs",
        "distractor1": "an increase in woman s rights",
        "distractor2": "the westernization and modernization of the nation",
        "distractor3": "the introduction of a democratic form of government"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who were David Ben-Gurion, Golda Meir, and Menachem Begin?",
        "correct_answer": "leaders of the modern state of Israel",
        "distractor1": "scientist who developed better methods of discovering oil",
        "distractor2": "clergy who supported Islamic Fundamentalism",
        "distractor3": "Egyptian presidents who encouraged peace with Israel"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the late 1980 s and early 1990 s the greatest threat to the stability of the nations of Egypt, Algeria, and Morocco was the",
        "correct_answer": "rise of Islamic Fundamentalism",
        "distractor1": "rising standard of living of their citizens",
        "distractor2": "economic reforms taking place in Eastern Europe",
        "distractor3": "lack of financial aid from the United States"
    },
    {
        "question": "Israel is a country that has",
        "correct_answer": "a democratically elected government",
        "distractor1": "an abundance of oil",
        "distractor2": "Islam as its official religion",
        "distractor3": "friendly ties to Jordan"
    },
    {
        "question": "In 1979, the signing of the Camp David Accords by Egypt and Israel indicated that",
        "correct_answer": "former enemies were able to negotiate",
        "distractor1": "nationalism was no longer a force in middle Eastern politics",
        "distractor2": "the differences between Shi ite and Sunni Moslems had been settled",
        "distractor3": "the Soviet Union dominated Middle Eastern affairs"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980 s, the economic development of Iran and Iraq was disrupted because of",
        "correct_answer": "the war fought between these nations",
        "distractor1": "increased emphasis on agricultural production for export",
        "distractor2": "communist revolutionary movements in these nations",
        "distractor3": "severe drought and famine in the area"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major factor that continues to contribute to terrorist activities in the Middle East is",
        "correct_answer": "the Palestinian effort to establish a homeland",
        "distractor1": "a decrease in crude oil prices on the world market",
        "distractor2": "the presence of United Nations forces in Syria",
        "distractor3": "the worldwide rejection of violence as a means to end conflict"
    },
    {
        "question": "The 1979 Islamic Revolution in Iran was a reaction to the failure of Shah Reza Pahlavi to",
        "correct_answer": "meet the social and political needs of the people",
        "distractor1": "modernize the nation s economy",
        "distractor2": "establish political ties with western nations",
        "distractor3": "supply the military with advanced weapons technology"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980 s the governments of Libya and Iran were similar in that both were linked to",
        "correct_answer": "incidents of international terrorism",
        "distractor1": "efforts to separate religion and politics",
        "distractor2": "advocates of judicial reform",
        "distractor3": "promotion of democratic principles in third world nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "The actions of most Islamic fundamentalists show that they support",
        "correct_answer": "traditional Muslim teachings",
        "distractor1": "a Zionist movement",
        "distractor2": "equal rights for women",
        "distractor3": "a renewed attempt at modernization"
    },
    {
        "question": "In most of the nations of the Middle East, a major long-term economic concern will be the need for",
        "correct_answer": "diversified industry",
        "distractor1": "unskilled labor",
        "distractor2": "imported oil",
        "distractor3": "herds of camels"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which type of government did Ayatollah Khomeini establish as a result of the Iranian Revolution in 1979?",
        "correct_answer": "fundamentalist Islamic state",
        "distractor1": "constitutional monarchy",
        "distractor2": "democratic republic",
        "distractor3": "radical Marxist regime"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity in the leadership of Kemal Ataturk, Gamal Nasser, and Shah Reza Pahlavi is that all these leaders",
        "correct_answer": "sought to modernize their nations",
        "distractor1": "came to power as a result of democratic elections",
        "distractor2": "encouraged their people to convert to Hinduism",
        "distractor3": "led invasions into Israel"
    },
    {
        "question": "As a peace process continues in the Middle East, a major stumbling block to a settlement of the Arab-Israeli conflict is the question of",
        "correct_answer": "land and civil rights for Palestinian Arabs",
        "distractor1": "ownership and operation of the Suez Canal",
        "distractor2": "control of the Arabian Peninsula",
        "distractor3": "representation of Palestinian Arabs and Israelis"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Middle Eastern leaders Kemal Ataturk, David Ben-Gurion, and Yasir Arafat are best known for their support of",
        "correct_answer": "nationalism",
        "distractor1": "fascism",
        "distractor2": "colonialism",
        "distractor3": "communism"
    },
    {
        "question": " The time has come for you to go  Live where you like, but not among us... ",
        "correct_answer": "nationalism",
        "distractor1": "socialism",
        "distractor2": "absolutism",
        "distractor3": "humanitarianism"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 1990 s, the action by the Israeli Government that has most divided Israeli society has been the decision to",
        "correct_answer": "grant control of part of the West Bank and Gaza Strip to the Palestinians",
        "distractor1": "support the United States led Allied Coalition during the Persian Gulf War",
        "distractor2": "support the Camp David accords",
        "distractor3": "oppose Islamic fundamentalist rule in Iran"
    },
    {
        "question": "The response of the international community to Iraq s invasion of Kuwait in 1990 best illustrates the",
        "correct_answer": "effect of oil on world politics",
        "distractor1": "lack of cooperation between the major world powers",
        "distractor2": "global acceptance of imperialism",
        "distractor3": "ineffectiveness of United Nations peacekeeping forces"
    },
    {
        "question": "The statements below refer to changes in Afghanistan in the 1990 s.     The Taliban controls the government. ",
        "correct_answer": "Islamic fundamentalism",
        "distractor1": "Marxist ideology",
        "distractor2": "liberation theology",
        "distractor3": "constitutional reforms"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which conclusion is best supported by this cartoon?",
        "correct_answer": "Imprisonment of political dissidents rarely ends opposition to the government.",
        "distractor1": "The United Nations supports punishment for acts of civil disobedience.",
        "distractor2": "Better media coverage would prevent the imprisonment of protesters.",
        "distractor3": "Mistreatment of political prisoners often results in their acceptance of government policies."
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Republic of South Africa, the primary goal of the African National Congress (ANC) has been to",
        "correct_answer": "rule as the majority political party",
        "distractor1": "eliminate communist influence",
        "distractor2": "create a united Africa",
        "distractor3": "promote homeland areas for Blacks"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 1980 s, global concern for Blacks in the Republic of South Africa led many nations to",
        "correct_answer": "impose economic sanctions on South Africa",
        "distractor1": "demand that Whites return to their European homelands",
        "distractor2": "sent troops to South Africa",
        "distractor3": "support policies of Apartheid"
    },
    {
        "question": " The Very First Thing You Should Know About South African Stocks and Bonds     Two Leading Financial Institutions Show You Around South Africa s Banking World   ",
        "correct_answer": "a renewed interest in investing in South Africa s economy",
        "distractor1": "a continuation of the international trade sanctions imposed on South Africa in 1985",
        "distractor2": "the hazards associated with overseas economic investment",
        "distractor3": "a belief that the banks and the bond market in South Africa are inferior to those in Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "In which way has the end of apartheid had a positive economic effect on South Africa?",
        "correct_answer": "many foreign companies have resumed trading and investing in South Africa",
        "distractor1": "Black South African managers have increased industrial productivity throughout the nation",
        "distractor2": "the introduction of communism has led to a more equal distribution of income",
        "distractor3": "all profits of South Africa s industries are now reinvested out of the country"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best characterizes the period of apartheid in South Africa?",
        "correct_answer": "many racist ideas of the ruling minority were adopted into laws",
        "distractor1": "the majority of the population had the right to vote",
        "distractor2": "the Boers attempted to conquer Nigeria",
        "distractor3": "French was declared the official language of the nation"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Republic of South Africa, the slogans  Freedom in Our Lifetime  and  New South Africa  changed from promises to reality after",
        "correct_answer": "Nelson Mandela was elected President",
        "distractor1": "Frederik W. de Klerk took over the radical white police force",
        "distractor2": "Untied Nations troops occupied the Transvaal",
        "distractor3": "the majority of white South Africans returned to Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major problem currently facing the Republic of South Africa is the",
        "correct_answer": "struggle for power between different groups within South Africa s black majority",
        "distractor1": "continuation of attacks from neighboring Zimbabwe",
        "distractor2": "move toward the creation of a theocratic state",
        "distractor3": "continued international economic embargo against South Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since the end of apartheid in South Africa, what has been one of the major challenges to the current government?",
        "correct_answer": "resolving regional and ethnic rivalries",
        "distractor1": "establishing diplomatic relations with Europe",
        "distractor2": "guaranteeing religious freedom for all groups",
        "distractor3": "improving transportation throughout the country"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the main idea of this 1991 cartoon?",
        "correct_answer": "The economic differences between East and West Germany have limited the growth of the total German economy.",
        "distractor1": "The unification of Germany has been hurt by poor leadership in the country.",
        "distractor2": "East Germany's strong economy has strengthened a united Germany.",
        "distractor3": "Both East Germany and West Germany have contributed equally to the new economy of a reunified Germany."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the late 1980 s, the Soviet Union experienced internal unrest mainly as a result of",
        "correct_answer": "increased demands of minority ethnic groups",
        "distractor1": "widespread protests against involvement in Afghanistan",
        "distractor2": "a lack of raw materials and natural resources",
        "distractor3": "a failure to use modern technology in the military"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the presidency of Mikhail Gorbachev, which problem faced the Soviet Union?",
        "correct_answer": "ethnic minorities demanded the right of self-determination",
        "distractor1": "agricultural production grew faster than food consumption",
        "distractor2": "the nations of Eastern Europe insisted that the Soviet Union keep troops in Eastern Europe",
        "distractor3": "Western European nations refused to trade with the Soviet Union"
    },
    {
        "question": "Article 50 in accordance with the interests of the people and in order to strengthen and develop the socialist system, citizens of the USSR are guaranteed freedom of speech of the press, and of assembly, meetings, street processions and demonstrations.   Exercise of these political freedoms is ensured by putting public buildings, streets and squares at the disposal of the working people and their organizations, by broad dissemination of information, and by the opportunity to use the press, television, and radio. ",
        "correct_answer": "a constitutional guarantee may be limited by government actions",
        "distractor1": "constitutional rights guarantee a free society",
        "distractor2": "a national constitution always guarantees human rights",
        "distractor3": "a constitutional guarantee must be very specific in order to be effective"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980 s, Mikhail Gorbachev introduced Perestroika in the Soviet Union to",
        "correct_answer": "improve the economy and decentralize decision making",
        "distractor1": "abandon arms treaties with the United States and Western Europe",
        "distractor2": "tighten government controls over the communication media",
        "distractor3": "suppress the growing nationalist movements in Eastern Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "The revolt in Hungary (1956), the demonstrations in Czechoslovakia (1968), and the formation of solidarity in Poland (1980 s) are similar in that they",
        "correct_answer": "represented a challenge to communist leadership",
        "distractor1": "were movements in restore the power of the aristocracy",
        "distractor2": "were tolerated by the communist leaders, who accepted the need for change",
        "distractor3": "represented attempts to rid these countries of western ideas and influence"
    },
    {
        "question": "One result of the collapse of the Soviet Union has been that",
        "correct_answer": "ethnic violence has broken out in some regions",
        "distractor1": "some former republics have reorganized the Warsaw Pact",
        "distractor2": "an era of peace and stability has emerged in most of the former republics",
        "distractor3": "the republics have made an east transition to a market economy"
    },
    {
        "question": " Polish Communist Party Fails in Election Bid    Romanians Depose Communist Dictator   ",
        "correct_answer": "demands for democracy ended many totalitarian governments in Eastern Europe",
        "distractor1": "military buildups are continuing in Eastern Europe",
        "distractor2": "planned economies in Eastern Europe have become increasingly successful",
        "distractor3": "the Soviet Union stopped independence efforts in Eastern Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": " The Soviet Union Splits into 15 Republics    Yugoslavia Experiences Internal Conflict  ",
        "correct_answer": "the forces of nationalism can either divide of unite a nation",
        "distractor1": "communism remains an important force in Europe",
        "distractor2": "many Western European nations are experiencing civil war",
        "distractor3": "international sanctions strengthen a nation s ability to govern"
    },
    {
        "question": "The initial reaction of the Russian government to the fighting that broke out in Chechnya in the 1990 s demonstrated that Russia",
        "correct_answer": "is unwilling to grant independence to dissenting ethnic groups",
        "distractor1": "has little control over its arsenal of nuclear weapons",
        "distractor2": "will defend its remaining republics against foreign invasion",
        "distractor3": "favors reestablishing communism"
    },
    {
        "question": "In many Latin American nations, which group has most resisted social and economic changes since the end of World War II?",
        "correct_answer": "the military",
        "distractor1": "poor farmers",
        "distractor2": "union leaders",
        "distractor3": "the middle class"
    },
    {
        "question": "The main purpose of the Organization of American States (OAS) is to",
        "correct_answer": "provide a way to resolve regional problems peacefully",
        "distractor1": "integrate the economies of Latin American nations",
        "distractor2": "encourage United States military involvement in the region",
        "distractor3": "destroy the power of Colombian drug lords"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the last ten years, what has occurred in many of the nations of Latin America?",
        "correct_answer": "an increase in the number of popularly elected leaders",
        "distractor1": "successful communist revolutions",
        "distractor2": "a growing dependence on Cuba for economic support",
        "distractor3": "a return to their former colonial status"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which group has been a major force in calling for the protection of human rights in Central America during the 1980 s and 1990 s?",
        "correct_answer": "liberation theology clergy",
        "distractor1": "Caudillos",
        "distractor2": "military generals",
        "distractor3": "Landowners"
    },
    {
        "question": "Brazil s establishment of an equal partnership with foreign investors and Venezuela s control of its highly profitable oil industry are examples of",
        "correct_answer": "economic nationalism",
        "distractor1": "Neocolonialism",
        "distractor2": "new imperialism",
        "distractor3": "Fascism"
    },
    {
        "question": "At the present time, which is a major economic problem for many Latin American governments?",
        "correct_answer": "inability to pay foreign debts",
        "distractor1": "increased settlement in rural areas",
        "distractor2": "low rates of inflation",
        "distractor3": "lack of a chief executive"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which major economic problem has been faced by many Latin American nations throughout their histories?",
        "correct_answer": "lack of capital for industrial development",
        "distractor1": "declining birthrate",
        "distractor2": "widespread acceptance of Marxist economic policies",
        "distractor3": "lack of labor for factories"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 20th century, a major course of political problems in Latin American has been",
        "correct_answer": "widespread poverty",
        "distractor1": "a decrease in population",
        "distractor2": "the declining importance of international trade",
        "distractor3": "increasing social mobility"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which has been an important factor that has discouraged investment in the economic developments of many Latin American nations?",
        "correct_answer": "political instability",
        "distractor1": "lack of natural resources",
        "distractor2": "history of colonial dependence",
        "distractor3": "declining birthrate"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the Roman Catholic Church in most Latin American countries in the 1980 s?",
        "correct_answer": "the church has become active in social and human rights issues",
        "distractor1": "the activities of the church are controlled by the national governments",
        "distractor2": "the church has confined its activities to religious issues",
        "distractor3": "most people see the church as having little influence in daily life"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which type of government has resulted from the changing political trends in much of Latin America during the 1990 s?",
        "correct_answer": "democracy",
        "distractor1": "monarchy",
        "distractor2": "military juntas",
        "distractor3": "fascism"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major problem facing many Central American nations is that their nation s wealth is",
        "correct_answer": "controlled by a small group of landed elite",
        "distractor1": "generally invested in consumer industries",
        "distractor2": "distributed throughout the large middle class",
        "distractor3": "held mainly by government agencies"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 20th century, an economic weakness of many Central American nations has been",
        "correct_answer": "an overdependence on one or two cash crops for export",
        "distractor1": "a reliance on monsoons for water to irrigate crops",
        "distractor2": "chronic labor shortages caused by slow population growth",
        "distractor3": "excessive investment in foreign manufacturing industries"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since World War II, what action have many Latin American nations taken to improve their economies?",
        "correct_answer": "encouraging industrial development",
        "distractor1": "reinforcing traditional farming methods",
        "distractor2": "encouraging citizens to emigrate to other nations",
        "distractor3": "adopting protectionist policies"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Latin America during the 1960 s and 1970 s, which group became increasingly active in promoting human rights?",
        "correct_answer": "Roman Catholic clergy",
        "distractor1": "wealthy landholders",
        "distractor2": "successful industrialists",
        "distractor3": "military leaders"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which political trend exists in present-day Latin America?",
        "correct_answer": "Democracy is replacing dictatorship.",
        "distractor1": "Most countries are becoming military juntas.",
        "distractor2": "Communism is spreading throughout the region.",
        "distractor3": "Religious leaders are making government policy."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which conclusion about the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) can be drawn from this 1994 cartoon?",
        "correct_answer": "NATO did not react quickly enough to the crisis in Bosnia.",
        "distractor1": "Bosnia and NATO continue to disagree about the causes of the civil war.",
        "distractor2": "NATO's actions have allowed communism to take advantage of the destruction of Bosnia.",
        "distractor3": "The United States will probably withdraw from NATO as a result of the Bosnian crisis."
    },
    {
        "question": " Russia Takes Soviet Union Seat ",
        "correct_answer": "responds to changing political conditions",
        "distractor1": "is usually dominated by industrialized countries",
        "distractor2": "generally relies on the use of force to enforce its decisions",
        "distractor3": "permits developing nations to block the proposals of Westerns nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Recent events in the former nations of Czechoslovakia and Yugoslavia reflect a nationalist trend of",
        "correct_answer": "dividing nations along ethnic lines",
        "distractor1": "encouraging multiethnic cooperation",
        "distractor2": "uniting nations with similar interests",
        "distractor3": "supporting the development of a command economy"
    },
    {
        "question": "Disputes over India s control of Kashmir, Jammu, and Punjab are examples of the continuing problem of",
        "correct_answer": "territorial claims based on religion",
        "distractor1": "Chinese claims to this region",
        "distractor2": "terrorist actions by Serbian refugees",
        "distractor3": "the policy of nonalignment"
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason North Korea has been the focus of worldwide attention in the mid-1990 s is because of its",
        "correct_answer": "nuclear weapons development programs",
        "distractor1": "commitment to increasing political freedoms",
        "distractor2": "development of a strong and expanding economy",
        "distractor3": "efforts to revive communism in Eastern Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "The major goal of many minority groups, such as the Kurds, Tamils, and Sikhs, is to",
        "correct_answer": "obtain self-rule and economic control of a homeland",
        "distractor1": "establish a multicultural state",
        "distractor2": "install Christianity as the state religion",
        "distractor3": "acquire economic aid from the World Bank"
    },
    {
        "question": "Under the leadership of Fidel Castro, Cuba has become an example of",
        "correct_answer": "a communist government struggling to maintain power despite economic problems",
        "distractor1": "the success of democracy in improving conditions in a developing nation",
        "distractor2": "a nation in which the efforts of the United Nations has improved human rights",
        "distractor3": "the successful reform of agriculture from single-crop to multicrop production"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since the end of the Cold War, Cuba has experienced",
        "correct_answer": "the loss of a major source of its foreign financial support",
        "distractor1": "increased economic growth from expanded trade",
        "distractor2": "expanded political influence in Latin American affairs",
        "distractor3": "greater independence from Communist China"
    },
    {
        "question": "In France, a person drinks coffee imported from Brazil, works at a computer made in Japan, and uses gasoline from Saudi Arabia in a German automobile.  This situation illustrates the concept of",
        "correct_answer": "interdependence",
        "distractor1": "empathy",
        "distractor2": "scarcity",
        "distractor3": "world citizenship"
    },
    {
        "question": "Japan sells cars to the United States, the United States exports high technology to Saudi Arabia, and Saudi Arabia exports oil to Japan.  Which is a valid conclusion that can be drawn from this statement?",
        "correct_answer": "the nations of the world are economically interdependent",
        "distractor1": "Saudi Arabia controls most of the world's natural resources",
        "distractor2": "The United States is the world's leading exporter",
        "distractor3": "most nations of the world specialize in one export"
    },
    {
        "question": "Global problems of uneven economic development, environmental pollution, and hunger reflect the need for",
        "correct_answer": "increased international cooperation",
        "distractor1": "a return to policies of economic nationalism",
        "distractor2": "increased military spending by all nations",
        "distractor3": "a reduction in foreign aid provided by industrialized nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Middle East is a global importance today because it",
        "correct_answer": "provides much of the petroleum used by industrial nations",
        "distractor1": "has become a model of economic and political equality",
        "distractor2": "allows major European powers to retain their spheres of influence",
        "distractor3": "remains a primary source of uranium"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major purpose of the Organization of African Unity (OAU), the Organization of American States (OAS), and the European Union (EU) is to",
        "correct_answer": "encourage political and economic cooperation between member nations",
        "distractor1": "end colonialism in member nations",
        "distractor2": "control overpopulation in member nations",
        "distractor3": "provide military assistance to member nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the past decade, Japanese automobile manufacturers have sought to improve Japanese-American trade relations by",
        "correct_answer": "building an increasing number of Japanese automobiles in the United States",
        "distractor1": "drastically lowering the price of Japanese automobiles for American consumers",
        "distractor2": "allowing an unlimited number of American automobiles to be sold in Japan",
        "distractor3": "importing most spare parts from Mexico"
    },
    {
        "question": "In recent years, a major success of the European Union (EU) has been the",
        "correct_answer": "elimination of trade barriers",
        "distractor1": "creation of a single military force",
        "distractor2": "rejection of national sovereignty",
        "distractor3": "adoption of a single language"
    },
    {
        "question": "The major reason the Mexican Government strongly supported the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) was that this agreement would",
        "correct_answer": "promote investment and economic growth in Mexico",
        "distractor1": "raise tariffs on United States products entering Mexico",
        "distractor2": "reduce Mexico s economic dependence on Europe",
        "distractor3": "stimulate trade between Asia and Latin America"
    },
    {
        "question": "Within the past decade, the decision of the United States Government to grant China  most favored nation  status was important to China because this decision",
        "correct_answer": "increased China s ability to trade with the United States",
        "distractor1": "allowed China to join the Southeast Treaty Organization (SEATO)",
        "distractor2": "helped protect China from a possible Japanese invasion",
        "distractor3": "eliminated Russian influence in East Asia"
    },
    {
        "question": "Modern Japan must trade to maintain its industry and living standard because Japan has",
        "correct_answer": "few mineral resources",
        "distractor1": "a limited amount of investment capital",
        "distractor2": "little access to the sea",
        "distractor3": "a lack of communication systems"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which action will help slow the trend indicated by the graph?",
        "correct_answer": "using alternative energy sources",
        "distractor1": "expanding Green Revolution technology",
        "distractor2": "increasing industrialization in developing nations",
        "distractor3": "lowering worldwide oil prices"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which conclusion can be drawn from the information in the chart?",
        "correct_answer": "The nations with relatively low birthrates have relatively high per capita incomes.",
        "distractor1": "Developing countries are instituting programs to limit the growth of their populations.",
        "distractor2": "Infant mortality is a greater problem in Africa than in Asia.",
        "distractor3": "The national birthrate is determined by many different factors."
    },
    {
        "question": "In many Latin American nations, reliance on the production of a single cash crop has led to",
        "correct_answer": "economic dependence on other nations",
        "distractor1": "rapid repayment of foreign loans",
        "distractor2": "a high per capita Gross National Product",
        "distractor3": "development of a strong industrial economy"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which fact about China has been the cause of the other three?",
        "correct_answer": "China s population exceeds one billion",
        "distractor1": "the economy of China has trouble providing for all the needs of the people",
        "distractor2": "the Chinese government has set limits on the number of children families may have",
        "distractor3": "Chinese cities have a severe shortage of housing"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since the collapse of the Soviet Union in the early 1990 s, Russia has attempted to build an economic system based on",
        "correct_answer": "free-market a system",
        "distractor1": "a return to feudalism",
        "distractor2": "the ideas of Marx and Lenin",
        "distractor3": "the writings of Mao Zedong"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which conclusion is valid concerning the food shortages some nations of Africa and Asia during the 1970 s and 1980 s?",
        "correct_answer": "too few people in Africa and Asia are involved in food production",
        "distractor1": "misuse of the land has destroyed many rich food-producing regions",
        "distractor2": "acid rain has been the major cause of crop failures",
        "distractor3": "European nations stopped shipping food to these regions"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is best supported by the data in the graph?",
        "correct_answer": "Belize and Costa Rica are meeting the water needs of their urban population.",
        "distractor1": "The urban areas of Honduras and Panama require the largest supply of water in Central America.",
        "distractor2": "Urban water supplies are declining in many Central American countries.",
        "distractor3": "Most Central American countries experienced a decrease in urban population between 1980 and 1988."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Mexico and India, the Green Revolution has been successful because it has",
        "correct_answer": "increased agricultural productivity",
        "distractor1": "promoted democratic reform",
        "distractor2": "introduced western culture and values",
        "distractor3": "established economic equality among the people"
    },
    {
        "question": "The major goal of the Green Revolution has been to",
        "correct_answer": "increase agricultural output",
        "distractor1": "decrease the use of modern farm machinery",
        "distractor2": "decrease population growth",
        "distractor3": "increase the number of traditional farms"
    },
    {
        "question": "The term ?Green Revolution? is used to describe the",
        "correct_answer": "development of new types of grains and new methods of growing them",
        "distractor1": "tensions between developing and developed nations",
        "distractor2": "heavy reliance on manual labor in agriculture",
        "distractor3": "protests against environmental destruction caused by industry"
    },
    {
        "question": "The main goal of the Green Revolution was to",
        "correct_answer": "solve chronic food shortages through the use of technology",
        "distractor1": "prevent further destruction of the world?s rain forests",
        "distractor2": "expand the economies of developing nations with foreign investment",
        "distractor3": "insure that foreign aid was received by people with the greatest need"
    },
    {
        "question": "A study of the accident at the Chernobyl nuclear power plant in the Soviet Union and of severe air pollution in Mexico would lead to the conclusion that",
        "correct_answer": "technology can cause problems throughout the world",
        "distractor1": "international trade is more profitable than domestic commerce",
        "distractor2": "modern science cannot solve most political problems",
        "distractor3": "agricultural nations have caused major world environmental problems"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major environmental problem affecting Latin America, Sub-Saharan Africa, and Southeast Asia has been",
        "correct_answer": "Deforestation",
        "distractor1": "air pollution",
        "distractor2": "disposal of nuclear waste",
        "distractor3": "acid rain"
    },
    {
        "question": "Many scientist believe that the ?greenhouse effect? is the result of",
        "correct_answer": "using large amounts of gasoline, oil, and coal in developed nations",
        "distractor1": "overgrazing on land in developing nations",
        "distractor2": "testing nuclear weapons in violation of the Nuclear Test Ban Treaty",
        "distractor3": "using natural fertilizers to increase crop production"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major factor contributing to the destruction of the Amazon rain forests is the",
        "correct_answer": "need for more farmland",
        "distractor1": "movement of people from rural to urban areas",
        "distractor2": "attempt of native peoples to end illegal drug traffic",
        "distractor3": "spread of Christianity"
    },
    {
        "question": "The amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere has increased in recent years.  Environmentalists suggest this change is a direct result of the",
        "correct_answer": "overcutting of forests and the increased use of fossil fuels",
        "distractor1": "improper storage of solid and nuclear waste",
        "distractor2": "dumping of inorganic material into lakes and rivers",
        "distractor3": "use of herbicides and toxic substances such as asbestos and DDT"
    },
    {
        "question": "In developing countries, the use of wood, charcoal, and dung as major sources of energy has created an increase in",
        "correct_answer": "deforestation and other environmental problems",
        "distractor1": "economic dependence on industrialized nations",
        "distractor2": "sales an profits for international oil corporations",
        "distractor3": "nuclear waste products"
    },
    {
        "question": "A negative impact of the use of modern technology is that",
        "correct_answer": "levels of air and water pollution often increase",
        "distractor1": "economic opportunities are frequently limited",
        "distractor2": "contacts with other cultures decrease",
        "distractor3": "international trade is limited"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Latin America, the deforestation of the Amazon rain forest has led to",
        "correct_answer": "environmental dangers",
        "distractor1": "the maintenance of a traditional way of life",
        "distractor2": "the discovery of new medicines",
        "distractor3": "overpopulation in rural regions"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 1980?s, the governments of both Brazil and Malaysia supported the cutting of timber in their rain forests as a means of",
        "correct_answer": "achieving economic prosperity",
        "distractor1": "increasing the national debt",
        "distractor2": "controlling rebellions of indigenous peoples",
        "distractor3": "preventing exploitation by imperialist nations"
    },
    {
        "question": " ?What harms the victim most is not the cruelty of the oppressor, but the silence of the bystander.?",
        "correct_answer": "nations of the world must always condemn human rights violations whenever they occur",
        "distractor1": "totalitarian governments generally support civil liberties",
        "distractor2": "ethnic cleansing is not an issue to be addressed by the United Nations",
        "distractor3": "demonstrations against human rights violations are of limited value"
    },
    {
        "question": "?United States Adopts Economic Sanctions Against South Africa?  ?Chinese Dissidents Imprisoned After Student Protest? ",
        "correct_answer": "human rights violation",
        "distractor1": "imperialist expansion",
        "distractor2": "peasant revolts",
        "distractor3": "isolationist policies"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Tiananmen Square massacre in China was a reaction to",
        "correct_answer": "student demands for greater individual rights and freedom of expression",
        "distractor1": "Deng Xiaoping?s plan to revive the Cultural Revolution",
        "distractor2": "China?s decision to seek Western investors",
        "distractor3": "Great Britain?s decision to return Hong Kong to China"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes a result of the student demonstrations in Beijing?s Tiananmen Square in 1989?",
        "correct_answer": "the government further restricted freedom of expression in China",
        "distractor1": "prodemocracy protestors were successful in achieving their goals",
        "distractor2": "a state-controlled education program was begun",
        "distractor3": "collectivization programs were started in China"
    },
    {
        "question": "A common problem facing most Latin American and Eastern European nations today is that these nations",
        "correct_answer": "are struggling with a transition to democracy after experiencing years of dictatorial rule",
        "distractor1": "have little arable land and few mineral resources with which to improve their economies",
        "distractor2": "have chosen not to belong to international organizations",
        "distractor3": "are experiencing major problems with the flood of illegal immigrants entering their nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Today, human rights violations most often occur in nations in which",
        "correct_answer": "leaders have absolute control",
        "distractor1": "freedom of the press exists",
        "distractor2": "government is limited by law",
        "distractor3": "government has a multiparty system"
    },
    {
        "question": "An analysis of the Chinese student demonstrations in Tiananmen Square in 1989 would show that",
        "correct_answer": "totalitarian governments frequently survive by the use of force",
        "distractor1": "communist governments continue to have little control over the actions of their citizens",
        "distractor2": "peaceful demonstrations often succeed in achieving democratic reforms",
        "distractor3": "negative global reaction sometimes leads to economic decline"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Ancient Kingdom of Mali and in the Roman Republic, an important feature of life was the development of",
        "correct_answer": "codified laws",
        "distractor1": "social and political equality",
        "distractor2": "the Islamic religion",
        "distractor3": "agricultural communes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best explains the periods of the Gupta Empire of India, the Golden Age of Greece, and the Renaissance in Italy?",
        "correct_answer": "a combination of wealth and a time of relative peace often leads to cultural achievement",
        "distractor1": "the winning of a war often inspires scientific and artistic achievement",
        "distractor2": "a dictatorship usually encourages cultural growth and development",
        "distractor3": "periods of censorship are needed for a nation to achieve cultural and scientific greatness"
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which Medieval European society, Latin American colonial society, and society in Imperial China were similar is that each",
        "correct_answer": "was organized according to a rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "placed great value on public education",
        "distractor2": "experienced a surplus of skilled labor",
        "distractor3": "de-emphasized the role of religion"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which idea did Napoleon Bonaparte, Sun Yat-Sen, and Simone Bolivar have in common?",
        "correct_answer": "nationalism",
        "distractor1": "divine right",
        "distractor2": "totalitarianism",
        "distractor3": "nonviolence"
    },
    {
        "question": "Eighteenth-century Russia and nineteenth-century Japan were similar in that both countries",
        "correct_answer": "began the process of modernization after a long period of isolation",
        "distractor1": "developed democratic governments after years under absolute monarchies",
        "distractor2": "refused to accept western technological ideas",
        "distractor3": "adopted socialist economic systems after capitalism had failed"
    },
    {
        "question": "Until the 1500 s, China and Japan were similar in that both",
        "correct_answer": "had little contact with Western European nations",
        "distractor1": "were invaded by the Mongols",
        "distractor2": "welcomed Christian Missionaries",
        "distractor3": "were developing democratic traditions"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Middle Ages, Europeans did not eat potatoes or corn because these vegetables",
        "correct_answer": "had not yet been introduced to Europe from the New World",
        "distractor1": "were forbidden by the Catholic Church for religious reasons",
        "distractor2": "were believed to be poisonous",
        "distractor3": "were too expensive to import from China"
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which Medieval European society, Latin American colonial society, and society in Imperial China were similar is that each",
        "correct_answer": "was organized according to a rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "placed great value on public education",
        "distractor2": "experienced a surplus of skilled labor",
        "distractor3": "de-emphasized the role of religion"
    },
    {
        "question": "The societies of traditional China, Feudal Japan, and Czarist Russia were all characterized by",
        "correct_answer": "a rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "much interaction with other cultures",
        "distractor2": "great economic change",
        "distractor3": "rapidly changing social values"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between the decline of the Roman Empire and the fall of the Manchu Dynasty was that both initially led to",
        "correct_answer": "political chaos and decentralization of government",
        "distractor1": "improved economic conditions",
        "distractor2": "democratically elected governments",
        "distractor3": "major accomplishments in art, science, and technology"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Japanese feudal system and the Hindu caste system are similar in that both systems",
        "correct_answer": "developed a rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "promoted social mobility",
        "distractor2": "encouraged the people to take part in government",
        "distractor3": "resulted in economic opportunities for the lower classes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Eighteenth-century Russia and nineteenth-century Japan were similar in that both countries",
        "correct_answer": "began the process of modernization after a long period of isolation",
        "distractor1": "developed democratic governments after years under absolute monarchies",
        "distractor2": "refused to accept western technological ideas",
        "distractor3": "adopted socialist economic systems after capitalism had failed"
    },
    {
        "question": "Changes in Russia under Peter the Great were most similar to changes that occurred in",
        "correct_answer": "Japan during the Meiji Restoration",
        "distractor1": "China before the Opium War",
        "distractor2": "Iran after the fall of Shah Pahlevi",
        "distractor3": "France during the feudal period"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Tamils in Sri Lanka, the Sikhs in India, and the Zulus in South Africa have all attempted to",
        "correct_answer": "achieve political separatism",
        "distractor1": "establish colonies in Asia",
        "distractor2": "practice passive resistance",
        "distractor3": "encourage mercantilism"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was characteristic of France under Napoleon s rule and Germany under Hitler s rule?",
        "correct_answer": "authoritarian control and a strong sense of nationalism prevailed",
        "distractor1": "democratic ideas and diversity were encouraged",
        "distractor2": "peaceful relations with neighboring countries wee fostered",
        "distractor3": "artistic and literary freedom flourished"
    },
    {
        "question": "A study of the French Revolution and the Russian Revolution of 1917 would lead to the conclusion that",
        "correct_answer": "control of revolutions often shifts from moderates to radicals",
        "distractor1": "revolutions only occur when a majority of citizens become directly involved",
        "distractor2": "university students are most often responsible for starting revolutions",
        "distractor3": "revolutions seldom result in long-term changes"
    },
    {
        "question": "The French Revolution, the Bolshevik Revolution in Russia, and the Communist Revolution in China were similar in that all three",
        "correct_answer": "were influenced by the peasants  desire for more land",
        "distractor1": "brought about few political changes",
        "distractor2": "were inspired by Marxism",
        "distractor3": "were supported primarily by the nobility"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ancient Greek city-state of Sparta and the Soviet Union under Stalin were similar in that both societies",
        "correct_answer": "were powerful military states",
        "distractor1": "were primarily concerned with the health of their people",
        "distractor2": "granted universal suffrage to their people",
        "distractor3": "placed great emphasis on literature and the arts"
    },
    {
        "question": "In China, the building of the Great Wall, the use of the tribute system, and the government s support of the Boxer Rebellion are examples of attempts by different dynasties to limit",
        "correct_answer": "foreign influence",
        "distractor1": "nationalism",
        "distractor2": "communist expansion",
        "distractor3": "industrialization"
    },
    {
        "question": "The French Revolution of 1789 and the Cuban Revolution of 1959 were similar in that both were caused primarily by the",
        "correct_answer": "failure of the government to meet the needs of the people",
        "distractor1": "desire of the people to be free from foreign rule",
        "distractor2": "pressure of religious leaders for government reform",
        "distractor3": "ambition of the upper class to attain wealth and property"
    },
    {
        "question": "The philosophies of Confucius and Mao Zedong both emphasized",
        "correct_answer": "group rather than individual welfare",
        "distractor1": "individual rather than cooperative gain",
        "distractor2": "industry rather than agriculture",
        "distractor3": "religious values rather than economic profits"
    },
    {
        "question": "Japan during the Meiji Restoration was similar to Japan after World War II in that during these periods Japan",
        "correct_answer": "underwent political reform and economic expansion",
        "distractor1": "pursued a foreign policy of isolationism and limited political freedoms",
        "distractor2": "reduced the powers of the Emperor and the nobility",
        "distractor3": "was ruled by dictators and the military"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since the late 1940 s, India, Northern Ireland, and Israel have faced the common problem of",
        "correct_answer": "continued violent confrontations between different religious groups",
        "distractor1": "adjusting to a post-Communist political and economic system",
        "distractor2": "economic depression as a result of rapid industrialization",
        "distractor3": "uncertainty of their acceptance by the European Community"
    },
    {
        "question": "The events that led to the overthrow of Czar Nicholas II in 1917 and to the forced resignation of Mikhail Gorbachev in 1991 show that",
        "correct_answer": "economic crises often lead to political change",
        "distractor1": "Russian absolutism continued into the 1990 s",
        "distractor2": "international conflicts often strengthen the power of leaders",
        "distractor3": "Russia is an ethnically unified nation"
    },
    {
        "question": "Events in both Eastern Europe in the early 1900 s and in the Soviet Union in the late 1980 s were mainly the result of",
        "correct_answer": "challenges by ethnic groups desiring independence",
        "distractor1": "movements toward the repression of individual rights",
        "distractor2": "declines in the use of advanced technology",
        "distractor3": "the influence of religion on government"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the late 1980 s and early 1990 s, the Soviet Union experienced ethnic tensions that were most similar to those experienced by",
        "correct_answer": "Austria-Hungary in the late 19th century",
        "distractor1": "Japan in the early 17th century",
        "distractor2": "Spain in the mid-18th century",
        "distractor3": "Cuba in the late 20th century"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Holocaust in Europe and the actions of the Khmer Rouge in Kampuchea (Cambodia) were similar in that they were examples of",
        "correct_answer": "Genocide",
        "distractor1": "Interdependence",
        "distractor2": "Segregation",
        "distractor3": "Empathy"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between Mao Zedong and Fidel Castro is that they",
        "correct_answer": "led revolutionary movements that established communist governments",
        "distractor1": "achieved their goals through the use of peaceful resistance",
        "distractor2": "worked to protect citizens  rights to freedom of expression",
        "distractor3": "considered capitalism to be the best economic system"
    },
    {
        "question": " Germany Will Make Reparations For WWI    OPEC Supports Oil Embargo Against Western Nations  ",
        "correct_answer": "economic measures are often designed to achieve political goals",
        "distractor1": "communism as an economic system has failed",
        "distractor2": "economic policies are often formulated to encourage investment",
        "distractor3": "nationalism plays a small role in economic decisionmaking"
    },
    {
        "question": "A study of the policy of  ethnic cleansing  in Bosnia and the Holocaust in Europe would suggest that",
        "correct_answer": "anti-Semitism and ethnic hatred remain powerful forces in the 20th century",
        "distractor1": "world opinion is effective in stopping genocide",
        "distractor2": "countries generally use reason and negotiation in dealing with important ethnic issues",
        "distractor3": "military leaders cannot be held responsible for acts committed during wartime"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor has most limited the development of national unity in India, Lebanon, and Bosnia-Herzegovina?",
        "correct_answer": "religious and ethnic differences",
        "distractor1": "lack of natural resources",
        "distractor2": "inability to end colonialism",
        "distractor3": "rapid growth of industry"
    },
    {
        "question": "Both the Chinese Mandate of Heaven and the Japanese belief that the Emperor descends from the Sun Goddess are similar to the",
        "correct_answer": "divine right theory of the French monarchy",
        "distractor1": " master race  theory of Adolf Hitler s Third Reich",
        "distractor2": "natural rights theory of the Age of Reason",
        "distractor3": "Marxist theory of a workers  revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which the caste system and apartheid were similar is that both",
        "correct_answer": "supported a rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "described specific religious practices and beliefs",
        "distractor2": "were created by British colonial governments",
        "distractor3": "gave power to the lower classes in their respective societies"
    },
    {
        "question": "Within their respective nations, both Ho Chi Minh and Fidel Castro achieved their goals by",
        "correct_answer": "using armed conflict to bring a communist government to power",
        "distractor1": "seeking aid and support from the European Union",
        "distractor2": "following a policy of nonalignment",
        "distractor3": "working to build a capitalist system"
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which the Meiji Restoration in Japan and the Golden Age of India are similar is that in each region these events led to",
        "correct_answer": "periods of rapid change",
        "distractor1": "the persecution of minority peoples",
        "distractor2": "the rise of feudalism as the dominant political system",
        "distractor3": "governments ruled by absolute monarchs"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Sepoy Rebellion in India and the Boxer Rebellion in China were similar in that both were",
        "correct_answer": "revolts against foreign influence",
        "distractor1": "attempts to improve foreign trade",
        "distractor2": "nonviolent resistance efforts",
        "distractor3": "revolutions against traditional monarchs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Suleiman held complete religious and political power.  Charles I stormed the English Parliament. ",
        "correct_answer": "absolutism",
        "distractor1": "scientific theory",
        "distractor2": "natural rights",
        "distractor3": "mercantilism"
    },
    {
        "question": "What would a study of the recent civil wars in Cambodia, Bosnia-Herzegovina, and Rwanda show about these conflicts?",
        "correct_answer": "Genocide was used as a political and military tactic.",
        "distractor1": "Ethnic conflict was not a factor in the late 20th century.",
        "distractor2": "The United Nations was successful in resolving these disputes.",
        "distractor3": "Civilians were not affected by these disputes."
    },
    {
        "question": "A similarity of the goals of Nelson Mandela and Mohandas Gandhi is that both leaders wanted to",
        "correct_answer": "secure political power for the majority of the people",
        "distractor1": "encourage a greater degree of industrialization",
        "distractor2": "improve the economy by expanding governmental control",
        "distractor3": "gain independence from the Soviet Union"
    },
    {
        "question": " Statement 1:   This organization is created for the purpose of realizing the national ideal:",
        "correct_answer": "Self-determination of the people is an important goal.",
        "distractor1": "War is a means of achieving national policies.",
        "distractor2": "Industrial growth is critical to a country s prosperity.",
        "distractor3": "Social class differences are the source of all conflicts."
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which Sim n Bol var, Jomo Kenyatta, and Ho Chi Minh are similar is that each leader",
        "correct_answer": "sought independence from colonial rule",
        "distractor1": "ruled during a period of peace and prosperity",
        "distractor2": "demanded human rights for all citizens",
        "distractor3": "established a totalitarian government"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which document is an example of a primary source?",
        "correct_answer": "the diary of a survivor of a Nazi death camp",
        "distractor1": "a textbook on Russian history",
        "distractor2": "an encyclopedia article on religions of the Middle East",
        "distractor3": "a novel on the Age of Exploration"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which historical events are in the correct chronological order?",
        "correct_answer": "Neolithic Revolution -> Roman Empire -> Crusades -> Renaissance",
        "distractor1": "Crusades -> Renaissance -> Neolithic Revolution -> Roman Empire",
        "distractor2": "Roman Empire -> Neolithic Revolution -> Crusades -> Renaissance",
        "distractor3": "Renaissance ->Neolithic Revolution -> Crusades -> Roman Empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "  The United Nations Declaration of Human Rights",
        "correct_answer": "primary sources",
        "distractor1": "secondary sources",
        "distractor2": "examples of oral traditions",
        "distractor3": "statements of different religious beliefs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best explains why most of the population of the people s Republic of China live in the eastern third of the nation?  ",
        "correct_answer": "best agricultural land is in the East",
        "distractor1": "largest forests are in the East",
        "distractor2": "best fishing areas are off the eastern coast",
        "distractor3": "largest oil deposits are in the East"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is an accurate statement about Japan s natural resources?",
        "correct_answer": "Japan has extensively used the seas for fishing",
        "distractor1": "large reserves of petroleum are located in the northern part of Japan",
        "distractor2": "Japan has large fertile plains suitable for growing grain",
        "distractor3": "large coal and iron-ore deposits are located in the mountain region"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Japan, a major economic problem has been the lack of",
        "correct_answer": "natural resources",
        "distractor1": "investment capital",
        "distractor2": "skilled labor",
        "distractor3": "experienced management"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes an effect that geography has had on Japan?",
        "correct_answer": "the lack of important natural resources has led Japan to depend on trade with other nations",
        "distractor1": "Japan s smooth coastline has prevented the development of a fishing industry",
        "distractor2": "Japan s large plains have made wheat growing a primary industry",
        "distractor3": "the location of Japan has encouraged great ethnic diversity within the nation"
    },
    {
        "question": "Both Japan and Indonesia are made up of a chain of islands called",
        "correct_answer": "an archipelago",
        "distractor1": "a peninsula",
        "distractor2": "a delta",
        "distractor3": "an atoll"
    },
    {
        "question": "The term  Latin America  most accurately refers to the",
        "correct_answer": "areas of the Western Hemisphere south of the United States",
        "distractor1": "countries that belong to the Organization of American States",
        "distractor2": "continents of North and South America",
        "distractor3": "countries that have close economic ties with Spain"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which generalization about geography of Latin America is accurate?",
        "correct_answer": "great variations in latitude and landforms resulted in a diversity of climates",
        "distractor1": "geographic features prevented foreign imperialism",
        "distractor2": "harsh climatic conditions have prevented the development of large-scale agriculture",
        "distractor3": "the lack of geographic barriers facilitated the development of transportation and communication systems"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which geographic factor has had the most influence on Poland's historical and cultural development?",
        "correct_answer": "location on the great European Plain",
        "distractor1": "a severe climate",
        "distractor2": "vast deposits of oil",
        "distractor3": "a rugged coastline"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these nations is located closet to the Philippines, Malaysia, and Indonesia?",
        "correct_answer": "Vietnam",
        "distractor1": "Korea",
        "distractor2": "Somalia",
        "distractor3": "Pakistan"
    },
    {
        "question": "One effect that mountain ranges, rain forests, and river systems have had on Latin America has been to",
        "correct_answer": "limit the development of transportation and communication systems",
        "distractor1": "encourage cultural diffusion",
        "distractor2": "permit the nations of the area to use a single form of government",
        "distractor3": "allow the development of large amounts of arable land"
    },
    {
        "question": "In addition to providing water for Indian agriculture, the Ganges River remains important to India because it is",
        "correct_answer": "a sacred river for the Hindu population",
        "distractor1": "the only source of Indian hydroelectric power",
        "distractor2": "the birthplace of Hindu culture",
        "distractor3": "an unofficial boundary between the Hindus and Muslims"
    },
    {
        "question": "An effect of a mountainous topography on Inca and Chinese civilizations was the development of",
        "correct_answer": "terrace farming",
        "distractor1": "industrialization",
        "distractor2": "single-crop economy",
        "distractor3": "desalinization projects"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major effect of geography on Japan is that the",
        "correct_answer": "scarcity of natural resources has forced Japan to obtain raw materials from other nations",
        "distractor1": "export of oil has helped Japan maintain a favorable balance of trade",
        "distractor2": "fertile plains have enabled Japan to keep food prices low",
        "distractor3": "mountains have prevented invasions obey foreign nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which geographic factor has most strongly influenced Russia s foreign policies and economic development?",
        "correct_answer": "limited access to warm-water ports",
        "distractor1": "lack of natural resources",
        "distractor2": "vast desert regions",
        "distractor3": "extensive mountain ranges"
    },
    {
        "question": "Many people in Southeast Asia hope for the timely arrival of the summer monsoons each year because",
        "correct_answer": "little rain has fallen for many months",
        "distractor1": "floods are the only way to water their farmlands",
        "distractor2": "daily temperatures often reach 100 degrees Fahrenheit",
        "distractor3": "oases provide water for nomadic herders"
    },
    {
        "question": "A topographical map would most likely be used to",
        "correct_answer": "estimate the elevation of Bangkok, Thailand",
        "distractor1": "identify the major agricultural products of Egypt",
        "distractor2": "determine the population of Beijing, China",
        "distractor3": "count the number of provinces in India"
    },
    {
        "question": "On a map of the world, Asia is to Japan as Europe is to",
        "correct_answer": "Great Britain",
        "distractor1": "the Netherlands",
        "distractor2": "Austria",
        "distractor3": "Italy"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Russian steppe is most similar in topography to the",
        "correct_answer": "savannas in Africa",
        "distractor1": "mountains in Switzerland",
        "distractor2": "deserts in the Middle East",
        "distractor3": "rainforests in South America"
    },
    {
        "question": "Areas of Africa and parts of Siberia in Russia are often said to be gems-in-the-rough because they have",
        "correct_answer": "many undeveloped natural resources",
        "distractor1": "extensive tracts of permanently frozen land",
        "distractor2": "well-developed coastal fishing industries",
        "distractor3": "decreasing populations"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Africa, an effect of topography and climate has been to",
        "correct_answer": "promote the growth of diverse societies",
        "distractor1": "encourage rapid industrialization of the interior",
        "distractor2": "prevent the development of kingdoms",
        "distractor3": "promote large-scale trade between African and Asia"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Suez Canal, the Strait of Hormuz, and the Strait of Gibraltar are important because they",
        "correct_answer": "control access to vital trade routes",
        "distractor1": "prevent attacks on bordering nations",
        "distractor2": "limit Russian access to warm-water points",
        "distractor3": "prohibit the movement of ships carrying nuclear weapons"
    },
    {
        "question": "Geographic diversity in the Middle East has contributed to",
        "correct_answer": "unequal standards of living",
        "distractor1": "a common economic system",
        "distractor2": "similar political systems",
        "distractor3": "military alliances with Japan"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Suez Canal, the Panama Canal, and the Straits of the Dardanelles are similar because they",
        "correct_answer": "are strategic waterways that have been the center of conflicts",
        "distractor1": "was part of the French colonial empire",
        "distractor2": "are located in regions that are rich in natural resources",
        "distractor3": "prohibit the movement of ships carrying nuclear weapons"
    },
    {
        "question": "The map shows that the",
        "correct_answer": "distribution of income in China is unequal",
        "distractor1": "economies of all the regions of China are developing at the same rate",
        "distractor2": "economies of the interior provinces of China are developing faster than those of the coastal provinces",
        "distractor3": "economic development in China is dependent upon the cash crops of Xinjiang and Tibet"
    },
    {
        "question": "One factor that accounted for Chinese influence on traditional Japanese culture was the",
        "correct_answer": "geographic location of the countries",
        "distractor1": "continuous warfare between the countries",
        "distractor2": "refusal of western nations to trade with Japan",
        "distractor3": "annexation of Japan into the Chinese Empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "Throughout the 1800 s, Russia was interested in acquiring Turkey mainly because Russia wanted",
        "correct_answer": "access to the Mediterranean Sea",
        "distractor1": "to maintain peace in the Middle East",
        "distractor2": "to reestablish the Byzantine Empire",
        "distractor3": "the rich farmland of the Anatolian Plateau"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which geographic factor has contributed most to the economic growth of Japan, Egypt, and Great Britain?",
        "correct_answer": "access to important waterways",
        "distractor1": "variety of natural resources",
        "distractor2": "reliable amount of rainfall",
        "distractor3": "abundance of arable land"
    },
    {
        "question": "In which way have the Andes Mountains and the Amazon rain forest affected the development of Latin America?",
        "correct_answer": "increasing cultural diversity",
        "distractor1": "promoting international unity",
        "distractor2": "encouraging trade agreements",
        "distractor3": "strengthening political alliances"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which geographic factor has helped China remain isolated for many centuries?",
        "correct_answer": "northern and western mountain ranges",
        "distractor1": "many natural harbors",
        "distractor2": "navigable river systems",
        "distractor3": "severe climate"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes an impact of topography on eastern Europe?",
        "correct_answer": "Many different languages, religions, and customs developed.",
        "distractor1": "A Russian czar ruled the area as a single empire.",
        "distractor2": "An extensive single-crop agricultural system emerged.",
        "distractor3": "Neighbors who were more powerful could not invade the region."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which geographic factor was most important to the development of the early river valley civilizations?",
        "correct_answer": "fertile soils",
        "distractor1": "high mountains",
        "distractor2": "vast deserts",
        "distractor3": "smooth coastlines"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor contributes most to the recurring food shortages in Africa?",
        "correct_answer": "poor distribution of agricultural products",
        "distractor1": "extensive river systems",
        "distractor2": "location between two major oceans",
        "distractor3": "rainforest environment"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which condition is a major obstacle to economic development in the Middle East and Northern Africa",
        "correct_answer": "scarcity of water resources",
        "distractor1": "use of strip mining to obtain minerals",
        "distractor2": "reliance on capitalist economic systems",
        "distractor3": "lack of access to world markets"
    },
    {
        "question": "Singapore and Hong Kong have become major economic powers by taking advantage of their",
        "correct_answer": "favorable location on international trade routes",
        "distractor1": "abundant mineral resources",
        "distractor2": "imported cheap labor from Japan",
        "distractor3": "profits from agricultural surpluses"
    },
    {
        "question": "Throughout the 1800 s, Russia was interested in acquiring Turkey mainly because Russia wanted",
        "correct_answer": "access to the Mediterranean Sea",
        "distractor1": "to maintain peace in the Middle East",
        "distractor2": "to reestablish the Byzantine Empire",
        "distractor3": "the rich farmland of the Anatolian Plateau"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which conclusion can be drawn from the information in the chart?",
        "correct_answer": "The nations with relatively low birthrates have relatively high per capita incomes.",
        "distractor1": "Developing countries are instituting programs to limit the growth of their populations.",
        "distractor2": "Infant mortality is a greater problem in Africa than in Asia.",
        "distractor3": "The national birthrate is determined by many different factors."
    },
    {
        "question": "A comparison of Japan s policies before 1945 with the policies in effect after 1945 indicates that",
        "correct_answer": "territorial aggression is not necessary to secure national economic goals",
        "distractor1": "reduction in spending on military goods leads to economic depression",
        "distractor2": "dependence on foreign trade usually leads to a weakened national economy",
        "distractor3": "democratic institutions hinder economic growth"
    },
    {
        "question": "A study of Japan s economy since World War II would lead to the conclusion that",
        "correct_answer": "a. government support of technological advances can improve a nation s economic position",
        "distractor1": "a. imperialism is necessary form the economic development of a nation",
        "distractor2": "a. a communist system leads to economic prosperity",
        "distractor3": "a. the feudal system is more economically productive than the market system"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which situation has contributed most to recent Japanese economic growth?",
        "correct_answer": "The Japanese government and Japanese businesses have cooperated with each other.",
        "distractor1": "The Japanese government has place limits on Japanese exports.",
        "distractor2": "Japanese industries spend very little on the research and development of new products.",
        "distractor3": "Japanese citizens save less of their incomes than the citizens of other industrialized nation do."
    },
    {
        "question": "The emergence of Japan as a world economic power has been based mostly on Japan s",
        "correct_answer": "business enterprise and organization",
        "distractor1": "development of nuclear power",
        "distractor2": "abundance of fossil fuels",
        "distractor3": "strong traditional of military rule"
    },
    {
        "question": "In recent years, which factor has been a major reason for the economic tensions between the United States and Japan?",
        "correct_answer": "the United States imported more from Japan than it exported to Japan",
        "distractor1": "Japan s trade deficit with the United States was very high",
        "distractor2": "the United States refused to place quotas on Japanese goods",
        "distractor3": "Japan lowered tariffs on goods imported from the United States"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since World War II, people in both Africa and Latin America have moved from rural to urban areas.  The major cause of this movement has been the",
        "correct_answer": "expectation of improved economic opportunities",
        "distractor1": "rejection of traditional custom",
        "distractor2": "guarantee of better housing",
        "distractor3": "fear of civil war"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor best accounts for the existence of cash-crop production as a major form of agriculture in many Central American nations today?",
        "correct_answer": "demand of world markets for such crops",
        "distractor1": "lack of modern agricultural technology",
        "distractor2": "inadequate supply of water and other natural resources",
        "distractor3": "peasant ownership of most farmlands"
    },
    {
        "question": "Economic development in Japan after World War II and in Communist China since the 1980 s is similar in that both nations have sought to",
        "correct_answer": "nationalize most major industries and restrict competition",
        "distractor1": "end foreign investment",
        "distractor2": "develop their vast natural resources to achieve economic growth",
        "distractor3": "utilize the concepts of capitalism to improve their economies"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980 s and 1990 s, the economic policies of China, supported by Deng Xiaoping, have led directly to",
        "correct_answer": "an increase in trade with the West",
        "distractor1": "an expansion of China s colonial empire",
        "distractor2": "a return to a strict command economy",
        "distractor3": "the success of the commune system"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best explains China s economic shift toward capitalism in the 1980 s and early 1990 s?",
        "correct_answer": "communist economic policies were not meeting the needs of the society",
        "distractor1": "China s economic policies were directly influenced by the success of the Soviet economic system",
        "distractor2": "the Tiananmen Square massacre resulted in major economic reforms in China",
        "distractor3": "the success of the Cultural Revolution resulted in the increased westernization of China"
    },
    {
        "question": "One principle in the theory of mercantilism is that colonies should be",
        "correct_answer": "acquired as markets and sources of raw materials",
        "distractor1": "granted independence as soon as possible",
        "distractor2": "considered an economic burden for the colonial power",
        "distractor3": "encouraged to develop their own industries"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes how a command economy functioned in the Soviet Union?",
        "correct_answer": "A central authority determined the type and quantity of goods to be produced.",
        "distractor1": "The laws of supply and demand controlled the economy.",
        "distractor2": "Trade policies mandated that imports exceed exports.",
        "distractor3": "The success of the agricultural sector controlled the price of manufactured goods."
    },
    {
        "question": "To maintain its economic position, Japan has often limited the number of cars or the quantity of farm products that the United States can sell in Japan. Japan has imposed these limits to develop",
        "correct_answer": "a favorable balance of trade",
        "distractor1": "an equality-of-trade position",
        "distractor2": "a more open market",
        "distractor3": "a belief system"
    },
    {
        "question": "The economic policy of mercantilism first developed during the",
        "correct_answer": "Age of Exploration",
        "distractor1": "Enlightenment",
        "distractor2": "Cold War",
        "distractor3": "Green Revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "  Statement A:   The might of a country consists of gaining surpluses of gold and silver.",
        "correct_answer": "mercantile",
        "distractor1": "traditional",
        "distractor2": "feudal",
        "distractor3": "command"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which generalization about democracy is most valid?",
        "correct_answer": "democratic governments protect basic civil liberties",
        "distractor1": "democratic political systems require a highly industrialized society",
        "distractor2": "democratic governments first evolved in North America",
        "distractor3": "democratic governments prevent their citizens from traveling abroad"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor is necessary for the development of democratic institutions?",
        "correct_answer": "respect for individual rights",
        "distractor1": "strong military forces",
        "distractor2": "a one-party system",
        "distractor3": "an agricultural economy"
    },
    {
        "question": " Power tends to corrupt; absolute power corrupts absolutely. ",
        "correct_answer": "representative democracy",
        "distractor1": "dictatorship",
        "distractor2": "absolute monarchy",
        "distractor3": "totalitarian state"
    },
    {
        "question": "Democracy in modern Japan resulted primarily from",
        "correct_answer": "reforms imposed by the United States after World War II",
        "distractor1": "Shinto and Buddhist beliefs about equality and justice",
        "distractor2": "a history of imperial justice under the constitution of the Emperor",
        "distractor3": "the diffusion of ideas and practices from China and Korea"
    },
    {
        "question": "After the breakup of the Austro-Hungarian Empire and the Soviet Union, new nations were formed.  Which generalization accurately reflects the effect of the breakup on these new nations?",
        "correct_answer": "national and ethnic differences often lead to instability and violence in new nations",
        "distractor1": "new nations are generally too poor and weak to become active members of the United Nations",
        "distractor2": "new nations rarely use their limited resources to wage war",
        "distractor3": "self-determination generally leads to democratic forms of government in new nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement describes a characteristic of the British parliamentary system today?",
        "correct_answer": "the Prime Minister is elected by the majority party in Parliament",
        "distractor1": "the monarch serves as a strong head of state",
        "distractor2": "the members of the House of Commons are appointed for life",
        "distractor3": "the minority party has no vote in the Parliament"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which political system is the basis of Japan s government today?",
        "correct_answer": "parliamentary democracy",
        "distractor1": "military dictatorship",
        "distractor2": "absolute monarchy",
        "distractor3": "national socialism"
    },
    {
        "question": " A constitution? What for? The Koran is the oldest and most efficient constitution in the world.   --King Faisal of Saudi Arabia (1966)  ",
        "correct_answer": "the laws of Islam can be used to govern a country",
        "distractor1": "every country needs elected leaders",
        "distractor2": "Muslims believe in a weak central government",
        "distractor3": "religion should be separated from government"
    },
    {
        "question": " Cavour Provokes War Against Austria    Mazzini Establishes Young Italy  ",
        "correct_answer": "nationalism",
        "distractor1": "isolationism",
        "distractor2": "imperialism",
        "distractor3": "totalitarianism"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels believe would be the result when communism finally emerged as the dominant political and economic system?",
        "correct_answer": "All the evils of industrial society would disappear.",
        "distractor1": "Only two classes would exist in society.",
        "distractor2": "The Soviet Union would become the world s only superpower.",
        "distractor3": "Citizens would own their individual homes and farms."
    },
    {
        "question": "A similarity of the rule of the ancient Mongols and the ancient Greeks is that both",
        "correct_answer": "established vast empires and spread their cultures to the people they conquered",
        "distractor1": "protected the human rights of the peoples they controlled",
        "distractor2": "destroyed the civilizations they defeated",
        "distractor3": "remained isolated and peaceful for centuries"
    },
    {
        "question": "The code of Hammurabi is an example of",
        "correct_answer": "written rules for legal procedures",
        "distractor1": "the power of strong kings to control trade",
        "distractor2": "regulations on the way to conduct wars against neighboring nations",
        "distractor3": "the power of a legislature to veto laws passed by absolute monarchs"
    },
    {
        "question": " . . . suspending laws . . . , by regal [royal] authority without consent of Parliament is illegal. ",
        "correct_answer": "limited monarchy",
        "distractor1": "dynastic rule",
        "distractor2": "totalitarian",
        "distractor3": "theocracy"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Magna Carta, the Glorious Revolution, and the writings of John Locke all contributed to Great Britain s development of",
        "correct_answer": "parliamentary democracy",
        "distractor1": "absolute monarchy",
        "distractor2": "ethnic rivalries",
        "distractor3": "imperialist policies"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Soviet Union, Joseph Stalin governed by means of secret police, censorship, and purges.",
        "correct_answer": "totalitarian",
        "distractor1": "democracy",
        "distractor2": "limited monarchy",
        "distractor3": "theocracy"
    },
    {
        "question": "  Speaker A:   The gods approached Vishnu, the lord of creatures, and said:  Indicate to us that one person among mortals who alone is worthy of the highest rank . . .  Vishnu reflected, and brought forth a glorious son who became the first king.  ",
        "correct_answer": "A and D",
        "distractor1": "B and C",
        "distractor2": "A and C",
        "distractor3": "B and D"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which aspect of a nation s culture is most directly influenced by the physical geography of that nation?",
        "correct_answer": "population distribution",
        "distractor1": "form of government",
        "distractor2": "religious beliefs",
        "distractor3": "social class system"
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason the cultures of North Africa developed differently from the cultures of the rest of Africa was that these areas of Africa were separated by the",
        "correct_answer": "Sahara Desert",
        "distractor1": "Congo River Basin",
        "distractor2": "Great Rift Valley",
        "distractor3": "Arabian Sea"
    },
    {
        "question": "In China, the development of ethnocentrism was most influenced by",
        "correct_answer": "its geographic isolation",
        "distractor1": "its historic reliance on foreign nations",
        "distractor2": "a long history of democratic government",
        "distractor3": "a strong belief in Christianity"
    },
    {
        "question": "In most societies, works of art and architecture generally serve to",
        "correct_answer": "reflect the values of that society",
        "distractor1": "satisfy the needs of the leaders",
        "distractor2": "limit the influence of religion",
        "distractor3": "express opposition to the government in power"
    },
    {
        "question": "In modern African nations, the continued strength of the tribe or ethnic group is a reflection of the continuing influence of",
        "correct_answer": "traditional cultures",
        "distractor1": "European imperialism",
        "distractor2": "urban growth",
        "distractor3": "the slave trade"
    },
    {
        "question": "Traditional African art has had the greatest influence on",
        "correct_answer": "20th century sculpture and painting",
        "distractor1": "classical Roman mosaics and pottery",
        "distractor2": "Renaissance painting",
        "distractor3": "Medieval European architecture"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which generalization is characteristic of most traditional societies?",
        "correct_answer": "sons learn the same trades as their fathers",
        "distractor1": "people move from city to city seeking new jobs",
        "distractor2": "a high degree of social mobility exists",
        "distractor3": "all people have the same economic opportunities"
    },
    {
        "question": "Recent archeological studies suggest the theory that",
        "correct_answer": "the earliest humans evolved in the Rift Valley in Africa",
        "distractor1": "farming societies developed before hunting and gathering societies",
        "distractor2": "all the continents were settled at about the same time",
        "distractor3": "the wheel was used by all ancient societies"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor has contributed most to the social and cultural identity of the Middle East?",
        "correct_answer": "strong influence of Islam on the region",
        "distractor1": "political stability of the region",
        "distractor2": "ability of the region to export oil",
        "distractor3": "lack of foreign involvement in the region"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Chinese called their land  Middle Kingdom.   Europeans often used the term  backward  to refer to China.  These statements best illustrate",
        "correct_answer": "attitudes of ethnocentrism in both cultures",
        "distractor1": "the failure of geographers to establish a universal terminology",
        "distractor2": "the importance of East Asia in world history",
        "distractor3": "the adoption of policies of nonalignment"
    },
    {
        "question": "Geographic isolation of a people frequently reinforces",
        "correct_answer": "a traditional way of life",
        "distractor1": "the development of scientific investigation",
        "distractor2": "the need for higher education",
        "distractor3": "a process of cultural diffusion"
    },
    {
        "question": "In  most societies, urbanization has",
        "correct_answer": "weakened traditional values and life patterns",
        "distractor1": "strengthened the influence of the extended family system",
        "distractor2": "discouraged economic growth",
        "distractor3": "promoted population growth"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement cites an example of cultural diffusion?",
        "correct_answer": "young people dance to rock music in Russia",
        "distractor1": "Venezuela has large reserves of oil",
        "distractor2": "students in China learn calligraphy in school",
        "distractor3": "the Caste system is an important part of life in India"
    },
    {
        "question": "In most traditional societies, the teaching of values is mainly the responsibility of the",
        "correct_answer": "family",
        "distractor1": "judicial system",
        "distractor2": "government",
        "distractor3": "educational system"
    },
    {
        "question": "The study of culture primarily involves",
        "correct_answer": "learning why various peoples live as they do",
        "distractor1": "observing the physical environment of people",
        "distractor2": "understanding the technology of modern machinery",
        "distractor3": "analyzing the personalities of children in the same family"
    },
    {
        "question": "Extended families and limited social mobility are characteristic of",
        "correct_answer": "traditional societies",
        "distractor1": "constitutional monarchies",
        "distractor2": "polytheistic religions",
        "distractor3": "socialist economies"
    },
    {
        "question": "People in both Japan and India eat very little meat.  A study of these cultures would show that",
        "correct_answer": "although these cultures have similar practices, the reasons for these practices differ",
        "distractor1": "the raising of cattle in both nations is very difficult due to the extreme climate",
        "distractor2": "neither culture is concerned with health issues",
        "distractor3": "the governments of both nations enforce strict dietary laws"
    },
    {
        "question": "The dominance of the Spanish language in Latin America and continued use of the French language in Senegal are examples of",
        "correct_answer": "cultural diffusion",
        "distractor1": "social mobility",
        "distractor2": "humanism",
        "distractor3": "Marxism"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which activity is the best example of cultural diffusion in Africa?",
        "correct_answer": "practicing of Islam in Nigeria",
        "distractor1": "weaving kente cloth in Ghana",
        "distractor2": "using masks in traditional African ceremonies",
        "distractor3": "discovering bronze sculptures from Benin"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about India is a fact rather than an opinion?",
        "correct_answer": "The Mongols ruled India for more that 100 years",
        "distractor1": "most Indians are happy with the Hindu practice of arranged marriages",
        "distractor2": "India is fortunate to have a multiparty system of government",
        "distractor3": "the partition of British India in 1947 helped India prosper"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which reference would be used to find the most recent information about the gross domestic product (GDP) of a nation?",
        "correct_answer": "world almanac",
        "distractor1": "historical atlas",
        "distractor2": "thesaurus",
        "distractor3": "dictionary"
    },
    {
        "question": "Culture is sometimes referred to as  a blueprint for living  because it",
        "correct_answer": "includes all the things that contribute to a society s development",
        "distractor1": "flourished best in traditional societies",
        "distractor2": "is determined by genetics",
        "distractor3": "determines the types of jobs offered to the members of a society"
    },
    {
        "question": "In many African nations, a major result of migration from rural to urban areas has been",
        "correct_answer": "a weakening of ancestral lines and kinship bonds",
        "distractor1": "a strengthening of traditional values",
        "distractor2": "a decline in employment opportunities for educated Africans",
        "distractor3": "increased agricultural productivity"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about Japan is a fact rather than an opinion?",
        "correct_answer": "many of Japan s cultural traditions were borrowed from China",
        "distractor1": "Japanese family values have declined with modernization",
        "distractor2": "rapid industrialization has caused few problems for the Japanese people",
        "distractor3": "traditional farming techniques in Japan were better than modern ones"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between the culture of traditional China under dynastic rule and the culture of modern China under communism is that both stress",
        "correct_answer": "loyalty to the authority of leaders",
        "distractor1": "a state-supported religion",
        "distractor2": "the importance of a matriarchal society",
        "distractor3": "limits on population growth"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ancient Chinese expression  Middle Kingdom  and the European terms  Near East  and  Far East  best reflect",
        "correct_answer": "the influence of ethnocentrism on geographic perspective",
        "distractor1": "the impact of the Enlightenment on global thinking",
        "distractor2": "an improved knowledge of world geography",
        "distractor3": "an objective view of the world s cultures"
    },
    {
        "question": "The accusations of witchcraft in 17th century England and the practice of foot-binding in 19th century China are examples of the",
        "correct_answer": "discrimination against women in various cultures",
        "distractor1": "negative aspects of a matriarchal society",
        "distractor2": "gradual improvement of women s rights around the world",
        "distractor3": "respect give to mothers in traditional cultures"
    },
    {
        "question": "Buildings such as the Gothic cathedrals in Western Europe and the Parthenon in ancient Greece reflect each society s",
        "correct_answer": "cultural values",
        "distractor1": "imperialistic attitudes",
        "distractor2": "belief in democracy",
        "distractor3": "rigid social structure"
    },
    {
        "question": "Before towns and cities can develop in a society, the society needs to establish",
        "correct_answer": "an agricultural surplus",
        "distractor1": "an educational system",
        "distractor2": "a writing system",
        "distractor3": "a democratic government"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best supports the idea that cultural diffusion has greatly affected Southeast Asia?",
        "correct_answer": "Buddhism, Hinduism, and Islam are practiced throughout Southeast Asia",
        "distractor1": "the population of Southeast Asia is concentrated in rural areas",
        "distractor2": "monsoon climates affect food production in Indonesia",
        "distractor3": "a reliance on subsistence agriculture remains a problem for many Southeast Asian economies"
    },
    {
        "question": "In India, which aspect of society has been most heavily influenced by religious beliefs, tradition, and the division of labor?",
        "correct_answer": "caste system",
        "distractor1": "policy of neutrality",
        "distractor2": "urbanization",
        "distractor3": "parliamentary government"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between the cultures of traditional China and traditional Japan was that",
        "correct_answer": "the educated class was held in high esteem",
        "distractor1": "religion played a minor role in society",
        "distractor2": "social mobility was encouraged",
        "distractor3": "the people elected the political leaders"
    },
    {
        "question": "The invention of writing systems and the growth of cities occurred only in civilizations that",
        "correct_answer": "developed complex institutions",
        "distractor1": "originated in south Asia",
        "distractor2": "developed matriarchal leadership",
        "distractor3": "borrowed heavily from the Greeks and Romans"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sociologist interested in Indian culture would most likely focus on the study of",
        "correct_answer": "Hinduism and its influence on life in India",
        "distractor1": "India s development of nuclear weapons",
        "distractor2": "the parliamentary government of India",
        "distractor3": "the influence of agricultural production on India s Gross national Product (GNP)"
    },
    {
        "question": "In India, the Caste System determined a person s occupation, personal associations, and marriage partner.  This situation shows that the Caste system",
        "correct_answer": "has been a way of life as well as an element of religion",
        "distractor1": "has helped eliminate ethnic and religious rivalries",
        "distractor2": "has promoted social mobility within Indian society",
        "distractor3": "has been stronger in urban areas that in rural areas"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the centuries of dynastic rule, the Chinese rejected other cultures as inferior to their own.  This situation illustrates the concept of",
        "correct_answer": "ethnocentrism",
        "distractor1": "imperialism",
        "distractor2": "social mobility",
        "distractor3": "cultural diffusion"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the status of women in most traditional Asian societies?",
        "correct_answer": "women were expected to dedicate their lives to their families",
        "distractor1": "women were encouraged to obtain an education",
        "distractor2": "women were expected to run for political office",
        "distractor3": "women were encouraged to work outside the home"
    },
    {
        "question": "One result of the Neolithic Revolution was",
        "correct_answer": "the establishment of villages and the rise of governments",
        "distractor1": "an increase in the number of nomadic tribes",
        "distractor2": "a reliance on hunting and gathering for food",
        "distractor3": "a decrease in trade between cultural groups"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Japanese feudal system and the Hindu caste system are similar in that both systems",
        "correct_answer": "developed a rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "promoted social mobility",
        "distractor2": "encouraged the people to take part in government",
        "distractor3": "resulted in economic opportunities for the lower classes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which situation best illustrates a traditional practice of women in Masai society?",
        "correct_answer": "a young woman marrying and her husband giving cattle to her family as a wedding gift",
        "distractor1": "a young woman leaving her village to attend a university in the capital city",
        "distractor2": "an educated woman returning to her village to become leader of her tribe",
        "distractor3": "a young mother discouraging her children from practicing animism"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Japanese feudal system and the Hindu caste system are similar in that both systems",
        "correct_answer": "developed a rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "promoted social mobility",
        "distractor2": "encouraged the people to take part in government",
        "distractor3": "resulted in economic opportunities for the lower classes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement concerning modern Japan is most accurate?",
        "correct_answer": "Japan has modernized while maintaining some elements of its traditional culture",
        "distractor1": "Japan has become a leader in global peacekeeping efforts",
        "distractor2": "Japan has shown little concern for its natural environment",
        "distractor3": "Japan has severed all traditional ties in favor of western values"
    },
    {
        "question": "The introduction of Buddhism into China and of Islam into Indonesia are examples of",
        "correct_answer": "cultural diffusion",
        "distractor1": "social mobility",
        "distractor2": "ethnocentrism",
        "distractor3": "interdependence"
    },
    {
        "question": "In a traditional society, the influence of an extended family decreases when that society is",
        "correct_answer": "experiencing rapid urbanization and industrialization",
        "distractor1": "being governed by a council of elders",
        "distractor2": "faced with a decreasing population",
        "distractor3": "raising only enough crops to feed its people"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor has been most responsible for the common culture found in Japan?",
        "correct_answer": "ethnic homogeneity",
        "distractor1": "religious diversity",
        "distractor2": "success of democracy",
        "distractor3": "political instability"
    },
    {
        "question": " From a little spark may burst a mighty flame.   --Dante  ",
        "correct_answer": "People from different cultures often view situations in similar ways.",
        "distractor1": "All cultures are concerned with transportation and conservation.",
        "distractor2": "In all cultures, people make excuses for their mistakes.",
        "distractor3": "Geography is important to the development of all cultures."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Church of the Holy Sepulchre, the Dome of the Rock, and the Western (Wailing) Wall are religious sites in Jerusalem. These sites symbolize the",
        "correct_answer": "cultural diversity of the Middle East",
        "distractor1": "Roman domination of the Mediterranean region in the 1st century",
        "distractor2": "limited architectural skills of builders in the Middle East",
        "distractor3": "geographic isolation of the city"
    },
    {
        "question": "Throughout much of history, both China and Japan held a common view that other nations were",
        "correct_answer": "barbarians not worthy of their attention",
        "distractor1": "valued sources of worthwhile knowledge",
        "distractor2": "envoys of an advanced civilization",
        "distractor3": "sources of cheap labor and goods"
    },
    {
        "question": "Historians are interested in studying Maya ruins in Mexico, the haiku poetry of Japan, and the music of Chopin because such cultural and intellectual developments",
        "correct_answer": "reflect the values of that society",
        "distractor1": "illustrate the economic status of individuals in that society",
        "distractor2": "help to explain the role of geography in that society",
        "distractor3": "reveal the political structure of that society"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which term is used to describe the spread of Buddhism from India through Southeast Asia?",
        "correct_answer": "cultural diffusion",
        "distractor1": "ethnocentrism",
        "distractor2": "isolation",
        "distractor3": "imperialism"
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason for the development of an early civilization in the Tigris-Euphrates river valleys was that",
        "correct_answer": "periodic flooding left rich soil, which was ideal for farming",
        "distractor1": "the location protected the people from land invasion",
        "distractor2": "these rivers provided a direct trade route between Europe and Asia",
        "distractor3": "these rivers flowed into the Mediterranean Sea"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which characteristic did the early civilizations that developed along the Nile, the Tigris-Euphrates and the Huang He (Yellow River) have in common?",
        "correct_answer": "transportation and communication were promoted by a mild climate, fertile soil, and natural waterways",
        "distractor1": "each society s religious beliefs were based on monotheism",
        "distractor2": "urban communities were built using iron and steel tools",
        "distractor3": "the form of government in each community was based on male suffrage"
    },
    {
        "question": "The early civilizations of the Nile River Valley, Mesopotamia, and the Yellow River Valley were similar because they were",
        "correct_answer": "dependent on fertile land",
        "distractor1": "industrialized societies",
        "distractor2": "monotheistic",
        "distractor3": "dependent on each other for trade"
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which the civilizations of the Sumerians, the Phoenicians, and the Maya were similar is that each",
        "correct_answer": "developed extensive writing systems",
        "distractor1": "emphasized equality in education",
        "distractor2": "established monotheistic religions",
        "distractor3": "encouraged democratic participation in government"
    },
    {
        "question": " If a seignior (noble) has knocked out the tooth of a seignior of his own rank, they shall knock out his tooth.  But if he has knocked out a commoner s tooth, he shall pay one-third mina of silver.   -Code of Hammurabi",
        "correct_answer": "divisions existed between social classes",
        "distractor1": "all men were equal under the law",
        "distractor2": "fines were preferable to corporal punishment",
        "distractor3": "violence was always punished with violence"
    },
    {
        "question": "The ancient civilizations of Mesopotamia and Egypt were similar in that both cultures",
        "correct_answer": "developed along rivers",
        "distractor1": "used the ziggurat form for their temples",
        "distractor2": "established trade routes to China",
        "distractor3": "used a hieroglyphic writing system"
    },
    {
        "question": "Notre Dame Cathedral in Paris, the Dome of the Rock in Jerusalem and the Great Pyramid in Egypt are examples of",
        "correct_answer": "architectural accomplishments that reflect religious beliefs",
        "distractor1": "the influence of Buddhist architecture on conquered nations",
        "distractor2": "ancient architectural monuments no longer in use",
        "distractor3": "the influence of cultural diffusion on contemporary architecture"
    },
    {
        "question": "Judaism, Islam, and Christianity share a belief in",
        "correct_answer": "monotheism and ethical conduct",
        "distractor1": "the central authority of the Pope",
        "distractor2": "a prohibition of the consumption of port",
        "distractor3": "reincarnation and the Four Noble Truths"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is a valid statement about the history of South Asia?",
        "correct_answer": "Religious beliefs have both unified and divided the people of the region.",
        "distractor1": "Little cultural diffusion has occurred in this region.",
        "distractor2": "Urbanization has strengthened the traditional beliefs and lifestyles of the people of the region.",
        "distractor3": "Superpower involvement has brought peace and economic prosperity to the region."
    },
    {
        "question": " When I go to the office, I put on my shirt and I take off my caste; when I come home, I take off my shirt and I put on my caste. ",
        "correct_answer": "the caste system continues to influence Indian society",
        "distractor1": "the caste system has been reflected by most Indians",
        "distractor2": "successful urban workers in India belong the same Caste",
        "distractor3": "the Indian government officially supports the Caste system"
    },
    {
        "question": "According the teachings of Confucius, the key to the successful organization of society is that",
        "correct_answer": "individuals should know and do what is expected of them",
        "distractor1": "the ruler should be chosen democratically",
        "distractor2": "the evil in humans must be eliminated",
        "distractor3": "ancestor worship should be discontinued"
    },
    {
        "question": "In traditional Chinese culture, which philosophy had the greatest influence on the development of social order and political organization?",
        "correct_answer": "Confucianism",
        "distractor1": "Taoism",
        "distractor2": "Shintoism",
        "distractor3": "Marxism"
    },
    {
        "question": "The teachings of Confucius encouraged people to",
        "correct_answer": "follow a code of moral conduct",
        "distractor1": "put their own interests first",
        "distractor2": "reject government authority",
        "distractor3": "believe in reincarnation"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Japan, the martial arts, the tea ceremony, and flower arranging best reflect the influences of",
        "correct_answer": "Buddhism and Shintoism",
        "distractor1": "imperialism and militarism",
        "distractor2": "capitalism",
        "distractor3": "mercantilism"
    },
    {
        "question": "A person who practices the Shinto faith would be most likely to",
        "correct_answer": "visit a shrine placed on the shore of a lake",
        "distractor1": "pray five times a day",
        "distractor2": "bathe in the Ganges River",
        "distractor3": "make a pilgrimage to Jerusalem"
    },
    {
        "question": "Taoism and Shintoism are similar in that both religions stress",
        "correct_answer": "developing harmony between humans and nature",
        "distractor1": "adhering to the five Confucian relationships",
        "distractor2": "following the Eightfold Path",
        "distractor3": "believing in one God"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between the Five Pillars of Islam and the Ten Commandments is that both",
        "correct_answer": "provide a guide to proper ethical and moral behavior",
        "distractor1": "support a belief in reincarnation",
        "distractor2": "promote learning as a means to salvation",
        "distractor3": "encourage the use of statues to symbolize God"
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which Eastern Orthodoxy, Roman Catholicism, and Protestantism are similar is that each",
        "correct_answer": "is a branch of Christianity",
        "distractor1": "accepts the supreme authority of the Pope",
        "distractor2": "rejects the Old Testament as part of the Bible",
        "distractor3": "was once the official religion of the Byzantine Empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Koran, jihad, and the hegira are most closely associated with the practice of",
        "correct_answer": "Islam",
        "distractor1": "Judaism",
        "distractor2": "Shinto",
        "distractor3": "Buddhism"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Buddhist religion teaches that salvation is earned by",
        "correct_answer": "learning to give up selfish desire",
        "distractor1": "following the Ten Commandments",
        "distractor2": "worshiping Allah as the one true god",
        "distractor3": "being baptized and confirmed"
    },
    {
        "question": "Confucianism in traditional China served to",
        "correct_answer": "maintain social order",
        "distractor1": "create ethnic unrest",
        "distractor2": "emphasize material wealth",
        "distractor3": "support democratic government"
    },
    {
        "question": "Traditional animistic beliefs in Africa, Asia, and Latin America are based on",
        "correct_answer": "an appreciation for the forces of nature",
        "distractor1": "a desire for wealth",
        "distractor2": "a written tradition",
        "distractor3": "a willingness to accept Christianity"
    },
    {
        "question": "Jewish religions and cultural identity has been greatly influenced by",
        "correct_answer": "the Torah and the Diaspora",
        "distractor1": "Ramadan and the concept of reincarnation",
        "distractor2": "the New Testament and the Four Noble Truths",
        "distractor3": "the Koran and the code of bushido"
    },
    {
        "question": "In India, the Caste system determined a person s occupation, personal associations, and marriage partner.  This situation shows that the Caste system",
        "correct_answer": "has been a way of life as well as an element of religion",
        "distractor1": "has helped eliminate ethnic and religious rivalries",
        "distractor2": "has promoted social mobility within Indian society",
        "distractor3": "has been stronger in urban areas that in rural areas"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mansa Musa s journey to Mecca in the 1300 s is evidence that",
        "correct_answer": "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire",
        "distractor1": "the Crusades had a great influence on western Africa",
        "distractor2": "most African leaders were educated in the Middle East",
        "distractor3": "European culture was superior to the cultures of western Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": " From as early as I can remember, the Emperor was an important presence even in our remote home.  He was a descendant of the gods from thousands of years before, never to be looked at or listened to by mere mortals, a presence to be revered and protected and obeyed Finally , my family and neighbors gathered around the radio and listened in stunned silence to the voice that had never before been heard, saying he was only human after all.  Everyone was crying.  I was sad and confused   ",
        "correct_answer": "Shintoism",
        "distractor1": "Christianity",
        "distractor2": "Islam",
        "distractor3": "Judaism"
    },
    {
        "question": " Beginning with childhood, all of man s study is centered on one aim alone   to emerge successfully from the three days  examination   and all he has in his mind is what success can bring to him in terms of power, influence, and prestige. ",
        "correct_answer": "civil service system",
        "distractor1": "social welfare system",
        "distractor2": "contemplation of nature",
        "distractor3": "religious practices"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Eightfold Path, the Four Noble Truths, and the concept of nirvana are associated with the religion of",
        "correct_answer": "Buddhism",
        "distractor1": "Islam",
        "distractor2": "Jainism",
        "distractor3": "Shinto"
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which the Vedas, the Bible, and the Koran are similar is that these religious books",
        "correct_answer": "provide guidelines to govern the behavior of believers",
        "distractor1": "deny the existence of a supreme being who rules the universe",
        "distractor2": "encourage strife between segments of believers",
        "distractor3": "support political rebellions to overthrow existing governments"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which values are most closely associated with the fundamental principles of Buddhism?",
        "correct_answer": "practicing nonviolence and giving up worldly desires",
        "distractor1": "competition and financial success",
        "distractor2": "maintaining the caste system and providing education for all people",
        "distractor3": "self-determination and democracy"
    },
    {
        "question": "A belief of animism is that",
        "correct_answer": "spirits of nature inhabit all living and nonliving objects",
        "distractor1": "after death the soul is reborn in another human form",
        "distractor2": "holy wars must be fought to gain entry into heaven",
        "distractor3": "meditation leads followers to nirvana"
    },
    {
        "question": " The Analects :    In his [the leader] personal conduct, he was respectful.",
        "correct_answer": "law",
        "distractor1": "anarchy",
        "distractor2": "trade",
        "distractor3": "architecture"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major impact of Ancient Greece and Rome on Western Civilization was that",
        "correct_answer": "Greek sculpture and Roman architecture were much admired and copied in the 18th and 19th centuries",
        "distractor1": "the Greeks and Romans succeeded in achieving a classless society, which was later copied in Western Europe",
        "distractor2": "Greece and Rome transmitted Islamic philosophy to the areas they conquered",
        "distractor3": "Greek and Latin are still widely spoken in universities throughout the West"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Ancient Romans  most significant contribution to Europe has been in the area of",
        "correct_answer": "law",
        "distractor1": "economics",
        "distractor2": "poetry",
        "distractor3": "drama"
    },
    {
        "question": "An immediate result of the fall of the Roman Empire was",
        "correct_answer": "a period of disorder and weak central government",
        "distractor1": "a renewed interest in education and the arts",
        "distractor2": "an increase in trade and manufacturing",
        "distractor3": "the growth of cities and dominance by the middle class"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Ancient Athenians are credited with",
        "correct_answer": "establishing governments that had democratic elements",
        "distractor1": "inventing and using the wheel",
        "distractor2": "eliminating slavery",
        "distractor3": "inventing the printing press"
    },
    {
        "question": "Both the Ancient Romans and the Ancient Chinese viewed foreigners as barbarians.  This is an example of",
        "correct_answer": "ethnocentrism",
        "distractor1": "cultural diffusion",
        "distractor2": "materialism",
        "distractor3": "imperialism"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major contribution of the Roman Republic to Western European culture was the",
        "correct_answer": "concept of government by laws",
        "distractor1": "belief that political power should be controlled by the military",
        "distractor2": "establishment of agricultural communes",
        "distractor3": "rejection of the concept of slavery"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which ancient civilization established the basis of western democracy?",
        "correct_answer": "Greek",
        "distractor1": "Phoenician",
        "distractor2": "Egyptian",
        "distractor3": "Sumerian"
    },
    {
        "question": "The political system of the Ancient Roman Empire was characterized by",
        "correct_answer": "a strong central government",
        "distractor1": "rule by a coalition of emperors and religious leaders",
        "distractor2": "universal suffrage in national elections",
        "distractor3": "a strict adherence to constitutional principles"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which societal condition was basic to the development of Greek philosophy?",
        "correct_answer": "mass education",
        "distractor1": "rigid social classes",
        "distractor2": "emphasis on individualism",
        "distractor3": "religious uniformity"
    },
    {
        "question": "Important long-term contributions of Ancient Greek and Roman civilizations are primarily found in the area of",
        "correct_answer": "government and law",
        "distractor1": "military technology",
        "distractor2": "religious doctrine",
        "distractor3": "economic policy and planning"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Ancient Greek city-state of Sparta",
        "correct_answer": "was a powerful military state",
        "distractor1": "was primarily concerned with the health of their people",
        "distractor2": "granted universal suffrage to their people",
        "distractor3": "placed great emphasis on literature and the arts"
    },
    {
        "question": "An immediate result of the fall of the Roman Empire was",
        "correct_answer": "a period of disorder and weak central government",
        "distractor1": "a renewed interest in education and the arts",
        "distractor2": "an increase in trade and manufacturing",
        "distractor3": "the growth of cities and dominance by the middle class"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which societal condition was basic to the development of Greek philosophy and Renaissance art?",
        "correct_answer": "emphasis on individualism",
        "distractor1": "rigid social classes",
        "distractor2": "religious uniformity",
        "distractor3": "mass education"
    },
    {
        "question": "An influence that spread from the Byzantine Empire to Early Russia was the",
        "correct_answer": "Orthodox Christian religion",
        "distractor1": "use of the Latin alphabet",
        "distractor2": "beginning of democracy",
        "distractor3": "factory system"
    },
    {
        "question": "The adoption of the Eastern Orthodox religion and the Cyrillic alphabet by the Russian people occurred as a result of",
        "correct_answer": "contact with Byzantine culture in the 10th century",
        "distractor1": "territorial expansion during the reign of Catherine the Great",
        "distractor2": "the westernization policies of Peter the Great",
        "distractor3": "the influence of the Crusaders during the Middle Ages"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between Axum, Kush, and Nubia was that they were",
        "correct_answer": "early civilizations in Africa",
        "distractor1": "military leaders in the Neolithic Age",
        "distractor2": "rivers along which early trade developed",
        "distractor3": "writers of epic poems about Greek cities"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between the decline of the Roman Empire and the fall of the Manchu Dynasty was that both initially led to",
        "correct_answer": "political chaos and decentralization of government",
        "distractor1": "improved economic conditions",
        "distractor2": "democratically elected governments",
        "distractor3": "major accomplishments in art, science, and technology"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major contribution of the Roman Empire to Western society was the development of",
        "correct_answer": "an effective legal system",
        "distractor1": "gunpowder",
        "distractor2": "the principles of revolutionary socialism",
        "distractor3": "monotheism"
    },
    {
        "question": "After the fall of Rome, the eastern portion of the Roman Empire became known as the",
        "correct_answer": "Byzantine Empire",
        "distractor1": "Persian Empire",
        "distractor2": "Mongol Empire",
        "distractor3": "Gupta Empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which conclusion can be drawn from a study of the early civilizations of Axum, Kush, Mali and Songhai?",
        "correct_answer": "these societies had a long and rich history before their first contact with Europeans",
        "distractor1": "these African societies flourished at the same time",
        "distractor2": "farming was more extensive in the Nile River Valley than it was in the Fertile Crescent",
        "distractor3": "the Neolithic Revolution occurred in Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major effect of the decline of the Roman Empire was that Western Europe",
        "correct_answer": "entered a period of chaos and disorder",
        "distractor1": "came under the control of the Muslims",
        "distractor2": "was absorbed by the Byzantine Empire",
        "distractor3": "returned to a republican form of government"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which characteristic was common to the Golden Age of Greece and the Italian Renaissance?",
        "correct_answer": "prosperity led to the creation of many works of art",
        "distractor1": "a strong military led to national unity",
        "distractor2": "written constitutions led to the establishment of democratic governments",
        "distractor3": "political instability led directly to the formation of unified nation-states"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the centuries of dynastic rule, the Chinese rejected other cultures as inferior to their own.  This situation illustrates the concept of",
        "correct_answer": "ethnocentrism",
        "distractor1": "imperialism",
        "distractor2": "social mobility",
        "distractor3": "cultural diffusion"
    },
    {
        "question": "Alexander the Great s conquests of Greece, Asia Minor, Egypt, and Persia led to the",
        "correct_answer": "spread of Hellenic culture",
        "distractor1": "adoption of a feudal system",
        "distractor2": "establishment of representative democracy",
        "distractor3": "spread of Islamic culture throughout Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between the Ancient African kingdoms of Egypt, Ghana, Mali and Songhai is that all of these kingdoms were located",
        "correct_answer": "on major trading routes",
        "distractor1": "in mountainous terrain",
        "distractor2": "in coastal areas",
        "distractor3": "in rain forest areas"
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason the ancient kingdoms in western Africa prospered was that they",
        "correct_answer": "developed extensive trade in gold, ivory, and salt",
        "distractor1": "were located along the Tigris and Euphrates rivers",
        "distractor2": "had no contact with the rest of the world",
        "distractor3": "followed the Hindu beliefs of their rulers"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mansa Musa s journey to Mecca in the 1300 s is evidence that",
        "correct_answer": "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire",
        "distractor1": "the Crusades had a great influence on western Africa",
        "distractor2": "most African leaders were educated in the Middle East",
        "distractor3": "European culture was superior to the cultures of western Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "The contributions of the ancient civilizations of Ghana, Axum, Kush, and Mali demonstrate that",
        "correct_answer": "advanced societies developed in Africa before Europeans colonized this region",
        "distractor1": "industrial technology was needed for African civilizations to develop",
        "distractor2": "many African civilizations developed in southern Africa",
        "distractor3": "most of the African Continent was unified under a single political system"
    },
    {
        "question": "A similarity between the ancient western African kingdoms of Mali, Ghana, and Songhai is that these kingdoms ",
        "correct_answer": "established economies based on trade",
        "distractor1": "limited the power of their rulers",
        "distractor2": "practiced Christianity",
        "distractor3": "isolated themselves from contact with other cultures"
    },
    {
        "question": " Western Europe owed a debt of gratitude to the Empire that for almost a thousand years ensured the survival of Christianity during a time when Europe was too weak to accomplish the task. ",
        "correct_answer": "Byzantine",
        "distractor1": "Hellenistic",
        "distractor2": "Mongol",
        "distractor3": "Ottoman"
    },
    {
        "question": "An influence that spread from the Byzantine Empire to Early Russia was the",
        "correct_answer": "Orthodox Christian religion",
        "distractor1": "use of the Latin alphabet",
        "distractor2": "beginning of democracy",
        "distractor3": "factory system"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which empire introduced the Eastern Orthodox Church and the Cyrillic alphabet to Russia? ",
        "correct_answer": "Byzantine",
        "distractor1": "Mongol",
        "distractor2": "British",
        "distractor3": "Gupta"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major feature of the Golden Age of Moslem culture was the",
        "correct_answer": "development of the foundations of modern science and mathematics",
        "distractor1": "political and economic isolation of the Arab world",
        "distractor2": "adoption of democratic government",
        "distractor3": "persecution of Jews and Christians"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor helps explain the scientific and literary achievements of the Muslims during their Golden Age (A.D. 800-1300)?",
        "correct_answer": "cultural diversity accepted by many Islamic governments",
        "distractor1": "expansion of trans-Atlantic trade",
        "distractor2": "innovations introduced by the Europeans during the Renaissance",
        "distractor3": "legal equality of all people in the Islamic empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mansa Musa s journey to Mecca in the 1300 s is evidence that",
        "correct_answer": "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire",
        "distractor1": "the Crusades had a great influence on western Africa",
        "distractor2": "most African leaders were educated in the Middle East",
        "distractor3": "European culture was superior to the cultures of western Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which activity occurred during the Golden Age of Muslim culture?",
        "correct_answer": "major discoveries in mathematics and science",
        "distractor1": "destruction of books containing Greek and Roman ideas",
        "distractor2": "beginning of pilgrimages to Mecca",
        "distractor3": "opposition to freedom of thought and to foreign ideas by rulers"
    },
    {
        "question": "The contributions of the Golden Age of Islamic civilization include",
        "correct_answer": "advances in mathematics",
        "distractor1": "irrigation systems",
        "distractor2": "polytheistic beliefs",
        "distractor3": "gunpowder and guns"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Europe during the Middle Ages, increases in trade and commerce resulted in",
        "correct_answer": "development of towns and cities",
        "distractor1": "lower living standards for industrial workers",
        "distractor2": "decreased economic rivalry between kings",
        "distractor3": "increased political power for the clergy"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Middle Ages, Europeans did not eat potatoes or corn because these vegetables",
        "correct_answer": "had not yet been introduced to Europe from the New World",
        "distractor1": "were forbidden by the Catholic Church for religious reasons",
        "distractor2": "were believed to be poisonous",
        "distractor3": "were too expensive to import from China"
    },
    {
        "question": " All things were under its domain...its power was such that no one could hope to escape its scrutiny. ",
        "correct_answer": "the Church",
        "distractor1": "the Guild",
        "distractor2": "Knighthood",
        "distractor3": "the nation-state"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Middle Ages in Western Europe was characterized by",
        "correct_answer": "the manor system and the importance of land ownership",
        "distractor1": "absolute monarchies and strong central governments",
        "distractor2": "decreased emphasis on religion in daily life",
        "distractor3": "extensive trade with Asia and the Middle East"
    },
    {
        "question": "Feudal societies are generally characterized by",
        "correct_answer": "an emphasis on social order",
        "distractor1": "a representative government",
        "distractor2": "many economic opportunities",
        "distractor3": "the protection of political rights"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Europe, a long-term effect of the Crusades was",
        "correct_answer": "an increased demand for goods from the East",
        "distractor1": "the strengthening of the feudal system",
        "distractor2": "the adoption of Islamic religious practices",
        "distractor3": "increased European isolation"
    },
    {
        "question": "The art, music, and philosophy of the medieval period in Europe generally dealt with",
        "correct_answer": "religious themes",
        "distractor1": "human scientific achievements",
        "distractor2": "materialism",
        "distractor3": "classic Greek and Roman subjects"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the result of the Crusades?",
        "correct_answer": "trade between Europe and the Middle East was expanded",
        "distractor1": "Europeans maintained a lasting control over much of the Middle East",
        "distractor2": "Islamic influence dominated Europe",
        "distractor3": "Europeans developed tolerance of Non-Christian religions"
    },
    {
        "question": "What were two indirect results of the Crusades?",
        "correct_answer": "trade and commerce increased and the feudal system was weakened",
        "distractor1": "trade and commerce increased and the feudal system was strengthened",
        "distractor2": "trade and commerce declined and the feudal system was strengthened",
        "distractor3": "trade and commerce declined and the feudal system was weakened"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Europe during the Middle Ages, the force that provided unification and stability was the",
        "correct_answer": "Roman Catholic Church",
        "distractor1": "central government in Rome",
        "distractor2": "military alliance between France and Germany",
        "distractor3": "federation of the craft guilds"
    },
    {
        "question": "Feudalism in Western Europe was similar to feudalism in Japan in that",
        "correct_answer": "power was based on class relationships",
        "distractor1": "equality among the social classes",
        "distractor2": "direct democracy",
        "distractor3": "monotheism"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is a characteristic of a feudal society?",
        "correct_answer": "rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "rapid social change",
        "distractor2": "high literacy rate",
        "distractor3": "industrial-based economy"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Europe, the Crusades resulted in",
        "correct_answer": "an increased demand for goods from the Middle East and Asia",
        "distractor1": "greater isolation of the region from the world",
        "distractor2": "the adoption of Islam as the official religion of many European nations",
        "distractor3": "the strengthening of the feudal system"
    },
    {
        "question": "One important effect of the Crusades on Western Europe was that they",
        "correct_answer": "furthered cultural diffusion throughout Western Europe",
        "distractor1": "led to a decline in the importance of the church in Western Europe",
        "distractor2": "introduced the Industrial Revolution to Western Europe",
        "distractor3": "ended the western European quest for an overseas empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "In European feudal society, an individual s social status was generally determined by",
        "correct_answer": "birth",
        "distractor1": "education and training",
        "distractor2": "individual abilities",
        "distractor3": "marriage"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which economic system existed in Europe during the early Middle Ages?",
        "correct_answer": "manorialism",
        "distractor1": "free market",
        "distractor2": "socialism",
        "distractor3": "command"
    },
    {
        "question": "One major result of the Crusades was the",
        "correct_answer": "spread of Middle Eastern culture and technology to Europe",
        "distractor1": "permanent occupation of the Holy Land by the Europeans",
        "distractor2": "long-term decrease in European trade",
        "distractor3": "conversion of most Muslims to Christianity"
    },
    {
        "question": "The growth of feudalism in Europe during the Middle Ages was primarily caused by the",
        "correct_answer": "collapse of a strong central government",
        "distractor1": "rivalry between the colonial empires",
        "distractor2": "suppression of internationalism",
        "distractor3": "decline of the Roman Catholic Church"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Crusades have been called  history s most successful failures.     Which statement best explains this expression?",
        "correct_answer": "The Crusades did not achieve their original goals, but they brought about many desirable changes in Europe.",
        "distractor1": "Although the Crusaders captured the Holy Land, they were unable to bring about democratic reforms.",
        "distractor2": "The Crusades helped bring about the fall of the Roman Empire",
        "distractor3": "The Crusaders prevented the Turks from capturing Constantinople for many centuries"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Roman Catholic Church during the Middle Ages in Europe can best be described as a church that",
        "correct_answer": "was a stabilizing influence during a period of weak central governments",
        "distractor1": "favored separation from secular governments",
        "distractor2": "avoided involvement in social and educational matters",
        "distractor3": "was a strong force that divided many people"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major goal of the Christian Church during the Crusades (1096 1291) was to",
        "correct_answer": "capture the Holy Land from Islamic rulers",
        "distractor1": "establish Christianity in western Europe",
        "distractor2": "unite warring Arab peoples",
        "distractor3": "strengthen English dominance in the Arab world"
    },
    {
        "question": "Korea greatly influenced the development of early Japan by",
        "correct_answer": "acting as a bridge for ideas from China",
        "distractor1": "providing Japan with the technology for industrialization",
        "distractor2": "serving as a barrier against Chinese aggression",
        "distractor3": "protecting Japan from early European exploration"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Japan between 1603 and 1868, the most notable action taken by the Tokugawa Shogunate was the",
        "correct_answer": "virtual isolation of the country from the outside world",
        "distractor1": "military conquest of China",
        "distractor2": "development of extensive trade with the Americas",
        "distractor3": "formation of cultural links with Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "The code of bushido of the Japanese samurai is most similar to",
        "correct_answer": "practice of chivalry by European knights",
        "distractor1": "belief in reincarnation and karma of Hindus",
        "distractor2": "teachings of Judaism",
        "distractor3": "theory of natural rights of the Enlightenment writers"
    },
    {
        "question": "Feudal societies are generally characterized by",
        "correct_answer": "an emphasis on social order",
        "distractor1": "a representative government",
        "distractor2": "many economic opportunities",
        "distractor3": "the protection of political rights"
    },
    {
        "question": "Feudalism in Western Europe was similar to feudalism in Japan in that",
        "correct_answer": "power was based on class relationships",
        "distractor1": "equality among the social classes",
        "distractor2": "direct democracy",
        "distractor3": "monotheism"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is a characteristic of a feudal society?",
        "correct_answer": "rigid class structure",
        "distractor1": "rapid social change",
        "distractor2": "high literacy rate",
        "distractor3": "industrial-based economy"
    },
    {
        "question": "The diagram illustrates the social structure of feudal Japan.",
        "correct_answer": "a well-defined class system",
        "distractor1": "a classless society",
        "distractor2": "a growing middle class",
        "distractor3": "high social mobility"
    },
    {
        "question": "A valid generalization about early Japanese culture is that Japan",
        "correct_answer": "maintained a uniquely individual culture while borrowing much from other cultures",
        "distractor1": "had a strong influence on the development of culture in Korea",
        "distractor2": "spread Shinto throughout Asia",
        "distractor3": "imported almost all of its cultural ideas from China, resulting in nearly identical cultures"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Mongols played a significant role in Russian history by",
        "correct_answer": "isolating Russia from Western Europe during the early Renaissance",
        "distractor1": "supporting Czar Nicholas II during the Russian Revolution",
        "distractor2": "supporting the rule of Ivan the Terrible",
        "distractor3": "ending the reign of Catherine the Great"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Europe, a major characteristic of humanism was",
        "correct_answer": "an appreciation for the basic worth of individual achievement",
        "distractor1": "a belief in the supremacy of the state in relation to individual rights",
        "distractor2": "a rejection of ancient civilizations and their cultures",
        "distractor3": "an emphasis on social control and obedience to national rulers"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes a characteristic of the Renaissance in Europe?",
        "correct_answer": "creativity in the arts was encouraged",
        "distractor1": "the social structure became very rigid",
        "distractor2": "the political structure was similar to that of the Roman Empire",
        "distractor3": "humanism decreased in importance"
    },
    {
        "question": "  Europe is waking out of a long, deep sleep time was when learning was only found in the religious orders learning has passed to secular princes and peers.  ",
        "correct_answer": "Renaissance",
        "distractor1": "decline of the Roman Empire",
        "distractor2": "Crusades",
        "distractor3": "rise of Christianity"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a major characteristic of the Renaissance?",
        "correct_answer": "humanism",
        "distractor1": "conformity",
        "distractor2": "mysticism",
        "distractor3": "obedience"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement describes a direct effect of the Renaissance on Western Europe?",
        "correct_answer": "the philosophy of humanism brought about a decrease in the power of the Roman Catholic Church",
        "distractor1": "art began to reflect an increased emphasis on religious themes",
        "distractor2": "nationalistic movements among the minority ethnic groups in the region declines",
        "distractor3": "the feudal system was developed to provide stability in a decentralized political structure"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Renaissance and the Protestant Reformation were similar in that both were",
        "correct_answer": "stimulated by a spirit of inquiry",
        "distractor1": "supported by the working class",
        "distractor2": "limited to Italy, France, and Germany",
        "distractor3": "encouraged by the successes of the French Revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes a change that occurred during both the Renaissance and the Enlightenment?",
        "correct_answer": "a new questioning spirit and attitude emerged",
        "distractor1": "feudalism became the dominant political system",
        "distractor2": "the use of reason and logic were discouraged",
        "distractor3": "technology and science were considered unimportant"
    },
    {
        "question": "One factor that enabled the Renaissance to flourish in Northern Italy was that the region had",
        "correct_answer": "a wealthy class that invested in the arts",
        "distractor1": "a socialist for of government",
        "distractor2": "limited contact with the Byzantine Empire",
        "distractor3": "a shrinking middle class"
    },
    {
        "question": "European society during the Renaissance differed from European society during the Middle Ages in that during the Renaissance",
        "correct_answer": "the emphasis on individual worth increased",
        "distractor1": "the Church was no longer influential",
        "distractor2": "economic activity declined",
        "distractor3": "art no longer contained religious themes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which societal condition was basic to the development of Greek philosophy and Renaissance art?",
        "correct_answer": "emphasis on individualism",
        "distractor1": "rigid social classes",
        "distractor2": "religious uniformity",
        "distractor3": "mass education"
    },
    {
        "question": "The humanists of the Renaissance differed from the traditional medieval philosophers in the humanists ",
        "correct_answer": "emphasis on the importance of the individual",
        "distractor1": "interest in the spiritual life of people",
        "distractor2": "lack of interest in Ancient Greek and Roman culture",
        "distractor3": "rejection of Christian principles"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which characteristic was common to the Golden Age of Greece and the Italian Renaissance?",
        "correct_answer": "prosperity led to the creation of many works of art",
        "distractor1": "a strong military led to national unity",
        "distractor2": "written constitutions led to the establishment of democratic governments",
        "distractor3": "political instability led directly to the formation of unified nation-states"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which idea about leadership would Niccolo Machiavelli most likely support?",
        "correct_answer": "leaders should do whatever is necessary to achieve their goals",
        "distractor1": "leaders should fight against discrimination and intolerance",
        "distractor2": "leaders should listen to the desires of the people",
        "distractor3": "elected leaders should be fair and good"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Renaissance period, which factor was emphasized by the philosophy of humanism?",
        "correct_answer": "value of the individual",
        "distractor1": "superiority of medieval thought",
        "distractor2": "devotion to religion",
        "distractor3": "obedience to government officials"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement concerning the Renaissance in Europe is based on opinion rather than on fact?",
        "correct_answer": "The art of the Northern Renaissance was superior to that of the Italian Renaissance.",
        "distractor1": "Literature began to appear in languages other than Latin.",
        "distractor2": "Art reflected the ideas of humanism and individualism.",
        "distractor3": "Art produced during the Renaissance had religious as well as secular themes."
    },
    {
        "question": "Martin Luther s Ninety-Five Theses were a call for",
        "correct_answer": "reforms within the Roman Catholic Church",
        "distractor1": "religious revolt against the German princes",
        "distractor2": "greater papal authority",
        "distractor3": "crusades to spread Christianity"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Western Europe, a major immediate effect of the Reformation was a",
        "correct_answer": "decline in religious unity and in the power of the Catholic Church",
        "distractor1": "renewed domination of the Catholic Church over the German states",
        "distractor2": "greater tolerance of religions other than Christianity",
        "distractor3": "decrease in educational opportunities for the middle class"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Renaissance, which development contributed most to the Protestant Reformation?",
        "correct_answer": "questioning of traditional authority",
        "distractor1": "interest in Ancient Greece and Rome",
        "distractor2": "advances in mathematics and science",
        "distractor3": "attention to realism and detail"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a result of the Protestant Reformation in Europe?",
        "correct_answer": "the power of the Catholic Church in Europe was weakened",
        "distractor1": "the Catholic Church accepted the dominance of the new Protestant religions in Italy, France, and Germany",
        "distractor2": "Spain became a predominately Protestant nation",
        "distractor3": "Catholic Church leaders refused to make any changes in church practices"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a major result of the Reformation?",
        "correct_answer": "new Christian denominations emerged",
        "distractor1": "religious teachings were no longer allowed in the universities",
        "distractor2": "the Crusades were organized",
        "distractor3": "the power of the Pope was strengthened"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor helped most to bring about the Protestant Reformation?",
        "correct_answer": "kings and princes in Northern Europe resented the power of the Catholic Church",
        "distractor1": "the Catholic clergy had lost faith in their religion",
        "distractor2": "Islam was attracting many converts in Western Europe",
        "distractor3": "the exploration of the Americas led to the introduction of new religious ideas"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Protestant Reformation and the European Renaissance were similar in that both",
        "correct_answer": "encouraged people to question tradition",
        "distractor1": "discouraged the growth of strong monarchs",
        "distractor2": "were led by the military",
        "distractor3": "supported the return of the Roman Empire"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Protestant Reformation represents a turning point in European history because it",
        "correct_answer": "ended religious unity in Western Europe",
        "distractor1": "allowed religious reformers to escape persecution",
        "distractor2": "standardized all religious writings",
        "distractor3": "forced most of Europe s monarchs to become Protestants"
    },
    {
        "question": " Christians should be taught that he who gives to a poor man or lends to a needy man does better than if he used the money to buy an indulgence. ",
        "correct_answer": "Protestant Reformation",
        "distractor1": "Commercial Revolution",
        "distractor2": "Industrial Revolution",
        "distractor3": "Renaissance"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Renaissance and the Protestant Reformation were similar in that both were",
        "correct_answer": "stimulated by a spirit of inquiry",
        "distractor1": "supported by the working class",
        "distractor2": "limited to Italy, France, and Germany",
        "distractor3": "encouraged by the successes of the French Revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "One major influence the Renaissance had on the Protestant Reformation was that the philosophers of the Renaissance",
        "correct_answer": "encouraged a questioning attitude",
        "distractor1": "supported democratic forms of government",
        "distractor2": "stressed the importance of life after death",
        "distractor3": "denied the existence of God"
    },
    {
        "question": " Unless I am convinced by Scripture and plain reason... my conscience is captive to the Word of God. I cannot and I will hot recant anything, for to go against conscience is neither right nor safe. Here I stand, I cannot do otherwise.    Martin Luther, Diet of Worms (1517)   ",
        "correct_answer": "the supremacy of the Bible over Church policies",
        "distractor1": "imprisoning those who disagreed with Church teachings",
        "distractor2": "maintaining the unity of the Church",
        "distractor3": "the need for nepotism"
    },
    {
        "question": "Martin Luther s posting of the Ninety-Five Theses is considered by many to be a turning point in history because ",
        "correct_answer": "the power of the Roman Catholic Church was lessened and royal power grew",
        "distractor1": "the Pope s right to sell indulgences was strengthened",
        "distractor2": "Luther soon became the leader of Germany",
        "distractor3": "the Roman Catholic Church unified the German states"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Spain, an effect of the Inquisition during the 16th century was to",
        "correct_answer": "prevent the introduction of Protestant religions",
        "distractor1": "reintroduce Moorish culture to the Iberian Peninsula",
        "distractor2": "encourage the development of the Industrial Revolution",
        "distractor3": "implement the ideas of the Renaissance in major cities"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Latin America, the Maya and the Aztec civilizations were similar in that they",
        "correct_answer": "developed complex mathematical and calendar systems",
        "distractor1": "showed little evidence of urbanization",
        "distractor2": "lacked a strong central government",
        "distractor3": "used military weapons superior to those of Europeans"
    },
    {
        "question": "A study of Mayas, Aztecs, and Incas would show that these ancient American civilizations",
        "correct_answer": "rivaled the accomplishments of early Middle Eastern cultures",
        "distractor1": "produced few cultural achievements",
        "distractor2": "lived at peace with their neighbors",
        "distractor3": "welcomed the new technology brought by European explorers"
    },
    {
        "question": "A study of the Maya, Aztec, and Inca civilizations of Latin America would show that these civilizations",
        "correct_answer": "developed advanced and complex societies before the arrival of the Europeans",
        "distractor1": "established extensive trade with Pacific Rim nations",
        "distractor2": "were strongly influenced by their contact with Asian and African civilizations",
        "distractor3": "were relatively large, but not well organized"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a result of the Commercial Revolution",
        "correct_answer": "expansion of European influence overseas",
        "distractor1": "decline in population growth in Europe",
        "distractor2": "shift of power from Western Europe to Eastern Europe",
        "distractor3": "spread of feudalism throughout Western Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was an immediate result of the European Age of Exploration?",
        "correct_answer": "European influence spread to the Western hemisphere",
        "distractor1": "Islamic culture spread across Africa and Asia",
        "distractor2": "independence movements developed in Asia and Africa",
        "distractor3": "military dictatorships were established throughout Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major result of the Age of Exploration was",
        "correct_answer": "the end of regional isolation and the beginning of a period of European global domination",
        "distractor1": "a long period of peace and prosperity for the nations of Western Europe",
        "distractor2": "extensive migration of people from the Western Hemisphere to Europe and Asia",
        "distractor3": "the fall of European national monarchies and the end of the power of the Catholic Church"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Commercial Revolution in Western Europe led directly to the",
        "correct_answer": "expansion of world trade",
        "distractor1": "development of a socialist economy",
        "distractor2": "establishment of the Guild System",
        "distractor3": "weakening of the power of the middle class"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which system developed as a result of the Commercial Revolution",
        "correct_answer": "market economy",
        "distractor1": "manorialism",
        "distractor2": "communism",
        "distractor3": "bartering"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these events during the Age of Exploration was a cause of the other three?",
        "correct_answer": "advances in learning and technology made long ocean voyages possible",
        "distractor1": "Europeans brought food, animals, and ideas from one continent to another",
        "distractor2": "European diseases had an adverse effect on the native populations of new territories",
        "distractor3": "warfare increased as European nations competed for land and power"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Native American population of Mexico in 1492 has been estimated at 25 million; the population in 1608 has been estimated at 1.7 million.  This decrease in population was mainly a result of",
        "correct_answer": "diseases introduced by the Spanish",
        "distractor1": "crop failures brought on by poor weather conditions",
        "distractor2": "emigration of Native Americans to Europe and Africa",
        "distractor3": "wars between various native groups"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Latin America during the early period of Spanish colonialism, the deaths of large numbers of the native people led to",
        "correct_answer": "the importation of slaves from Africa",
        "distractor1": "a decline in Spanish immigration to the Americas",
        "distractor2": "the removal of most Spanish troops from the Americas",
        "distractor3": "improved health care in the colonies"
    },
    {
        "question": "Both Japan and China decided to limit trade with Europe during much of the 16th and 17th centuries because the Japanese and the Chinese",
        "correct_answer": "believed they would receive no benefit from increased contact with the Europeans",
        "distractor1": "had few products to sell to the Europeans",
        "distractor2": "held religious beliefs that prohibited contact with foreigners",
        "distractor3": "thought European technology would hinder any effort to modernize"
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason the Spanish conquistadors were able to conquer the Aztec and Inca Empires rapid is that",
        "correct_answer": "the Spanish had better weapons than the Aztecs and Incas did",
        "distractor1": "these empires had no standing armies",
        "distractor2": "the Spanish greatly outnumbered the Aztecs and Incas",
        "distractor3": "the Aztecs and Incas joined together to fight the Spanish"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which conclusion can be drawn from a study of the early civilizations of Axum, Kush, Mali and Songhai?",
        "correct_answer": "these societies had a long and rich history before their first contact with Europeans",
        "distractor1": "these African societies flourished at the same time",
        "distractor2": "farming was more extensive in the Nile River Valley than it was in the Fertile Crescent",
        "distractor3": "the Neolithic Revolution occurred in Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a characteristic of the policy of mercantilism followed by Spanish colonial rulers in Latin America?",
        "correct_answer": "the colonies were required to provide raw materials to Spain and to purchase Spanish manufactured goods",
        "distractor1": "the colonies were forced to develop local industries to support themselves",
        "distractor2": "Spain sought trade agreements between its colonies and the English colonies in North America",
        "distractor3": "Spain encouraged the colonies to develop new political systems to meet colonial needs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes a result of the scarcity of native Indian labor in Latin America during the colonial period?",
        "correct_answer": "large numbers of African slaves were imported",
        "distractor1": "unskilled laborers were imported from Asia",
        "distractor2": "many people from Spain and Portugal immigrated to the region",
        "distractor3": "Native American Indians from the British colonies went south to work"
    },
    {
        "question": "The influence of African culture on some areas of Latin America was largely a result of the",
        "correct_answer": "Atlantic slave trade",
        "distractor1": "American Revolution",
        "distractor2": "building of the Panama Canal",
        "distractor3": "success of Communist Revolutions"
    },
    {
        "question": "In many Latin American nations, a major effect of colonial rule has been the",
        "correct_answer": "concentration of power in a small group of landowners",
        "distractor1": "minor political role of the military",
        "distractor2": "equal distribution of wealth among social classes",
        "distractor3": "economic control held by the Indian population"
    },
    {
        "question": "Spain s colonial policy of mercantilism affected the development of Latin American nations by promoting",
        "correct_answer": "the production of raw material and cash crops",
        "distractor1": "free and rapid trade with Asia and Africa",
        "distractor2": "respect for the rights of indigenous people",
        "distractor3": "isolationism as a response to international political issues"
    },
    {
        "question": "One result of the European conquest of Latin America was that in Latin America",
        "correct_answer": "Spanish became the major spoken language",
        "distractor1": "Native American cultures flourished",
        "distractor2": "the Aztec religion spread",
        "distractor3": "many parliamentary democracies were established"
    },
    {
        "question": "In colonial Latin America, the main purpose of the encomienda system was to",
        "correct_answer": "provide a steady labor supply for early colonists",
        "distractor1": "insure that the Indians were humanely treated",
        "distractor2": "prevent slaver in Spain s New World colonies",
        "distractor3": "build and maintain forts to repel foreign invaders"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to the theory of mercantilism, colonies should be",
        "correct_answer": "acquired as markets and sources of raw materials",
        "distractor1": "considered an economic burden for the colonial power",
        "distractor2": "grated independence as soon as possible",
        "distractor3": "encouraged to develop their own industries"
    },
    {
        "question": " He once sent fifty horsemen with pikes (spears) to destroy an entire province.  Not a single human being survived that massacre, neither women nor children nor aged infirm This terrible massacre was punishment for a trifling offense: some Indians had not responded to a summons promptly enough when the tyrant had commanded that they bring him a load of maize (corn) , or else had asked for more Indians to be assigned to serve him or his comrades.  And there was no place where the Indians could take refuge  ",
        "correct_answer": "encourage the colonial government to change its policies toward native peoples",
        "distractor1": "explain the problems associated with using native laborers",
        "distractor2": "justify the need for the harsh treatment of the native people",
        "distractor3": "show support for the governor s policy toward native peoples"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Treaty of Tordesillas (1494), concerning Latin America, and the Berlin Conference (1884-1885), concerning Africa, were similar in that each agreement",
        "correct_answer": "divided each area into European-controlled segments",
        "distractor1": "provided for self-government by the native peoples",
        "distractor2": "declared that in these areas monarchs rule by divine right",
        "distractor3": "suppressed revolts by native peoples against European imperialists"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best illustrates the contradictory actions of the Catholic Church in colonial Latin America?",
        "correct_answer": "the Church expressed concern over the mistreatment of Native Americans, but supported the encomienda system",
        "distractor1": "the Jesuits destroyed the temples of the Native Americans, but allowed them to continue their religious rituals",
        "distractor2": "the Church moved many Native Americas from Spanish territory to Portuguese territory, but encouraged the importation of African slaves",
        "distractor3": "the Pope endorsed the Treaty of Tordesillas, but outlawed further exploration"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Crusades indirectly contributed to the discovery of the New World by",
        "correct_answer": "stimulating European demand for goods from the East",
        "distractor1": "forcing the religious conversion of the Muslim population",
        "distractor2": "forcing the Turks to flee from Constantinople",
        "distractor3": "increasing the power of the feudal lords"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 1600 s, the interest of Europeans in Africa was based mainly on Europe s need to",
        "correct_answer": "obtain workers for its colonies in the Americas",
        "distractor1": "market its surplus agricultural products",
        "distractor2": "establish collective security arrangements",
        "distractor3": "settle its surplus population on new lands"
    },
    {
        "question": "The printing press, the astrolabe, and the Mercator projection were technological advances that contributed to the",
        "correct_answer": "exploration and overseas expansion of the colonial empires",
        "distractor1": "unification of Germany and Italy in the late 1800 s",
        "distractor2": "growth of industry in Latin America during the late 1900 s",
        "distractor3": "spread of Islam in the 700 s and 800 s"
    },
    {
        "question": "Peter the Great and Catherine the Great changed Russia by",
        "correct_answer": "introducing western ideas and customs",
        "distractor1": "abolishing all social class distinctions",
        "distractor2": "becoming constitutional monarchs",
        "distractor3": "preventing wars with neighboring nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Changes in Russia under Peter the Great were most similar to changes that occurred in",
        "correct_answer": "Japan during the Meiji Restoration",
        "distractor1": "China before the Opium War",
        "distractor2": "Iran after the fall of Shah Pahlevi",
        "distractor3": "France during the feudal period"
    },
    {
        "question": "Westernization in Russia came about largely through the",
        "correct_answer": "efforts of Peter the Great and his successors",
        "distractor1": "invasion of Russia by Sweden",
        "distractor2": "desire of the United States to seek new markets",
        "distractor3": "acceptance of the policies of the Eastern Orthodox Church"
    },
    {
        "question": " God hath power to create or destroy, make or unmake, at his pleasure; to give life or send death; to judge and to be judged (by) none And the like power have kings;  ",
        "correct_answer": "theory of divine right",
        "distractor1": "enlightened despotism",
        "distractor2": "Social Darwinism",
        "distractor3": "constitutional monarchy"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which type of government is shown in the cartoon?",
        "correct_answer": "an absolute monarchy",
        "distractor1": "a socialist republic",
        "distractor2": "a communist dictatorship",
        "distractor3": "a democracy"
    },
    {
        "question": " . . .The person of the King is sacred, and to attack him in any way is an attack on religion itself. Kings represent the divine majesty and have been appointed by Him to carry out His purposes. Serving God and respecting kings are bound together.    Bishop Jacques Bossuet   ",
        "correct_answer": "Age of Absolutism",
        "distractor1": "existed during the",
        "distractor2": "Renaissance",
        "distractor3": "Industrial Revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": " . . .The person of the King is sacred, and to attack him in any way is an attack on religion itself. Kings represent the divine majesty and have been appointed by Him to carry out His purposes. Serving God and respecting kings are bound together.    Bishop Jacques Bossuet   ",
        "correct_answer": "Louis XIV",
        "distractor1": "John Locke",
        "distractor2": "Karl Marx",
        "distractor3": "Elizabeth II"
    },
    {
        "question": "Francis Bacon, Galileo, and Isaac Newton promoted the idea that knowledge should be based on",
        "correct_answer": "experimentation and observation",
        "distractor1": "the experiences of past civilizations",
        "distractor2": "emotions and feelings",
        "distractor3": "the teachings of the Catholic Church"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Scientific Revolution and the Enlightenment, one similarity in the work of many scientists and philosophers was that they",
        "correct_answer": "examined natural laws governing the universe",
        "distractor1": "relied heavily on the ideas of medieval thinkers",
        "distractor2": "favored an absolute monarchy as a way of improving economic conditions",
        "distractor3": "received support from the Catholic Church"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the effects of the works of Nicolaus Copernicus, Galileo Galilei, Sir",
        "correct_answer": "The scientific method was used to solve problems.",
        "distractor1": "The acceptance of traditional authority was strengthened.",
        "distractor2": "Funding to education was increased by the English government.",
        "distractor3": "Interest in Greek and Roman drama was renewed."
    },
    {
        "question": "  Speaker A  : Good government stresses the importance of the nation and accepts the rights of the individual only if the interests of the individual are the same as those of the nation.",
        "correct_answer": "C",
        "distractor1": "A",
        "distractor2": "B",
        "distractor3": "D"
    },
    {
        "question": "  Speaker A  :  The story of history is the story of class struggles.  Revolution is necessary to overthrow the ruling class and eventually create a classless society in which no one will be exploited.",
        "correct_answer": "D",
        "distractor1": "A",
        "distractor2": "B",
        "distractor3": "C"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is a valid generalization about the immediate results of the French Revolution of 1789?",
        "correct_answer": "the French middle class gained more power",
        "distractor1": "the Roman Catholic Church increased its power and wealth",
        "distractor2": "the revolution achieved its goal of establishing peace, democracy, and justice for all",
        "distractor3": "the revolution had little impact outside France"
    },
    {
        "question": "In France, which was a major result of the French Revolution?",
        "correct_answer": "the middle class gained political influence",
        "distractor1": "the king was restored to unlimited power",
        "distractor2": "the clergy dominated government",
        "distractor3": "the tax burden was carried by the lower class"
    },
    {
        "question": "A study of revolutions would most likely lead to the conclusion that pre-Revolutionary governments",
        "correct_answer": "fail to meet the political and economic needs of their people",
        "distractor1": "are more concerned about human rights than the governments that replace them",
        "distractor2": "refuse to modernize their armed forces with advanced technology",
        "distractor3": "attempt to bring about the separation of government from religion"
    },
    {
        "question": " Congress of Vienna Restores Monarchy to France    Czar Nicholas I Limits Freedom of the Russian Press  ",
        "correct_answer": "reactions to the French Revolution",
        "distractor1": "movements to unify all of western Europe",
        "distractor2": "efforts to improve the conditions of factory workers",
        "distractor3": "attempts to promote trade between European nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "The French people supported Napoleon Bonaparte because they hoped he would ",
        "correct_answer": "provide stability for the nation",
        "distractor1": "adopt the ideas of the Protestant Reformation",
        "distractor2": "restore Louis XVI to power",
        "distractor3": "end British control of France"
    },
    {
        "question": "Simon Bolivar and Miguel Hidalgo, leaders of Latin American independence movements, were inspired by successful revolutions in",
        "correct_answer": "the Untied States and France",
        "distractor1": "the Soviet Union and China",
        "distractor2": "Cuba and Costa Rica",
        "distractor3": "Egypt and Kenya"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the early 1800 s, which was a major influence on the struggle for political independence in Latin America?",
        "correct_answer": "the American and French Revolutions",
        "distractor1": "poor conditions in urban centers in Latin America",
        "distractor2": "the desire of the Roman Catholic Church in Latin America to escape European control",
        "distractor3": "demands by Latin American workers to own their own factories"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity in the leadership of Latin Americas Jose de San Martin, Toussaint l Ouverture, Bernanrdo O Higgins, and Pedro I was that each leader",
        "correct_answer": "led a struggle to gain freedom for the people of his nation",
        "distractor1": "opposed United States intervention in Haiti",
        "distractor2": "opposed membership of his nation in the League of Nations",
        "distractor3": "established an absolute monarchy in his nation"
    },
    {
        "question": " I will never allow my hands to be idle nor my soul to rest until I have broken the chains laid upon us by Spain. ",
        "correct_answer": "a Latin American nationalist",
        "distractor1": "a Portuguese explorer",
        "distractor2": "a Roman Catholic bishop",
        "distractor3": "a Spanish conquistador"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these situations was the direct result of the other three?",
        "correct_answer": "nations of Latin America won independence",
        "distractor1": "revolutions occurred in North America and France",
        "distractor2": "the Napoleonic wars weakened Spain s power",
        "distractor3": "creoles and mestizos became discontented with Spanish rule"
    },
    {
        "question": "The 19th-century independence movements in Latin America were influenced by",
        "correct_answer": "the American and the French Revolutions",
        "distractor1": "Marxist ideology",
        "distractor2": "the Aztec wars against Hernando Cortez",
        "distractor3": "liberation theology"
    },
    {
        "question": "Simon Bolivar, Toussaint L Overture, and Bernardo O Higgins were Latin American leaders of",
        "correct_answer": "independence movements",
        "distractor1": "economic development",
        "distractor2": "educational reforms",
        "distractor3": "colonial expansion"
    },
    {
        "question": "In which region of the world did the American Revolution and the French Revolution have the greatest influence during the 1800 s?",
        "correct_answer": "Latin America",
        "distractor1": "Southeast Asia",
        "distractor2": "South Asia",
        "distractor3": "sub-Saharan Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sim n Bol var, Jos  de San Mart n, and Toussaint l Ouverture are important in Latin American history because they were",
        "correct_answer": "leaders of liberation movements",
        "distractor1": "20th-century caudillos",
        "distractor2": "members of the Organization of American States (OAS)",
        "distractor3": "winners of the Nobel Peace Prize"
    },
    {
        "question": " A country is not merely a geographic territory.  A country is also the idea given birth by the geographic territory.  A country is a sense of love that unites, as one, all the sons and daughters of that geographic territory  ",
        "correct_answer": "nationalism",
        "distractor1": "totalitarian rule",
        "distractor2": "absolute monarchy",
        "distractor3": "mercantilism"
    },
    {
        "question": "In a number of European countries in the 1800 s, which situation occurred as a result of the influence of the French Revolution?",
        "correct_answer": "rise of nationalistic movements",
        "distractor1": "increase in religious conflict",
        "distractor2": "decentralization of governmental power",
        "distractor3": "economic depression"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which quotation best reflects a feeling of nationalism?",
        "correct_answer": " For God, King, and Country ",
        "distractor1": " An eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth ",
        "distractor2": " A person s greatest social obligation is loyalty to the family ",
        "distractor3": " Opposition to evil is as much a duty as is cooperation with good "
    },
    {
        "question": "Nationalism is most likely to develop in an area that has",
        "correct_answer": "common customs, language, and history",
        "distractor1": "land suited to agriculture",
        "distractor2": "adequate industry to supply consumer demands",
        "distractor3": "a moderate climate with rivers for irrigation"
    },
    {
        "question": "Nationalism is best defined as",
        "correct_answer": "the loyalty of a people to their values, traditions, and a geographic region",
        "distractor1": "the achievement of world peace and global understanding",
        "distractor2": "the desire to take over other societies by force",
        "distractor3": "a method of solving basic economic problems of the society"
    },
    {
        "question": "The best example of the success of nationalism in Europe is the",
        "correct_answer": "unification of Germany",
        "distractor1": "development of socialism in France",
        "distractor2": "Industrial Revolution in Great Britain",
        "distractor3": "establishment of the Common Market"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which condition is most necessary to the process of industrialization in a society?",
        "correct_answer": "availability of investment capital",
        "distractor1": "dependence on subsistence agriculture",
        "distractor2": "creation of a one-crop economy",
        "distractor3": "capture of foreign lands"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Karl Marx, history is the record of the",
        "correct_answer": "struggle between classes in society",
        "distractor1": "granting of more political liberties to all people",
        "distractor2": "wars and conflicts between national leaders",
        "distractor3": "increasing prosperity brought about by industrialization"
    },
    {
        "question": "A main idea of Karl Marx and Friedrich Engles  Communist Manifesto is that the proletariat",
        "correct_answer": "must unite to overthrow the capitalist class",
        "distractor1": "would need foreign help to achieve its revolutionary ends",
        "distractor2": "had to cooperate with the capitalists to gain economic rewards",
        "distractor3": "should allow the capitalists to control the means of production"
    },
    {
        "question": " Revolution will occur more and more frequently in the industrialized nations as the proletariat struggles to overcome the abuses of the capitalist system. ",
        "correct_answer": "Karl Marx",
        "distractor1": "Charles Darwin",
        "distractor2": "Niccolo Machiavelli",
        "distractor3": "John Locke"
    },
    {
        "question": " The proletarians have nothing to lose but their chains Workers of the world, unite! ",
        "correct_answer": "Industrial Revolution",
        "distractor1": "Protestant Reformation",
        "distractor2": "Counter-Reformation",
        "distractor3": "Commercial Revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "Before a nation can begin to industrialize, that nation must first develop",
        "correct_answer": "an adequate food supply",
        "distractor1": "a democratic government",
        "distractor2": "a rigid class structure",
        "distractor3": "a strong religious foundation"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major result of the Industrial Revolution was the",
        "correct_answer": "concentration of workers in urban areas",
        "distractor1": "increased desire of the wealthy class to share its power",
        "distractor2": "formation of powerful craft guilds",
        "distractor3": "control of agricultural production by governments"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to the theories of Karl Marx, history can be viewed as a",
        "correct_answer": "continuous struggle between economic classes",
        "distractor1": "succession of famines that result in the destruction of civilizations",
        "distractor2": "repeating cycle of imperialism and colonialism",
        "distractor3": "listing of the accomplishments of the ruling classes"
    },
    {
        "question": "-Europeans sought new markets for their goods.  -Many Europeans migrated to the cities in search of jobs. ",
        "correct_answer": "Industrial Revolution",
        "distractor1": "rise of feudalism",
        "distractor2": "Congress of Vienna",
        "distractor3": "French Revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which revolution inspired Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels to express their ideas in The Communist Manifesto? ",
        "correct_answer": "Industrial",
        "distractor1": "Scientific",
        "distractor2": "Glorious",
        "distractor3": "Neolithic"
    },
    {
        "question": "Before Commodore Matthew Perry s expedition to Japan in 1853, Japan was most influenced by",
        "correct_answer": "China s religion, art, and writing",
        "distractor1": "Russia s need for warm water ports",
        "distractor2": "the introduction of advanced technology from the United States",
        "distractor3": "France s quest for new colonies"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Japan, the Meiji Restoration resulted in the",
        "correct_answer": "modernization of the nation s industry",
        "distractor1": "division of the nation between the European powers",
        "distractor2": "abolition of the position of emperor",
        "distractor3": "government being controlled by the samurai"
    },
    {
        "question": "An immediate result of Commodore Matthew Perry s visit to Japan in 1853 was",
        "correct_answer": "the development of trade between Japan and the West",
        "distractor1": "an alliance between Japan and Russia",
        "distractor2": "a war between Japan and the United States",
        "distractor3": "the continued isolation of Japan"
    },
    {
        "question": "The arrival of Commodore Matthew Perry in Japan in 1853 signaled the end of Japanese",
        "correct_answer": "policies of isolationism",
        "distractor1": "cultural contacts with the West",
        "distractor2": "militarism in Southeast Asia",
        "distractor3": "trade relations with the United States"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major goal of the Meiji government in Japan was to",
        "correct_answer": "establish Japan as an industrial power",
        "distractor1": "isolate Japan from other nations",
        "distractor2": "achieve political union with China",
        "distractor3": "encourage colonization of Asia by Western nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "The modernization of Japan during the Meiji Restoration resulted in",
        "correct_answer": "the rise of Japan as an imperialistic nation",
        "distractor1": "a return to a feudal system of government",
        "distractor2": "an alliance between China, Korea, Russia, and Japan",
        "distractor3": "a strengthening of Japan s isolationist policies"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes events in Japan during the period of the Meiji Restoration?",
        "correct_answer": "Rapid industrialization and economic growth occurred.",
        "distractor1": "Japan sought to isolate itself from world affairs.",
        "distractor2": "Local lords increased their power over the Japanese emperor.",
        "distractor3": "Agriculture was taken over by the government."
    },
    {
        "question": "A primary purpose for building the Suez Canal was to",
        "correct_answer": "increase trade between the Middle East, Europe and Asia",
        "distractor1": "encourage Jewish settlement in nearby Palestine",
        "distractor2": "reduce the time needed for travel between the Atlantic Ocean and the Caribbean Sea",
        "distractor3": "allow Indian merchants to reach the east coast of Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is an accurate statement about the partitioning of Africa by European imperialist nations during the 1800 s?",
        "correct_answer": "the cultural and ethnic diversity of the African people was disregarded",
        "distractor1": "new nations were based on old tribal boundaries",
        "distractor2": "the continent was divided equally among the colonial powers",
        "distractor3": "African unity was encouraged"
    },
    {
        "question": "After 1880, European nations sought colonies in Africa primarily because the Europeans were",
        "correct_answer": "competing of raw materials and markets",
        "distractor1": "in need of land for their surplus populations",
        "distractor2": "determined to bring Christianity to the Moslem world",
        "distractor3": "interested in completing their geographic knowledge of the world"
    },
    {
        "question": "The 19th century term  White Man s Burden  reflects the idea that",
        "correct_answer": "Europeans had a responsibility to improve the lives of the colonial peoples",
        "distractor1": "Asians and Africans were equal to Europeans",
        "distractor2": "Asians and Africans would be grateful for European help",
        "distractor3": "imperialism was opposed by most Europeans"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Sepoy Mutiny in India, the Boxer Rebellion in China, and the Islamic Revolution in Iran were similar in that they",
        "correct_answer": "resisted foreign influence in these countries",
        "distractor1": "restored power to the hereditary monarchies",
        "distractor2": "attempted to reject the traditional cultures in these countries",
        "distractor3": "reestablished the power of religious leaders"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 19th century, Europeans were able to divide China in Spheres of Influence mainly because the",
        "correct_answer": "Europeans had technologically superior military forces",
        "distractor1": "Chinese were eager to adopt western culture",
        "distractor2": "Europeans were willing to adopt Chinese customs",
        "distractor3": "Chinese lacked raw materials and resources"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Boxer Rebellion of the early 20th century was an attempt to",
        "correct_answer": "remove foreign influences from China",
        "distractor1": "eliminate poverty among the Chinese peasants",
        "distractor2": "bring western-style democracy to China",
        "distractor3": "restore trade between China and European nations"
    },
    {
        "question": " Yesterday, your ambassador petitioned my ministers regarding your trade with China our Celestial Empire possesses all things in great abundance and lacks no product within its own borders.  There is, therefore, no need to import any product manufactured by outside barbarians in exchange for our own goods. ",
        "correct_answer": "maintaining economic isolation",
        "distractor1": "expanding foreign trade",
        "distractor2": "increasing international interdependence",
        "distractor3": "developing into a colonial power"
    },
    {
        "question": "British control over South Africa, French control over Indochina, and Spanish control over Mexico are examples of",
        "correct_answer": "imperialism",
        "distractor1": "isolationism",
        "distractor2": "appeasement",
        "distractor3": "nonalignment"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the past, European nations have conquered other lands, made them into colonies, and controlled their economies.",
        "correct_answer": "imperialism",
        "distractor1": "socialism",
        "distractor2": "isolationism",
        "distractor3": "monotheism"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the past, European nations have conquered other lands, made them into colonies, and controlled their economies.",
        "correct_answer": "industrialization of Europe and the need for raw materials",
        "distractor1": "desire of Europeans to spread communism throughout the world",
        "distractor2": "European belief in human rights for all people",
        "distractor3": "requests of developing nations for modern machines and technology"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1840 s, China signed  unequal treaties  with Western nations mainly because",
        "correct_answer": "Western nations had superior military technology",
        "distractor1": "China had won the Opium War",
        "distractor2": "leaders in China favored expansion",
        "distractor3": "China had requested economic assistance from the West"
    },
    {
        "question": "Throughout the 1800 s, an increased need for both raw materials and new markets for manufactured goods led various European nations to pursue policies of",
        "correct_answer": "imperialism",
        "distractor1": "socialism",
        "distractor2": "isolationism",
        "distractor3": "communism"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 18th and 19th centuries, increased contact between European and the continents of Africa, Asia, and South America resulted in",
        "correct_answer": "the exploitation of the labor and resources of these continents",
        "distractor1": "closer cultural cooperation between Europe and these continents",
        "distractor2": "a return to the political and economic systems of feudal Europe",
        "distractor3": "preservation of the rights of the indigenous peoples"
    },
    {
        "question": "Take up the White Man s burden ",
        "correct_answer": "negative attitude of Europeans toward peoples of the non-Western world",
        "distractor1": "advantages Europeans would gain by colonizing Africa, Asia, and Latin America",
        "distractor2": "positive role of the Roman Catholic Church in Africa and Asia",
        "distractor3": "challenges non-Europeans faced when trading with the Europeans"
    },
    {
        "question": "Both the French and the British were interested in controlling Egypt in the mid-19th century because Egypt had",
        "correct_answer": "a strategic location",
        "distractor1": "control of the spice trade",
        "distractor2": "an industrial-based economy",
        "distractor3": "vital mineral resources"
    },
    {
        "question": " , you, Africa, suffered like a beast  Your ashes strewn to the wind that roams the desert, ",
        "correct_answer": "imperialism",
        "distractor1": "communism",
        "distractor2": "nationalism",
        "distractor3": "regionalism"
    },
    {
        "question": "The results of the Opium War (1839-1842) indicate that China was",
        "correct_answer": "not strong enough to resist Western demands",
        "distractor1": "still a major military power",
        "distractor2": "rapidly building a modern industrial economy",
        "distractor3": "accepting Western nations as equal trading partners"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 18th and 19th centuries, Europeans improved roads and bridges and built railroads in their colonies primarily to",
        "correct_answer": "obtain raw materials needed for industrialization",
        "distractor1": "provide jobs for the colonists",
        "distractor2": "impress the colonists with their technological knowledge",
        "distractor3": "help missionaries spread Christianity"
    },
    {
        "question": " Compared to other peoples of the world we have the greatest (largest) population and our civilization is four thousand years old Today we are the poorest and weakest nation in the world and occupy the lowest position in international affairs.  Other men are the carving knife and serving dish, we are the fish and the meat.  As a consequence we are being transformed everywhere into a colony of the foreign powers. ",
        "correct_answer": "Opium War and Boxer Rebellion",
        "distractor1": "Mau Mau uprising and adoption of apartheid",
        "distractor2": "Sepoy Mutiny and the Salt March",
        "distractor3": "Haitian Revolution and Cortes  march on Mexico City"
    },
    {
        "question": "One result of British colonialism in India was that India",
        "correct_answer": "adopted a parliamentary system of government",
        "distractor1": "developed religious unity",
        "distractor2": "supported Western foreign policies in the United Nations",
        "distractor3": "created programs to increase its population"
    },
    {
        "question": " The Ashanti and Ijebu... strongly resisted missionary incursion [interference]-for a time at least . . . Both groups grudgingly [reluctantly] accepted missionaries and their schools only after military defeat by imperial forces.       Edward H. Berman",
        "correct_answer": "opposed giving up their religious and cultural heritage",
        "distractor1": "returned to the worship of their traditional gods after the defeat of the missionaries",
        "distractor2": "cooperated with the missionaries for economic gain",
        "distractor3": "feared that missionaries would refuse to teach their children"
    },
    {
        "question": "In 19th-century China, the Opium War resulted in",
        "correct_answer": "an increase in European spheres of influence in China",
        "distractor1": "the control of Hong Kong being returned to China",
        "distractor2": "the removal of all British naval forces from China",
        "distractor3": "the rejection of Buddhism by the Chinese people"
    },
    {
        "question": "The borders that were established for many African nations during the late 1800 s were based primarily on",
        "correct_answer": "territorial claims of colonial rulers",
        "distractor1": "natural geographic barriers",
        "distractor2": "easy access to natural resources",
        "distractor3": "cultural differences between ethnic groups"
    },
    {
        "question": "An analysis of the Russo-Japanese War and the Boer War shows that one reason nations go to war is to ",
        "correct_answer": "satisfy imperialist goals",
        "distractor1": "assist oppressed people",
        "distractor2": "spread religious beliefs",
        "distractor3": "honor provisions of a treaty"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best expresses the motive for 19th-century European imperialism?",
        "correct_answer": "Imperialism would benefit the economies of the colonial powers.",
        "distractor1": "Living space was needed for the excess population in western Europe.",
        "distractor2": "European leaders believed imperialism was an effective method of reducing the number of wars.",
        "distractor3": "European nations would benefit from some aspects of the conquered nation s culture."
    },
    {
        "question": "In 1917, Bolshevik leaders in Russia sought peace with Germany because the new Russian government",
        "correct_answer": "wanted to retain power and avoid German occupation",
        "distractor1": "decided to join forces with Germany and the Central Powers",
        "distractor2": "needed to concentrate its troops and resources on its war with Turkey",
        "distractor3": "needed to control the Baltic Sea and wanted a warm water port"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Eastern Europe after World War I, the greatest obstacle to national unity in many nation-states was the",
        "correct_answer": "great ethnic diversity found in the region",
        "distractor1": "economic dependence of Eastern Europe on Japan",
        "distractor2": "acceptance of democratic traditions by most Eastern Europeans",
        "distractor3": "expansion of United States influence in the region"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the relationship between World War I and the Russian Revolution?",
        "correct_answer": "World War I created conditions within Russia that helped trigger a revolution",
        "distractor1": "World War I postponed the Russian Revolution by restoring confidence in the Czar",
        "distractor2": "the Russian Revolution inspired the Russian people to win World War I",
        "distractor3": "World War I gave the Czar s army the needed experience to suppress the Russian Revolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major cause of World War I was",
        "correct_answer": "the existence of opposing alliances",
        "distractor1": "a decline in the policy of imperialism",
        "distractor2": "an increase in acts of aggression by England",
        "distractor3": "the spread of communism throughout Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why was the Balkan region referred to as the  Powder Keg of Europe  prior to World War I?",
        "correct_answer": "Nationalistic and imperialistic rivalries were increasing.",
        "distractor1": "The aggression of the Ottoman Empire was disrupting the balance of power.",
        "distractor2": "Yugoslavia was invading its neighboring countries.",
        "distractor3": "The area was the leading supplier of military equipment to the rest of the world."
    },
    {
        "question": "The major impact of the Treaty of Versailles on Germany was that the treaty led to",
        "correct_answer": "an increase in Germany s desire to regain its power and prestige",
        "distractor1": "an era of peace and international good will in Germany",
        "distractor2": "a stable Germany that was both democratic and strong",
        "distractor3": "a leadership position for Germany in the League of Nations"
    },
    {
        "question": " Archduke Franz Ferdinand Assassinated!    Germany Declares War on Russia and France!  ",
        "correct_answer": "World War I",
        "distractor1": "Franco-Prussian War",
        "distractor2": "Crimean War",
        "distractor3": "Cold War"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is generally a characteristic of a communist economy?",
        "correct_answer": "government agencies are involved in production planning",
        "distractor1": "investment is encouraged by the promise of large profits",
        "distractor2": "the role of government in the economy is restricted by law",
        "distractor3": "entrepreneurs sell shares in their companies to the government"
    },
    {
        "question": " A group of planners makes all economic decisions. The group assigns natural, human, and capital resources to the production of those goods and services it wants. The group decides how to produce them and to whom to distribute them ",
        "correct_answer": "command economy of the Soviet Union",
        "distractor1": "manorial economy of feudal Europe",
        "distractor2": "mercantile economy of 18th century Europe",
        "distractor3": "market economy of the United States"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which situation resulted from the Russo-Japanese War of 1905?",
        "correct_answer": "dissident groups challenged the power of the Russian Czar",
        "distractor1": "Japan lost its status as a world power",
        "distractor2": "the Japanese Emperor encouraged reforms in Russia",
        "distractor3": "Russia gained control of China and Japan"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stalin s Five-Year Plans and his decision to form collectives are examples of",
        "correct_answer": "strategies to modernize the economy of the Soviet Union through forced communism",
        "distractor1": "a more friendly foreign policy toward China",
        "distractor2": "methods of dealing with the United States during the Cold War",
        "distractor3": "programs to westernize, educate, and enlighten the population"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major cause of the Russian Revolution of 1917 was the",
        "correct_answer": "existence of sharp economic differences between social classes",
        "distractor1": "defeat of Germany in the Russian campaign",
        "distractor2": "marriage of Czar Nicholas II to a German princess",
        "distractor3": "appeal of Marxism to the Russian nobility"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is an accurate statement about the Soviet economy under the leadership of Joseph Stalin?",
        "correct_answer": "the Soviet Union increased its industrial output by developing heavy industry",
        "distractor1": "a large selection of consumer goods became available",
        "distractor2": "private farmers were encouraged to sell their surplus produce in an open market",
        "distractor3": "the government reduced its role in planning industrial production"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major effect of Josef Stalin s policy of Collectivization on Soviet agriculture was",
        "correct_answer": "a widespread food shortage throughout the nation",
        "distractor1": "an increase in the export of agricultural products",
        "distractor2": "a surplus of agricultural goods",
        "distractor3": "the immediate creation of many small private farms"
    },
    {
        "question": "One action taken by both V.I. Lenin and Joseph Stalin was",
        "correct_answer": "jailing or murdering potential opponents",
        "distractor1": "attempting to bring democracy to Russia",
        "distractor2": "supporting the Russian Orthodox Church",
        "distractor3": "providing economic aid to Japan after World War I and World War II"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Russian peasants supported the Bolsheviks in the 1917 Revolutions mainly because the Bolsheviks promised to",
        "correct_answer": "redistribute the land owned by the nobility",
        "distractor1": "establish collective farms",
        "distractor2": "maintain the agricultural price-support system",
        "distractor3": "bring modern technology to Russian farms"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the political situation in the Soviet Union immediately after Lenin s death in 1924?",
        "correct_answer": "a power struggle developed among Communist Party leaders",
        "distractor1": "the nation adopted a constitutional monarchy",
        "distractor2": "Trotsky and his followers assumed full control of the Communist Party",
        "distractor3": "popular elections were held to choose a new general secretary"
    },
    {
        "question": "The term that best describes the position of Jews in Czarist Russia is",
        "correct_answer": "persecuted minority",
        "distractor1": "political elite",
        "distractor2": "landed gentry",
        "distractor3": "military leaders"
    },
    {
        "question": "  the organizations of the revolutionaries must consist first, foremost, and mainly of people who make revolutionary activity their profession such an organization must of necessity be not too extensive and as secret as possible  ",
        "correct_answer": "overthrow the Russian government",
        "distractor1": "defeat Germany in World War I",
        "distractor2": "establish democracy in Russia",
        "distractor3": "maintain communist power in Western Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "The 1917 victory of the communists in Russia was a contradiction of Marxist theory because Russia was",
        "correct_answer": "mainly an agricultural society",
        "distractor1": "already ruled by a socialist government",
        "distractor2": "involved in World War I",
        "distractor3": "not considered to be a military power"
    },
    {
        "question": "Josef Stalin s leadership of the Soviet Union can best be characterized as a period of",
        "correct_answer": "censorship and terror",
        "distractor1": "democratic reform and nationalism",
        "distractor2": "humanism and democracy",
        "distractor3": "religious freedom and tolerance"
    },
    {
        "question": "The political reorganization of Russia after the Communist Revolution of 1917 resulted in",
        "correct_answer": "a federation of socialist republics",
        "distractor1": "the establishment of a two-party political system",
        "distractor2": "increased political power for ethnic minorities",
        "distractor3": "a limited monarchy with the czar as a figurehead"
    },
    {
        "question": "Under Josef Stalin, the Soviet Union emphasized centralized economic planning and Five-Year Plans primarily to",
        "correct_answer": "develop heavy industry",
        "distractor1": "produce more consumer goods",
        "distractor2": "expand exports",
        "distractor3": "create a demand for high-quality imports"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which characteristic was common to both Russia under the Czars and the Soviet Union under Josef Stalin?",
        "correct_answer": "persecution of political dissenters",
        "distractor1": "a lack of concern about territorial expansion",
        "distractor2": "support of artistic and literary freedom",
        "distractor3": "encouragement of free enterprise"
    },
    {
        "question": "Under Joseph Stalin, life in the Soviet Union was characterized by",
        "correct_answer": "the use of censorship and the secret police",
        "distractor1": "an abundance of consumer goods",
        "distractor2": "political instability and numerous civil wars",
        "distractor3": "support for small family-run farms"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which slogan expressed the ideals of the Bolshevik Revolution of 1917?",
        "correct_answer": "Bread, Land, and Peace",
        "distractor1": "Liberty, Equality, and Fraternity",
        "distractor2": "Land and Liberty",
        "distractor3": "Nationalism, Democracy, and the People s Livelihood"
    },
    {
        "question": "Russian peasants supported the Bolsheviks in 1917 primarily because the Bolsheviks pledged to",
        "correct_answer": "redistribute land and make peace",
        "distractor1": "establish and maintain collective farms",
        "distractor2": "keep crop yields low",
        "distractor3": "limit the income of the nobility"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes a relationship between World War I and the Bolshevik Revolution?",
        "correct_answer": "World War I created conditions in Russia that helped trigger a revolution.",
        "distractor1": "World War I postponed the revolution in Russia by restoring confidence in the Czar.",
        "distractor2": "Opposing Russian forces cooperated to fight the foreign invaders.",
        "distractor3": "World War I gave the Czar s army the needed experience to suppress the revolution."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Kirghiz with whom we stopped was very well off. . . . After some tea our host asked me,  Where is the Ak Padsha now, the White Tsar Nikolai?    He and all his family, the Tsaritsa, their daughters and son, have been killed by the Bolsheviks,  I answered. ",
        "correct_answer": "after the Russian Revolution",
        "distractor1": "during the Napoleonic Wars",
        "distractor2": "after Mao Zedong came to power",
        "distractor3": "during World War II"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 1920 s and 1930 s, the rise of totalitarian governments in Germany, Italy, and Spain was largely the result of",
        "correct_answer": "severe economic and social problems that arose in Europe after World War I",
        "distractor1": "the success of the Communists in establishing a command economy in the Soviet Union",
        "distractor2": "the active support of the United States",
        "distractor3": "movements demanding the return of the old monarchies"
    },
    {
        "question": "The harsh conditions imposed by the Treaty of Versailles after World War I helped lay the foundation for the",
        "correct_answer": "rise of fascism Germany",
        "distractor1": "uprisings during the French Revolution",
        "distractor2": "division of Korea along the 38th parallel",
        "distractor3": "Bolshevik Revolution in Russia"
    },
    {
        "question": "Between the Meiji Restoration and World War II, Japan tried to solve the problem of its scarcity of natural resources by",
        "correct_answer": "establishing a policy of imperialism",
        "distractor1": "exporting agricultural products in exchange for new technology",
        "distractor2": "building nuclear power plants",
        "distractor3": "cooperating with the Soviet Union to gain needed resources"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which idea was included in the provisions of the Treaty of Versailles to show the intent of the Allies to punish the Central Powers for their role in World War II?",
        "correct_answer": "Germany will accept full responsibility for causing the war",
        "distractor1": "all nations shall maintain open covenants of peace",
        "distractor2": "freedom of the seas will be maintained",
        "distractor3": "territorial settlements shall be made along clearly recognizable lines of nationality"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fascism in Europe during the 1920 s and 1930 s is best described as a",
        "correct_answer": "form of totalitarianism that glorified the state above the individual",
        "distractor1": "demonstration of laissez-faire capitalism that promoted free enterprise",
        "distractor2": "type of economic system that stressed a classless society",
        "distractor3": "set of humanist ideas that emphasized the dignity and worth of the individual"
    },
    {
        "question": "Censorship, mass arrests, and a secret police force are most characteristic of",
        "correct_answer": "totalitarian regimes",
        "distractor1": "parliamentary democracies",
        "distractor2": "republics",
        "distractor3": "constitutional monarchies"
    },
    {
        "question": "After World War I, Japan attempted to solve some of its economic problems by",
        "correct_answer": "expanding its influence in Asia",
        "distractor1": "establishing extensive trade with the Soviet Union",
        "distractor2": "practicing the principles of Marxism",
        "distractor3": "refusing to rely on Western technology"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which policy shows that appeasement does not always prevent war?",
        "correct_answer": "British policy toward Germany in Munich during the 1930 s",
        "distractor1": "French policy in Indochina in the 1950 s",
        "distractor2": "United States policy toward Cuba in the early 1960 s",
        "distractor3": "Iraqi policy toward Iran in the 1980 s"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 1930 s, the Japanese government followed a policy of imperialism primarily to",
        "correct_answer": "acquire new sources of raw materials",
        "distractor1": "spread Zen Buddhism throughout Asia",
        "distractor2": "sell more consumer goods to European nations",
        "distractor3": "spread the ideas of bushido"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was one reason the Nazi programs and policies of the early 1930 s appealed to many people in Germany?",
        "correct_answer": "the people were frustrated with their current economic and political situation",
        "distractor1": "Germany had been denied membership in the United Nations",
        "distractor2": "a coup d etat had forced communism on the German people",
        "distractor3": "the German people feared that the French of the British would soon gain control of the Polish corridor"
    },
    {
        "question": "The imperialist policies followed by Japan after World War I were based on a desire to",
        "correct_answer": "obtain natural resources for manufacturing",
        "distractor1": "convert people to Shinto",
        "distractor2": "acquire markets for its oil industry",
        "distractor3": "compete with Chinese trade policies"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the mid-1930 s, which characteristic was common to Fascist Italy, Nazi Germany, and Communist Russia?",
        "correct_answer": "one-party system that denied basic human rights",
        "distractor1": "government ownership of the means of production and distribution",
        "distractor2": "encouragement of individual freedom of expression in the arts",
        "distractor3": "emphasis on consumer goods rather than on weapons"
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason the Fascist governments of Benito Mussolini and Adolf Hitler came to power in Italy",
        "correct_answer": "faced economic and political difficulties",
        "distractor1": "were threatened by the United States",
        "distractor2": "supported civil liberties for all",
        "distractor3": "failed to join the League of Nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a characteristic of Germany under Adolf Hitler and the Soviet Union under Josef Stalin?",
        "correct_answer": "governmental control of the media",
        "distractor1": "an official foreign policy of isolationism",
        "distractor2": "public ownership of business and industry",
        "distractor3": "the absence of a written constitution"
    },
    {
        "question": "World War II is often considered to be a turning point in history because",
        "correct_answer": "European domination of the world began to weaken as nationalism in colonies increased",
        "distractor1": "the League of nations demonstrated that an international organization could maintain world peace",
        "distractor2": "the war brought an end to dictatorships as a form of government",
        "distractor3": "religious and ethnic differences were no longer a source of conflict between nations"
    },
    {
        "question": " From as early as I can remember, the Emperor was an important presence even in our remote home.  He was a descendant of the gods from thousands of years before, never to be looked at or listened to by mere mortals, a presence to be revered and protected and obeyed Finally , my family and neighbors gathered around the radio and listened in stunned silence to the voice that had never before been heard, saying he was only human after all.  Everyone was crying.  I was sad and confused  ",
        "correct_answer": "defeat of the Japanese in World War II",
        "distractor1": "his overthrow by communist forces",
        "distractor2": "signing of the Versailles Treaty",
        "distractor3": "conclusion of the Russo-Japanese War"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which reform took place in Japan after World War II?",
        "correct_answer": "Japan became a representative democracy",
        "distractor1": "Japan s industrial capability was greatly reduced",
        "distractor2": "the Emperor s position was abolished",
        "distractor3": "labor unions were declared illegal"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major factor in the economic recoveries of Japan and West Germany after World War II was their",
        "correct_answer": "need to replace destroyed factories",
        "distractor1": "desire to avoid an invasion from China",
        "distractor2": "acceptance into the United Nations",
        "distractor3": "ability to produce nuclear weapons"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor most enabled Japan to rebuild and modernize rapidly after World War II?",
        "correct_answer": "a well-trained workforce",
        "distractor1": "vast mineral reserves",
        "distractor2": "large amounts of fertile land",
        "distractor3": "a strong military"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is one major reason the Holocaust is considered a unique event in modern European history?",
        "correct_answer": "The genocide was planned in great detail and required the cooperation of many people.",
        "distractor1": "Jews of Europe have seldom been victims of persecution.",
        "distractor2": "Civilians rarely were killed during air raids on Great Britain.",
        "distractor3": "Adolf Hitler concealed his anti-Jewish feelings until after he came to power."
    },
    {
        "question": "The economic policies of the Soviet Union traditionally emphasized the production of",
        "correct_answer": "heavy industrial goods",
        "distractor1": "automobiles for export",
        "distractor2": "building materials for luxury housing",
        "distractor3": "consumer goods"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is generally a characteristic of a communist economy?",
        "correct_answer": "government agencies are involved in production planning",
        "distractor1": "investment is encouraged by the promise of large profits",
        "distractor2": "the role of government in the economy is restricted by law",
        "distractor3": "entrepreneurs sell shares in their companies to the government"
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason the Soviet Union formed the Warsaw Pact was to",
        "correct_answer": "limit the threat of invasion from Western Europe",
        "distractor1": "ease the transition to democracy",
        "distractor2": "help institute capitalism in Eastern Europe",
        "distractor3": "challenge the economic successes of the Common Market"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes most Eastern European countries immediately after World War II?  They",
        "correct_answer": "became satellite states of the Soviet Union",
        "distractor1": "adopted democratic reforms in their political systems",
        "distractor2": "became dependent on aid provided by the Marshall Plan",
        "distractor3": "emerged as world economic powers"
    },
    {
        "question": "Communist governments were established in most nations of Eastern Europe shortly after World War II because",
        "correct_answer": "the Soviet Union used military and diplomatic pressures to install their governments",
        "distractor1": "the region had a long tradition of strong communist parties",
        "distractor2": "communist governments were able to significantly increase agricultural productivity",
        "distractor3": "members of the Communist party won free elections in these nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Cold War Era (1945-1990), the United States and the Soviet Union were reluctant to become involved in direct military conflict mainly because of",
        "correct_answer": "the potential for global nuclear destruction",
        "distractor1": "the peacekeeping role of the United Nations",
        "distractor2": "pressure from nonaligned nations",
        "distractor3": "increased tensions in the Middle East"
    },
    {
        "question": "After World War II, the Soviet Union established satellites in Eastern Europe to",
        "correct_answer": "expand its power and control over Eastern Europe",
        "distractor1": "support the remaining Fascist governments in Eastern Europe",
        "distractor2": "preserve capitalism in Eastern Europe",
        "distractor3": "establish democratic governments in Eastern European nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Soviet Union, a negative aspect of the Cold War Era was the",
        "correct_answer": "high cost of maintaining the arms race",
        "distractor1": "attempt to preserve democratic ideals",
        "distractor2": "development of peaceful uses for modern technology",
        "distractor3": "development of effective means of international cooperation"
    },
    {
        "question": " From Stetin in the Baltic to Trieste in the Adriatic, an Iron Curtain has descended across the continent. Behind that line lie all the capitals of the ancient states of Central and Eastern Europe. Warsaw, Berlin, Prague, Vienna, Budapest, Belgrade, Bucharest and Sofia, all these famous cities and the populations around them lie in what I might call the Soviet Sphere, and all are subject, in one form or another, not only to Soviet influence, but to very high, and in some cases increasing measure of control from Moscow.\"",
        "correct_answer": "The Soviet Union has expanded its influence throughout Eastern Europe",
        "distractor1": "The Soviet Union has helped the nations of Eastern Europe improve their standard of living",
        "distractor2": "The democratic nations of Western Europe have stopped the expansion of Soviet influence in the world",
        "distractor3": "The Soviet Union will support communist revolutions in Southeast Asia"
    },
    {
        "question": "Prior to the 1980 s, the emphasis of the Five-Year Plans in the Soviet Union was on heavy industry.  One result was the",
        "correct_answer": "scarcity of consumer goods",
        "distractor1": "abundance of manufactured goods",
        "distractor2": "rejection of agricultural planning",
        "distractor3": "decline in military spending"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Soviet Union s reaction to the 1968 revolt in Czechoslovakia was to",
        "correct_answer": "send Soviet troops to occupy Czechoslovakia",
        "distractor1": "permit limited political and economic reforms in Czechoslovakia",
        "distractor2": "withdraw Soviet troops from Eastern Europe",
        "distractor3": "bring the matter to the attention of the United Nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a major reason for the success of Soviet domination in Eastern Europe after World War II?",
        "correct_answer": "the Soviet Union had military forces in Eastern Europe as a result of World War II",
        "distractor1": "Eastern Europeans accepted the doctrine of Pan-Slavism",
        "distractor2": "the democracies of Western Europe needed greater security",
        "distractor3": "Western Europeans feared that Nazism would be rekindled in Eastern Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "The events that took place in Hungary in the 1950 s and in Czechoslovakia in the 1960 s demonstrated the Soviet Union s",
        "correct_answer": "determination to maintain political control over Eastern Europe at that time",
        "distractor1": "support of nationalism among satellite nations",
        "distractor2": "influence on the economies of developing nations",
        "distractor3": "attempts to promote its artistic and literary achievements in Western Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "The expansion of communism into Eastern Europe was a direct result of",
        "correct_answer": "World War II",
        "distractor1": "the Crimean war",
        "distractor2": "the Napoleonic Wars",
        "distractor3": "World War I"
    },
    {
        "question": "United States involvement in the Vietnam War and the Soviet Union s involvement in Afghanistan were motivated mainly by a desire to",
        "correct_answer": "support governments that would remain strong allies",
        "distractor1": "exploit the mineral resources of the regions",
        "distractor2": "stop the expansion of Japan into the Middle East",
        "distractor3": "establish independent nation-states in the regions"
    },
    {
        "question": " Warsaw Pact Tanks Invade Budapest\"",
        "correct_answer": "attempts by the Soviet Union to strengthen communist control",
        "distractor1": "Mikhail Gorbachev s introduction of the policy of Glasnost",
        "distractor2": "Adolf Hitler s efforts to promote national socialism",
        "distractor3": "the Soviet Union s acceptance of capitalism"
    },
    {
        "question": "The invasion of Hungary in 1956 by the Soviet Union and the building of the Berlin Wall in 1961 are examples of",
        "correct_answer": "Truman Doctrine failures",
        "distractor1": "United Nations Security Council resolutions",
        "distractor2": "Marshall Plan effects",
        "distractor3": "Cold War Era conflicts"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Cold War Era, many Asian and African nations followed a policy of nonalignment because they",
        "correct_answer": "wished to receive aid from the Soviet Union and the United States",
        "distractor1": "had the same goals and needs as the Soviet Union",
        "distractor2": "needed the natural resources of Western European nations",
        "distractor3": "were afraid of losing their vote in the United Nations"
    },
    {
        "question": " We believe in nonaggression and noninterference by one country in the affairs of another and the growth of tolerance between them and the capacity for peaceful coexistence.  We, therefore, endeavor to maintain friendly relations with all countries, even though we may disagree with them in their policies. ",
        "correct_answer": "nonalignment",
        "distractor1": "imperialism",
        "distractor2": "mercantilism",
        "distractor3": "isolationism"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is a major reason Cuban and Nicaraguan revolutionary movements were attracted to communism?",
        "correct_answer": "communist groups promised economic reform and better living standards",
        "distractor1": "business owners and the military were supported by communist groups",
        "distractor2": "the goal of communism was to encourage religion",
        "distractor3": "communist leaders promised to reduce Spanish colonialism in the Western Hemisphere"
    },
    {
        "question": "The main reason the United Nations sent troops to Korea in 1950 was to",
        "correct_answer": "prevent North Korea from conquering the people of South Korea",
        "distractor1": "ensure that food reached areas of the Korean Peninsula affected by famine",
        "distractor2": "force the inspection of nuclear weapons plants in North Korea",
        "distractor3": "restore peace between warring factions of Buddhism and Shinto"
    },
    {
        "question": "The conflict between Israel and the Arab nations since 1948 was often considered part of the Cold War primarily because",
        "correct_answer": "the United States supported Israel and the Soviet Union supported several Arab nations",
        "distractor1": "the policy of detente evolved from this conflict",
        "distractor2": "communist governments were established in many Arab nations",
        "distractor3": "the leadership of Joseph Stalin strongly influenced the policies of Saddam Hussein"
    },
    {
        "question": "-Berlin Blockade (1948-1949)",
        "correct_answer": "the level of tension between the United States and the Soviet Union varied",
        "distractor1": "throughout the period, the United States and the Soviet Union were reluctant to solve conflicts",
        "distractor2": "economics played a key role in causing conflict between the United States and the Soviet Union",
        "distractor3": "the United Nations was instrumental in reducing tensions between the United States and the Soviet Union"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement would be consistent with the views of Fidel Castro?",
        "correct_answer": "Progress and justice in Latin America can only be achieved through revolutionary socialism",
        "distractor1": "The spread of communism is the greatest danger facing Latin America",
        "distractor2": "An American military presence is the key to the defense of Latin America",
        "distractor3": "Introducing a free-market system will improve the economies of Latin American nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "From the perspective of the North Vietnamese, the war in Vietnam in the 1960 s was a battle between",
        "correct_answer": "nationalism and imperialism",
        "distractor1": "fascism and liberalism",
        "distractor2": "republicanism and totalitarianism",
        "distractor3": "theocracy and monarchy"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which headline concerning the Soviet Union refers to a Cold War event?",
        "correct_answer": " Warsaw Pact Formed ",
        "distractor1": " Yeltsin Assumes Power ",
        "distractor2": " Trotsky Forms Red Army",
        "distractor3": " Germany Invades USSR "
    },
    {
        "question": "A major development in relations between the Soviet Union and the United States occurred in the late 1980 s when the two nations agreed to",
        "correct_answer": "eliminate a group of nuclear missiles",
        "distractor1": "purchase all their oil from Mexico",
        "distractor2": "withdraw from the United Nations",
        "distractor3": "ban arms sales to developing nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980 s, the Soviet Union experimented with modifications of its command economy by",
        "correct_answer": "introducing some market economy strategies",
        "distractor1": "eliminating central planning",
        "distractor2": "allowing private ownership of major industries",
        "distractor3": "legalizing independent trade unions"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 30 years after World War II, which area was most influenced by the Soviet Union?",
        "correct_answer": "Eastern Europe",
        "distractor1": "Southeast Asia",
        "distractor2": "North Africa",
        "distractor3": "Central America"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the political situation in Eastern Europe during the 1980 s?",
        "correct_answer": "nationalism has often been a strong force for change",
        "distractor1": "communist governments have gained power through democratic elections",
        "distractor2": "ethnic rivalries have been eliminated throughout the region",
        "distractor3": "United States influence has been used to keep communist governments in power"
    },
    {
        "question": "The withdrawal of France from Indochina, the involvement of the Soviet Union in Cuba, and the United States support of the Contras in Nicaragua illustrate that nations",
        "correct_answer": "tend to base foreign policy decisions on what they believe to be their self-interests",
        "distractor1": "consistently discard traditional foreign policy goals after changes in administration",
        "distractor2": "no longer use warfare as a means to resolve international conflict",
        "distractor3": "tend to refer foreign policy conflicts to the United Nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is a valid statement about the Soviet Union from the time of the Bolshevik Revolution through 1991?",
        "correct_answer": "Demand for consumer goods has exceeded production",
        "distractor1": "Education has been limited to the communist party elite",
        "distractor2": "Military expenditures have been low",
        "distractor3": "Industrialization has not occurred"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Soviet Union, Vladimir Lenin s New Economic Policy (NEP) and Mikhail Gorbachev s policy of Perestroika both sought to",
        "correct_answer": "increase production through individual enterprise",
        "distractor1": "increase spending of nuclear weapons",
        "distractor2": "strengthen central planning",
        "distractor3": "reduce the influence of middle-class farmers"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980 s in the Soviet Union, a major element of the economic policy of Perestroika was",
        "correct_answer": "more reliance on local and regional decision making",
        "distractor1": "increased collectivization of farms",
        "distractor2": "the expanded use of national Five-Year plans",
        "distractor3": "an emphasis on the redistribution of wealth"
    },
    {
        "question": "  Blockade of Berlin    Operation of the Berlin Airlift ",
        "correct_answer": "situations that increased tensions between communist and democratic nations in Europe",
        "distractor1": "efforts to prevent military conflict between the superpowers",
        "distractor2": "attempts to weaken the Soviet Union s control of its Eastern European allies",
        "distractor3": "policies of peaceful coexistence and d tente"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Eastern Europe during the 1950 s and 1960 s, the Soviet Union responded to challenges to its control by",
        "correct_answer": "imposing prompt and severe repression",
        "distractor1": "allowing free elections, when necessary",
        "distractor2": "obtaining United Nations assistance",
        "distractor3": "granting independence to its satellite nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the People s Republic of China, which factor best reflects Marxism?",
        "correct_answer": "communal work teams on farms",
        "distractor1": "ownership of small farms by individuals",
        "distractor2": "small family-owned businesses in villages",
        "distractor3": "foreign influence on the economy"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Great Leap Forward in China and the five-year plans in the Soviet Union were attempts to increase",
        "correct_answer": "industrial productivity",
        "distractor1": "private capital investment",
        "distractor2": "religious tolerance",
        "distractor3": "individual ownership of land"
    },
    {
        "question": "In China and the former Soviet Union, the communist governments discouraged organized religion because religions",
        "correct_answer": "compete for the loyalties of the people",
        "distractor1": "support the principles of laissez-faire",
        "distractor2": "favor anarchy over organized government",
        "distractor3": "stress economic rather than political values"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major goal of the Cultural Revolution in China during the 1960 s was to",
        "correct_answer": "eliminate opposition to Mao Zedong",
        "distractor1": "restore China to the glory of the Han Dynasty",
        "distractor2": "reemphasize Confucian traditional values",
        "distractor3": "weaken communist ideas"
    },
    {
        "question": "After World War II, the Chinese Communists were successful in their revolution mainly because the",
        "correct_answer": "communists had the support of the peasants",
        "distractor1": "United States refused to support the Nationalists",
        "distractor2": "communists had more technologically advanced weapons",
        "distractor3": "nationalist had been defeated by Japan"
    },
    {
        "question": "An immediate result of the Cultural Revolution in China was that it",
        "correct_answer": "disrupted China s economic and educational systems",
        "distractor1": "helped to establish democracy in urban centers in China",
        "distractor2": "led to economic cooperation with Japan and South Korea",
        "distractor3": "strengthened political ties with the United States"
    },
    {
        "question": "The main reason the Chinese Communists gained control of mainland China in 1949 was that",
        "correct_answer": "the dynamic leadership of Mao Zedong had the support of the peasant class",
        "distractor1": "they were supported by many warlords and upper class Chinese",
        "distractor2": "the United States had supported the Chinese Communist Party during World War II",
        "distractor3": "they had superior financial resources and were supported by Japan"
    },
    {
        "question": "In China, the Great Leap Forward was an attempt to",
        "correct_answer": "increase agricultural and industrial production",
        "distractor1": "promote democratic reform",
        "distractor2": "end the private ownership of land",
        "distractor3": "strengthen economic ties with Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "Deng Xioaping s economic reforms in China differ from the previous economic policies of Mao Zedong in that Deng s reforms",
        "correct_answer": "include elements of capitalism",
        "distractor1": "discourage private ownership of businesses",
        "distractor2": "promote further collectivization",
        "distractor3": "decrease trade with the United States"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Confucian view of government and the Chinese Communist view of government were similar in that both stressed",
        "correct_answer": "loyalty to the government",
        "distractor1": "the need for filial piety",
        "distractor2": "a civil service system",
        "distractor3": "equality of men and women"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major reason for the success of the Communist revolution in China was that the Communists",
        "correct_answer": "promised land and power to the peasant class",
        "distractor1": "stressed Buddhism in their military training",
        "distractor2": "included important businessmen in their ranks",
        "distractor3": "fought successfully against the United States during World War II"
    },
    {
        "question": "In China, the Great Leap Forward and the Cultural Revolution promoted by Mao Zedong were similar in that both plans",
        "correct_answer": "disrupted industrial development",
        "distractor1": "ended dynastic rule",
        "distractor2": "encouraged capitalism",
        "distractor3": "guaranteed human rights"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980 s, the Chinese government adopted policies designed to",
        "correct_answer": "increase industrial productivity",
        "distractor1": "reestablish Confucian traditions and values",
        "distractor2": "gain colonies throughout East Asia",
        "distractor3": "maintain its isolation from world events"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about the economy of China in the 1980 s is most accurate?",
        "correct_answer": "China increased its industrial capacity and foreign trade",
        "distractor1": "China surpassed the Soviet Union in steel production",
        "distractor2": "China s economy slowed down because of a lack of natural resources",
        "distractor3": "China s economy suffered from overproduction of consumer goods"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sun Yat-sen s  Three Principles of the People  (1911) and the demonstrations in Tiananmen Square (1989) were similar in that they both demanded that the Chinese government",
        "correct_answer": "introduce democratic reforms",
        "distractor1": "achieve global interdependence",
        "distractor2": "restore dynastic rule",
        "distractor3": "end foreign influences in China"
    },
    {
        "question": "The goal of Mao Zedong s policy known as the Great Leap Forward was to",
        "correct_answer": "modernize China s economic system by dividing China into communes",
        "distractor1": "develop foreign export industries in China s coastal urban centers",
        "distractor2": "eliminate state-owned industries in rural China",
        "distractor3": "introduce capitalism to the Chinese economy"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about reforms in China during the 1980 s and 1990 s is most accurate?",
        "correct_answer": "Economic reforms were more successful than political reforms.",
        "distractor1": "Political reforms resulted in the overthrow of communism.",
        "distractor2": "Political reforms increased individual rights.",
        "distractor3": "Economic reforms forced China to return to a policy of isolationism."
    },
    {
        "question": " A wind has been blowing from the West; now it will begin to blow from the East.   \tMao Zedong, 1949",
        "correct_answer": "European power will decline as a new center of power emerges in Asia.",
        "distractor1": "The monsoons will soon shift and bring destruction to the mainland of Asia.",
        "distractor2": "Chinese culture will no longer influence the people of Asia.",
        "distractor3": "The Asian people have much to learn from the Western Europeans."
    },
    {
        "question": " When I go to the office, I put on my shirt and I take off my Caste; when I come home, I take off my shirt and I put on my Caste. ",
        "correct_answer": "the Caste system continues to influence Indian society",
        "distractor1": "the Caste system has been reflected by most Indians",
        "distractor2": "successful urban workers in India belong the same Caste",
        "distractor3": "the Indian government officially supports the Caste system"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor most limited the development of African nationalism?",
        "correct_answer": "political boundaries imposed by Europeans that had little relationship to African tribal boundaries",
        "distractor1": "European support of an educational system based on local traditions and language",
        "distractor2": "the prior experience of Africans with economic self-sufficiency",
        "distractor3": "the European practice of making decisions based on local customs"
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which Kwame Nkurmah, Jomo Kenyatta, and Kenneth Kaunda are similar is that they all",
        "correct_answer": "played a major role in independence movements in Africa",
        "distractor1": "supported the United Nations military action in the Persian Gulf War",
        "distractor2": "rejected financial aid from the World Bank",
        "distractor3": "opposed the Pan-African movement"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the political situation in Africa after World War II?",
        "correct_answer": "increased nationalism led to independence for many African nations",
        "distractor1": "France and West Germany sought to establish colonies in Africa",
        "distractor2": "European nations increased their control over their African colonies",
        "distractor3": "the United Nations opposed the idea of self-determination for African nations"
    },
    {
        "question": " If we are to remain free, if we are to enjoy the full benefits of Africa s enormous wealth, we must unite to plan for the full exploitation of our human and material resources in the interest of all our people ",
        "correct_answer": "Pan-Africanism",
        "distractor1": "colonialism",
        "distractor2": "imperialism",
        "distractor3": "urbanization"
    },
    {
        "question": "After World War II, which action was taken by many African territories?",
        "correct_answer": "demanding independence from their colonial rulers",
        "distractor1": "refusing to join international organizations",
        "distractor2": "rejecting most of the technology offered by western nations",
        "distractor3": "creating a strong, united Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mohandas Gandhi is best known for his",
        "correct_answer": "use of passive resistance to achieve Indian independence",
        "distractor1": "desire to establish and Islamic nations",
        "distractor2": "opposition to Hindus holding political office",
        "distractor3": "encouragement of violence to end British rule"
    },
    {
        "question": "The primary goal of the Indian National Congress (1855-1947) was to",
        "correct_answer": "gain independence from Great Britain",
        "distractor1": "reform the Hindu religion",
        "distractor2": "partition India between Muslims and Hindus",
        "distractor3": "create a socialist economy"
    },
    {
        "question": "The rise of independent states in Asia and Africa after World War II demonstrates the",
        "correct_answer": "decline of European colonial empires",
        "distractor1": "failure of nationalist movements",
        "distractor2": "influence of socialism",
        "distractor3": "success of United Nations peacekeeping forces"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which action best illustrates Mohandas Gandhi s concept of civil disobedience?",
        "correct_answer": "citizens in the United States went to jail for violation segregation laws",
        "distractor1": "a British army outpost was bombed as a protest against the British presence in Northern Ireland",
        "distractor2": "French citizens wrote letters to their government to oppose arms sale to Iraq",
        "distractor3": "supporters of Ferdinand Marcos attempted a coup d etat against the Philippine government"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which has been a characteristic of many Southeast Asian countries since World War II?",
        "correct_answer": "internal struggles for power that lead to political instability",
        "distractor1": "isolation from the influence of the superpowers",
        "distractor2": "democratic governments based on the principles of the French Revolution",
        "distractor3": "fundamentalist Islamic governments supported by Iran"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which event was used by Mohandas Gandhi to bring world attention to the injustices of British colonialism?",
        "correct_answer": "salt march",
        "distractor1": "partition of India",
        "distractor2": "Sepoy Mutiny",
        "distractor3": "formation of the Indian parliament"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since the 1950 s, India has experienced conflict with both Pakistan and China over",
        "correct_answer": "borders and related territorial issues",
        "distractor1": "United Nations peacekeeping efforts in the region",
        "distractor2": "India s increasing trade with Korea",
        "distractor3": "the interpretation of common religious works"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best reflects a belief of Mohandas Gandhi?",
        "correct_answer": "India must achieve independence, but not at the expense of further dividing the Indian people",
        "distractor1": "Muslims and Hindus must be separated if true peace is to come to India",
        "distractor2": "India must adopt the British factory system",
        "distractor3": "The caste system must remain an important cornerstone of Hindu society"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since India s independence in 1947, the government has had the greatest success in",
        "correct_answer": "increasing overall food production",
        "distractor1": "reducing the population",
        "distractor2": "eliminating religious conflict",
        "distractor3": "controlling industrial pollution"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Canal was dug by Egypt s sons and 120,000 of them died while working.  The Suez Canal Company in Paris is an imposter company.  It usurped our concessions  Therefore, I have signed today the following law which has been approved by the Cabinet: Article 1 of the decree reads,  The Universal Company of the Suez Maritime Canal Egyptian Joint-Stock Company   is hereby nationalized. All its assets, rights and obligations are hereby transferred to the Nation. ",
        "correct_answer": "take control of the Suez Canal",
        "distractor1": "end trade with Mediterranean countries",
        "distractor2": "stop building canals",
        "distractor3": "sell the Suez Canal to France"
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason India gained its independence from Great Britain in 1947 was that",
        "correct_answer": "Great Britain did not have the resources to maintain an empire after World War II",
        "distractor1": "Great Britain was defeated in World War II",
        "distractor2": "the Treaty of Versailles required Great Britain to give up its colonies",
        "distractor3": "India had supported the Axis Powers during World War II"
    },
    {
        "question": "One important similarity between Indira Gandhi of India and Benazir Bhutto of Pakistan is that both",
        "correct_answer": "became important national leaders in nations in which women have not traditionally had equal opportunities",
        "distractor1": "are Hindu leaders of Islamic nations",
        "distractor2": "came into power as a result of the breakup of the Soviet Union",
        "distractor3": "became leaders of the Asian bloc of nations at the United Nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between the Sepoys in India, the Boxers in China, and the Mau Mau in Kenya is that these groups",
        "correct_answer": "tried to drive Europeans out of their countries",
        "distractor1": "depended on Western support for their success",
        "distractor2": "adopted Marxist economic and political principles",
        "distractor3": "sought independence through nonviolence"
    },
    {
        "question": "The  homespun movement  and the Salt March promoted by Mohandas Gandhi in India are examples of his policy of",
        "correct_answer": "nonviolent protest",
        "distractor1": "industrialization",
        "distractor2": "isolationism",
        "distractor3": "nonalignment"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best explains why India was partitioned in 1947?",
        "correct_answer": "religious differences led to political division",
        "distractor1": "the British feared a united India",
        "distractor2": "one region wanted to remain under British control",
        "distractor3": "communist supporters wanted a separate state"
    },
    {
        "question": "During India s independence movement, Mohandas Gandhi s boycott of British-made products was effective because the British considered India a major",
        "correct_answer": "market for manufactured goods",
        "distractor1": "shipping center",
        "distractor2": "industrial center",
        "distractor3": "source of mineral resources"
    },
    {
        "question": "The stability of many African nations continues to be threatened by the",
        "correct_answer": "ethnic and tribal loyalties of the people",
        "distractor1": "spread of Animism among the people",
        "distractor2": "use of command economies",
        "distractor3": "establishment of labor unions"
    },
    {
        "question": "The war between India and Pakistan in Kashmir in 1965, the sending of Indian troops to Sir Lanka in 1987, and the assassination of Rajiv Gandhi in 1991 all demonstrate that in South Asia",
        "correct_answer": "b. regional and ethnic rivalries remain strong",
        "distractor1": "a. the Shino religion is a significant force",
        "distractor2": "a. United Nations peacekeeping forces are ineffective",
        "distractor3": "c. nations are vulnerable to a communist takeover"
    },
    {
        "question": "In India today, the continued discrimination based on caste illustrates",
        "correct_answer": "b. the gap between law and tradition",
        "distractor1": "a. a commitment to a capitalist economic system",
        "distractor2": "c. the influence of the Cold War on India",
        "distractor3": "c. the declining role of religion in modern society"
    },
    {
        "question": "India has developed a mixed economy that",
        "correct_answer": "c. blends free enterprise with socialism",
        "distractor1": "a. guarantees government control over the economy",
        "distractor2": "b. provides open competition without government interference",
        "distractor3": "d. relies on the traditional barter system"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980 s, national unity in India was hindered by",
        "correct_answer": "c. conflicts between Sikhs, Hindus, and Muslims",
        "distractor1": "a. a foreign policy of nonalignment",
        "distractor2": "b. continued fear of attack from the Soviet Union",
        "distractor3": "c. political interference from China"
    },
    {
        "question": "With which nation are Pol Pot, the Khmer Rouge, and genocide associated?",
        "correct_answer": "Cambodia (Kampuchea)",
        "distractor1": "Korea",
        "distractor2": "Japan",
        "distractor3": "Myanmar (Burma)"
    },
    {
        "question": "--Rebellion in the Congo during the 1960 s  --Civil war in Nigeria from 1967 to 1970 ",
        "correct_answer": "ethnic rivalries",
        "distractor1": "poor food distribution systems",
        "distractor2": "communist interference",
        "distractor3": "demands for land reform"
    },
    {
        "question": "In some African nations today, ethnic rivalries erupt when",
        "correct_answer": "political differences are motivated by ancient resentments",
        "distractor1": "trading companies hire nonunion workers",
        "distractor2": "scarce funds halt the exploration for mineral resources",
        "distractor3": "groups share a common heritage"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is most accurate about many African societies today?",
        "correct_answer": "new attitudes and values often clash with traditional tribal practices",
        "distractor1": "modern medicines have been ineffective in decreasing infant mortality throughout Africa",
        "distractor2": "agriculture is no longer the most important economic activity in Africa",
        "distractor3": "European influence no longer exists in the former colonial territories"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which situation would best encourage economic development in most African nations today?",
        "correct_answer": "b. attracting investment capital",
        "distractor1": "a. increasing the population growth rate",
        "distractor2": "c. reducing the number of skilled workers",
        "distractor3": "d. depleting their natural resources"
    },
    {
        "question": "The caste system is still practiced in India today primarily because it is",
        "correct_answer": "encouraged by village customs and traditions",
        "distractor1": "enforced by the military",
        "distractor2": "supported by Christian and Muslim teachings",
        "distractor3": "mandated by law"
    },
    {
        "question": "In 1991, Pakistan amended its constitution and made the Koran the basis of all its laws.  Which group was responsible for this action?",
        "correct_answer": "Islamic fundamentalists",
        "distractor1": "Kashmir separatists",
        "distractor2": "Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO)",
        "distractor3": "Buddhist monks"
    },
    {
        "question": "In India, the people have resisted changing their attitudes toward the caste system because",
        "correct_answer": "the Hindu beliefs of karma and dharma reinforce the caste system",
        "distractor1": "national Muslim leaders have supported the caste system",
        "distractor2": "the government is unwilling to end the caste system",
        "distractor3": "continued religious conflict prevents changes in the caste system"
    },
    {
        "question": " Today you won t find a single African head of state who stands on a podium and declares:  I am a Marxist.  Instead all the talk is about currency, private enterprise, and getting hold of capital.    --Tei Mante of Ghana   ",
        "correct_answer": "African nations are more concerned with obtaining investment capital than with discussing political philosophies",
        "distractor1": "African nations remain heavily dependent on China and North Korea for trade, capital, and food",
        "distractor2": "African nations realize they must cooperate",
        "distractor3": "the failure of capitalism in Africa has helped the communists grow in strength"
    },
    {
        "question": "The actions of Jomo Kenyatta, Kwame Nkrumah, Leopold Senghor, and Julius Nyerere were most closely associated with",
        "correct_answer": "a rise in nationalism in several African countries",
        "distractor1": "the end of apartheid in South Africa",
        "distractor2": "a resurgence of colonialism in east Africa",
        "distractor3": "the revival of Islam in northern Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "The wars that took place in the Democratic Republic of the Congo and Nigeria in the 1960 s and in Rwanda and Somalia in the early 1990 s are similar in that these wars were caused in part by disputes",
        "correct_answer": "between ethnic groups",
        "distractor1": "over water sources",
        "distractor2": "over oil and mineral rights",
        "distractor3": "between communist and noncommunist forces"
    },
    {
        "question": " Indian National Congress Refuses To Support British War Effort    Indians Answer Call for the Production of Homespun Cloth  ",
        "correct_answer": "attempts by the native people to gain Indian independence",
        "distractor1": "political reorganization in the British colonia empire",
        "distractor2": "programs to increase India s standard of living",
        "distractor3": "the benefits of economic interdependence between Britain and India"
    },
    {
        "question": "After World War II, the conflict between Hindus and Muslims in India resulted in the",
        "correct_answer": "creation of the Muslim state of Pakistan",
        "distractor1": "near genocide of the Hindu population",
        "distractor2": "forced removal of most Hindus from northern and western India",
        "distractor3": "decision of Mohandas Gandhi to seek election as Prime Minister of India"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is valid about the history of Southeast Asia?",
        "correct_answer": "Religious beliefs have both unified and divided the people of the region.",
        "distractor1": "Industrialization has strengthened the traditional beliefs and lifestyles of the people.",
        "distractor2": "The area has experienced little European contact.",
        "distractor3": "Superpower influence has brought peace and prosperity to the region."
    },
    {
        "question": "Since Nigeria s independence in 1960, its government has frequently shifted between democracy and military dictatorship. This situation suggests that",
        "correct_answer": "democracy is often difficult to establish in nations where little democratic tradition exists",
        "distractor1": "some Nigerians support British colonialism",
        "distractor2": "international problems are more easily solved by military governments",
        "distractor3": "economic prosperity is frequently achieved by military governments"
    },
    {
        "question": "The desire for self-determination in African nations became a powerful force for change immediately after",
        "correct_answer": "World War II",
        "distractor1": "the Boer War",
        "distractor2": "revolutions in Russia and France",
        "distractor3": "the end of the Cold War"
    },
    {
        "question": " Rhodesia Becomes Zimbabwe    Gold Coast Becomes Ghana   ",
        "correct_answer": "reflect traditional cultures",
        "distractor1": "avoid military overthrow",
        "distractor2": "reinforce colonial influences",
        "distractor3": "increase foreign investments"
    },
    {
        "question": "In India today, a major reason the caste system remains strongest in rural areas is that",
        "correct_answer": "tradition remains a strong influence in small villages",
        "distractor1": "economic change occurs rapidly in villages",
        "distractor2": "village laws have resulted in immediate social change",
        "distractor3": "Islam is the dominant religion"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Cold War period, India s foreign policy was committed to",
        "correct_answer": "nonalignment with the world powers",
        "distractor1": "supporting communism in Asia",
        "distractor2": "rejecting democracy in Pakistan",
        "distractor3": "isolationism in international commerce"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since the end of World War II, military rearmament in Japan has been limited by",
        "correct_answer": "specific restrictions in Japan s constitution",
        "distractor1": "Japan s refusal to sign a nuclear nonproliferation treaty",
        "distractor2": "the United Nations refusal to sell weapons to the Japanese",
        "distractor3": "a scarcity of technology and resources in Japan"
    },
    {
        "question": "A sense of national unity has been difficult to maintain in India because of",
        "correct_answer": "the desire of religious groups for greater autonomy",
        "distractor1": "its reliance on foreign aid",
        "distractor2": "the emergence of a mixed economic system",
        "distractor3": "the continuing influence of militarism"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about the problems of Indian independence is a fact rather than an opinion? ",
        "correct_answer": "Muslim leaders wanted their own separate Muslim state.",
        "distractor1": "Stronger government leadership would have prevented bloodshed.",
        "distractor2": "Control of India by Great Britain brought more benefits than difficulties.",
        "distractor3": "India would have been more prosperous if it had remained a colony."
    },
    {
        "question": " East Africa is changing. . . . When my children go . . . with us to visit my parents",
        "correct_answer": "conflict between tradition and modernization",
        "distractor1": "political problems of developing nations",
        "distractor2": "ethnic conflicts",
        "distractor3": "prejudice against elderly family members"
    },
    {
        "question": "The main course of the Arab-Israeli conflicts from 1948 to 1973 was the clash between",
        "correct_answer": "Arab nationalism and Jewish nationalism",
        "distractor1": "Islamic Fundamentalism and Orthodox Judaism",
        "distractor2": "Arab socialism and Israeli capitalism",
        "distractor3": "Israeli technology and Saudi Arabian economic goals"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Iran, the Revolution of 1979 and the rise of Islamic fundamentalism resulted in",
        "correct_answer": "a return to many traditional customs",
        "distractor1": "an increase in woman s rights",
        "distractor2": "the westernization and modernization of the nation",
        "distractor3": "the introduction of a democratic form of government"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who were David Ben-Gurion, Golda Meir, and Menachem Begin?",
        "correct_answer": "leaders of the modern state of Israel",
        "distractor1": "scientist who developed better methods of discovering oil",
        "distractor2": "clergy who supported Islamic Fundamentalism",
        "distractor3": "Egyptian presidents who encouraged peace with Israel"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the late 1980 s and early 1990 s the greatest threat to the stability of the nations of Egypt, Algeria, and Morocco was the",
        "correct_answer": "rise of Islamic Fundamentalism",
        "distractor1": "rising standard of living of their citizens",
        "distractor2": "economic reforms taking place in Eastern Europe",
        "distractor3": "lack of financial aid from the United States"
    },
    {
        "question": "Israel is a country that has",
        "correct_answer": "a democratically elected government",
        "distractor1": "an abundance of oil",
        "distractor2": "Islam as its official religion",
        "distractor3": "friendly ties to Jordan"
    },
    {
        "question": "In 1979, the signing of the Camp David Accords by Egypt and Israel indicated that",
        "correct_answer": "former enemies were able to negotiate",
        "distractor1": "nationalism was no longer a force in middle Eastern politics",
        "distractor2": "the differences between Shi ite and Sunni Moslems had been settled",
        "distractor3": "the Soviet Union dominated Middle Eastern affairs"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980 s, the economic development of Iran and Iraq was disrupted because of",
        "correct_answer": "the war fought between these nations",
        "distractor1": "increased emphasis on agricultural production for export",
        "distractor2": "communist revolutionary movements in these nations",
        "distractor3": "severe drought and famine in the area"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major factor that continues to contribute to terrorist activities in the Middle East is",
        "correct_answer": "the Palestinian effort to establish a homeland",
        "distractor1": "a decrease in crude oil prices on the world market",
        "distractor2": "the presence of United Nations forces in Syria",
        "distractor3": "the worldwide rejection of violence as a means to end conflict"
    },
    {
        "question": "The 1979 Islamic Revolution in Iran was a reaction to the failure of Shah Reza Pahlavi to",
        "correct_answer": "meet the social and political needs of the people",
        "distractor1": "modernize the nation s economy",
        "distractor2": "establish political ties with western nations",
        "distractor3": "supply the military with advanced weapons technology"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980 s the governments of Libya and Iran were similar in that both were linked to",
        "correct_answer": "incidents of international terrorism",
        "distractor1": "efforts to separate religion and politics",
        "distractor2": "advocates of judicial reform",
        "distractor3": "promotion of democratic principles in third world nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "The actions of most Islamic fundamentalists show that they support",
        "correct_answer": "traditional Muslim teachings",
        "distractor1": "a Zionist movement",
        "distractor2": "equal rights for women",
        "distractor3": "a renewed attempt at modernization"
    },
    {
        "question": "In most of the nations of the Middle East, a major long-term economic concern will be the need for",
        "correct_answer": "diversified industry",
        "distractor1": "unskilled labor",
        "distractor2": "imported oil",
        "distractor3": "herds of camels"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which type of government did Ayatollah Khomeini establish as a result of the Iranian Revolution in 1979?",
        "correct_answer": "fundamentalist Islamic state",
        "distractor1": "constitutional monarchy",
        "distractor2": "democratic republic",
        "distractor3": "radical Marxist regime"
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity in the leadership of Kemal Ataturk, Gamal Nasser, and Shah Reza Pahlavi is that all these leaders",
        "correct_answer": "sought to modernize their nations",
        "distractor1": "came to power as a result of democratic elections",
        "distractor2": "encouraged their people to convert to Hinduism",
        "distractor3": "led invasions into Israel"
    },
    {
        "question": "As a peace process continues in the Middle East, a major stumbling block to a settlement of the Arab-Israeli conflict is the question of",
        "correct_answer": "land and civil rights for Palestinian Arabs",
        "distractor1": "ownership and operation of the Suez Canal",
        "distractor2": "control of the Arabian Peninsula",
        "distractor3": "representation of Palestinian Arabs and Israelis"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Middle Eastern leaders Kemal Ataturk, David Ben-Gurion, and Yasir Arafat are best known for their support of",
        "correct_answer": "nationalism",
        "distractor1": "fascism",
        "distractor2": "colonialism",
        "distractor3": "communism"
    },
    {
        "question": " The time has come for you to go  Live where you like, but not among us... ",
        "correct_answer": "nationalism",
        "distractor1": "socialism",
        "distractor2": "absolutism",
        "distractor3": "humanitarianism"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 1990 s, the action by the Israeli Government that has most divided Israeli society has been the decision to",
        "correct_answer": "grant control of part of the West Bank and Gaza Strip to the Palestinians",
        "distractor1": "support the United States led Allied Coalition during the Persian Gulf War",
        "distractor2": "support the Camp David accords",
        "distractor3": "oppose Islamic fundamentalist rule in Iran"
    },
    {
        "question": "The response of the international community to Iraq s invasion of Kuwait in 1990 best illustrates the",
        "correct_answer": "effect of oil on world politics",
        "distractor1": "lack of cooperation between the major world powers",
        "distractor2": "global acceptance of imperialism",
        "distractor3": "ineffectiveness of United Nations peacekeeping forces"
    },
    {
        "question": "The statements below refer to changes in Afghanistan in the 1990 s.     The Taliban controls the government. ",
        "correct_answer": "Islamic fundamentalism",
        "distractor1": "Marxist ideology",
        "distractor2": "liberation theology",
        "distractor3": "constitutional reforms"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which conclusion is best supported by this cartoon?",
        "correct_answer": "Imprisonment of political dissidents rarely ends opposition to the government.",
        "distractor1": "The United Nations supports punishment for acts of civil disobedience.",
        "distractor2": "Better media coverage would prevent the imprisonment of protesters.",
        "distractor3": "Mistreatment of political prisoners often results in their acceptance of government policies."
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Republic of South Africa, the primary goal of the African National Congress (ANC) has been to",
        "correct_answer": "rule as the majority political party",
        "distractor1": "eliminate communist influence",
        "distractor2": "create a united Africa",
        "distractor3": "promote homeland areas for Blacks"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 1980 s, global concern for Blacks in the Republic of South Africa led many nations to",
        "correct_answer": "impose economic sanctions on South Africa",
        "distractor1": "demand that Whites return to their European homelands",
        "distractor2": "sent troops to South Africa",
        "distractor3": "support policies of Apartheid"
    },
    {
        "question": " The Very First Thing You Should Know About South African Stocks and Bonds     Two Leading Financial Institutions Show You Around South Africa s Banking World   ",
        "correct_answer": "a renewed interest in investing in South Africa s economy",
        "distractor1": "a continuation of the international trade sanctions imposed on South Africa in 1985",
        "distractor2": "the hazards associated with overseas economic investment",
        "distractor3": "a belief that the banks and the bond market in South Africa are inferior to those in Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "In which way has the end of apartheid had a positive economic effect on South Africa?",
        "correct_answer": "many foreign companies have resumed trading and investing in South Africa",
        "distractor1": "Black South African managers have increased industrial productivity throughout the nation",
        "distractor2": "the introduction of communism has led to a more equal distribution of income",
        "distractor3": "all profits of South Africa s industries are now reinvested out of the country"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best characterizes the period of apartheid in South Africa?",
        "correct_answer": "many racist ideas of the ruling minority were adopted into laws",
        "distractor1": "the majority of the population had the right to vote",
        "distractor2": "the Boers attempted to conquer Nigeria",
        "distractor3": "French was declared the official language of the nation"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Republic of South Africa, the slogans  Freedom in Our Lifetime  and  New South Africa  changed from promises to reality after",
        "correct_answer": "Nelson Mandela was elected President",
        "distractor1": "Frederik W. de Klerk took over the radical white police force",
        "distractor2": "Untied Nations troops occupied the Transvaal",
        "distractor3": "the majority of white South Africans returned to Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major problem currently facing the Republic of South Africa is the",
        "correct_answer": "struggle for power between different groups within South Africa s black majority",
        "distractor1": "continuation of attacks from neighboring Zimbabwe",
        "distractor2": "move toward the creation of a theocratic state",
        "distractor3": "continued international economic embargo against South Africa"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since the end of apartheid in South Africa, what has been one of the major challenges to the current government?",
        "correct_answer": "resolving regional and ethnic rivalries",
        "distractor1": "establishing diplomatic relations with Europe",
        "distractor2": "guaranteeing religious freedom for all groups",
        "distractor3": "improving transportation throughout the country"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the main idea of this 1991 cartoon?",
        "correct_answer": "The economic differences between East and West Germany have limited the growth of the total German economy.",
        "distractor1": "The unification of Germany has been hurt by poor leadership in the country.",
        "distractor2": "East Germany's strong economy has strengthened a united Germany.",
        "distractor3": "Both East Germany and West Germany have contributed equally to the new economy of a reunified Germany."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the late 1980 s, the Soviet Union experienced internal unrest mainly as a result of",
        "correct_answer": "increased demands of minority ethnic groups",
        "distractor1": "widespread protests against involvement in Afghanistan",
        "distractor2": "a lack of raw materials and natural resources",
        "distractor3": "a failure to use modern technology in the military"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the presidency of Mikhail Gorbachev, which problem faced the Soviet Union?",
        "correct_answer": "ethnic minorities demanded the right of self-determination",
        "distractor1": "agricultural production grew faster than food consumption",
        "distractor2": "the nations of Eastern Europe insisted that the Soviet Union keep troops in Eastern Europe",
        "distractor3": "Western European nations refused to trade with the Soviet Union"
    },
    {
        "question": "Article 50 in accordance with the interests of the people and in order to strengthen and develop the socialist system, citizens of the USSR are guaranteed freedom of speech of the press, and of assembly, meetings, street processions and demonstrations.   Exercise of these political freedoms is ensured by putting public buildings, streets and squares at the disposal of the working people and their organizations, by broad dissemination of information, and by the opportunity to use the press, television, and radio. ",
        "correct_answer": "a constitutional guarantee may be limited by government actions",
        "distractor1": "constitutional rights guarantee a free society",
        "distractor2": "a national constitution always guarantees human rights",
        "distractor3": "a constitutional guarantee must be very specific in order to be effective"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980 s, Mikhail Gorbachev introduced Perestroika in the Soviet Union to",
        "correct_answer": "improve the economy and decentralize decision making",
        "distractor1": "abandon arms treaties with the United States and Western Europe",
        "distractor2": "tighten government controls over the communication media",
        "distractor3": "suppress the growing nationalist movements in Eastern Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "The revolt in Hungary (1956), the demonstrations in Czechoslovakia (1968), and the formation of solidarity in Poland (1980 s) are similar in that they",
        "correct_answer": "represented a challenge to communist leadership",
        "distractor1": "were movements in restore the power of the aristocracy",
        "distractor2": "were tolerated by the communist leaders, who accepted the need for change",
        "distractor3": "represented attempts to rid these countries of western ideas and influence"
    },
    {
        "question": "One result of the collapse of the Soviet Union has been that",
        "correct_answer": "ethnic violence has broken out in some regions",
        "distractor1": "some former republics have reorganized the Warsaw Pact",
        "distractor2": "an era of peace and stability has emerged in most of the former republics",
        "distractor3": "the republics have made an east transition to a market economy"
    },
    {
        "question": " Polish Communist Party Fails in Election Bid    Romanians Depose Communist Dictator   ",
        "correct_answer": "demands for democracy ended many totalitarian governments in Eastern Europe",
        "distractor1": "military buildups are continuing in Eastern Europe",
        "distractor2": "planned economies in Eastern Europe have become increasingly successful",
        "distractor3": "the Soviet Union stopped independence efforts in Eastern Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": " The Soviet Union Splits into 15 Republics    Yugoslavia Experiences Internal Conflict  ",
        "correct_answer": "the forces of nationalism can either divide of unite a nation",
        "distractor1": "communism remains an important force in Europe",
        "distractor2": "many Western European nations are experiencing civil war",
        "distractor3": "international sanctions strengthen a nation s ability to govern"
    },
    {
        "question": "The initial reaction of the Russian government to the fighting that broke out in Chechnya in the 1990 s demonstrated that Russia",
        "correct_answer": "is unwilling to grant independence to dissenting ethnic groups",
        "distractor1": "has little control over its arsenal of nuclear weapons",
        "distractor2": "will defend its remaining republics against foreign invasion",
        "distractor3": "favors reestablishing communism"
    },
    {
        "question": "In many Latin American nations, which group has most resisted social and economic changes since the end of World War II?",
        "correct_answer": "the military",
        "distractor1": "poor farmers",
        "distractor2": "union leaders",
        "distractor3": "the middle class"
    },
    {
        "question": "The main purpose of the Organization of American States (OAS) is to",
        "correct_answer": "provide a way to resolve regional problems peacefully",
        "distractor1": "integrate the economies of Latin American nations",
        "distractor2": "encourage United States military involvement in the region",
        "distractor3": "destroy the power of Colombian drug lords"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the last ten years, what has occurred in many of the nations of Latin America?",
        "correct_answer": "an increase in the number of popularly elected leaders",
        "distractor1": "successful communist revolutions",
        "distractor2": "a growing dependence on Cuba for economic support",
        "distractor3": "a return to their former colonial status"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which group has been a major force in calling for the protection of human rights in Central America during the 1980 s and 1990 s?",
        "correct_answer": "liberation theology clergy",
        "distractor1": "Caudillos",
        "distractor2": "military generals",
        "distractor3": "Landowners"
    },
    {
        "question": "Brazil s establishment of an equal partnership with foreign investors and Venezuela s control of its highly profitable oil industry are examples of",
        "correct_answer": "economic nationalism",
        "distractor1": "Neocolonialism",
        "distractor2": "new imperialism",
        "distractor3": "Fascism"
    },
    {
        "question": "At the present time, which is a major economic problem for many Latin American governments?",
        "correct_answer": "inability to pay foreign debts",
        "distractor1": "increased settlement in rural areas",
        "distractor2": "low rates of inflation",
        "distractor3": "lack of a chief executive"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which major economic problem has been faced by many Latin American nations throughout their histories?",
        "correct_answer": "lack of capital for industrial development",
        "distractor1": "declining birthrate",
        "distractor2": "widespread acceptance of Marxist economic policies",
        "distractor3": "lack of labor for factories"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 20th century, a major course of political problems in Latin American has been",
        "correct_answer": "widespread poverty",
        "distractor1": "a decrease in population",
        "distractor2": "the declining importance of international trade",
        "distractor3": "increasing social mobility"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which has been an important factor that has discouraged investment in the economic developments of many Latin American nations?",
        "correct_answer": "political instability",
        "distractor1": "lack of natural resources",
        "distractor2": "history of colonial dependence",
        "distractor3": "declining birthrate"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the Roman Catholic Church in most Latin American countries in the 1980 s?",
        "correct_answer": "the church has become active in social and human rights issues",
        "distractor1": "the activities of the church are controlled by the national governments",
        "distractor2": "the church has confined its activities to religious issues",
        "distractor3": "most people see the church as having little influence in daily life"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which type of government has resulted from the changing political trends in much of Latin America during the 1990 s?",
        "correct_answer": "democracy",
        "distractor1": "monarchy",
        "distractor2": "military juntas",
        "distractor3": "fascism"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major problem facing many Central American nations is that their nation s wealth is",
        "correct_answer": "controlled by a small group of landed elite",
        "distractor1": "generally invested in consumer industries",
        "distractor2": "distributed throughout the large middle class",
        "distractor3": "held mainly by government agencies"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 20th century, an economic weakness of many Central American nations has been",
        "correct_answer": "an overdependence on one or two cash crops for export",
        "distractor1": "a reliance on monsoons for water to irrigate crops",
        "distractor2": "chronic labor shortages caused by slow population growth",
        "distractor3": "excessive investment in foreign manufacturing industries"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since World War II, what action have many Latin American nations taken to improve their economies?",
        "correct_answer": "encouraging industrial development",
        "distractor1": "reinforcing traditional farming methods",
        "distractor2": "encouraging citizens to emigrate to other nations",
        "distractor3": "adopting protectionist policies"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Latin America during the 1960 s and 1970 s, which group became increasingly active in promoting human rights?",
        "correct_answer": "Roman Catholic clergy",
        "distractor1": "wealthy landholders",
        "distractor2": "successful industrialists",
        "distractor3": "military leaders"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which political trend exists in present-day Latin America?",
        "correct_answer": "Democracy is replacing dictatorship.",
        "distractor1": "Most countries are becoming military juntas.",
        "distractor2": "Communism is spreading throughout the region.",
        "distractor3": "Religious leaders are making government policy."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which conclusion about the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) can be drawn from this 1994 cartoon?",
        "correct_answer": "NATO did not react quickly enough to the crisis in Bosnia.",
        "distractor1": "Bosnia and NATO continue to disagree about the causes of the civil war.",
        "distractor2": "NATO's actions have allowed communism to take advantage of the destruction of Bosnia.",
        "distractor3": "The United States will probably withdraw from NATO as a result of the Bosnian crisis."
    },
    {
        "question": " Russia Takes Soviet Union Seat ",
        "correct_answer": "responds to changing political conditions",
        "distractor1": "is usually dominated by industrialized countries",
        "distractor2": "generally relies on the use of force to enforce its decisions",
        "distractor3": "permits developing nations to block the proposals of Westerns nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Recent events in the former nations of Czechoslovakia and Yugoslavia reflect a nationalist trend of",
        "correct_answer": "dividing nations along ethnic lines",
        "distractor1": "encouraging multiethnic cooperation",
        "distractor2": "uniting nations with similar interests",
        "distractor3": "supporting the development of a command economy"
    },
    {
        "question": "Disputes over India s control of Kashmir, Jammu, and Punjab are examples of the continuing problem of",
        "correct_answer": "territorial claims based on religion",
        "distractor1": "Chinese claims to this region",
        "distractor2": "terrorist actions by Serbian refugees",
        "distractor3": "the policy of nonalignment"
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason North Korea has been the focus of worldwide attention in the mid-1990 s is because of its",
        "correct_answer": "nuclear weapons development programs",
        "distractor1": "commitment to increasing political freedoms",
        "distractor2": "development of a strong and expanding economy",
        "distractor3": "efforts to revive communism in Eastern Europe"
    },
    {
        "question": "The major goal of many minority groups, such as the Kurds, Tamils, and Sikhs, is to",
        "correct_answer": "obtain self-rule and economic control of a homeland",
        "distractor1": "establish a multicultural state",
        "distractor2": "install Christianity as the state religion",
        "distractor3": "acquire economic aid from the World Bank"
    },
    {
        "question": "Under the leadership of Fidel Castro, Cuba has become an example of",
        "correct_answer": "a communist government struggling to maintain power despite economic problems",
        "distractor1": "the success of democracy in improving conditions in a developing nation",
        "distractor2": "a nation in which the efforts of the United Nations has improved human rights",
        "distractor3": "the successful reform of agriculture from single-crop to multicrop production"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since the end of the Cold War, Cuba has experienced",
        "correct_answer": "the loss of a major source of its foreign financial support",
        "distractor1": "increased economic growth from expanded trade",
        "distractor2": "expanded political influence in Latin American affairs",
        "distractor3": "greater independence from Communist China"
    },
    {
        "question": "In France, a person drinks coffee imported from Brazil, works at a computer made in Japan, and uses gasoline from Saudi Arabia in a German automobile.  This situation illustrates the concept of",
        "correct_answer": "interdependence",
        "distractor1": "empathy",
        "distractor2": "scarcity",
        "distractor3": "world citizenship"
    },
    {
        "question": "Japan sells cars to the United States, the United States exports high technology to Saudi Arabia, and Saudi Arabia exports oil to Japan.  Which is a valid conclusion that can be drawn from this statement?",
        "correct_answer": "the nations of the world are economically interdependent",
        "distractor1": "Saudi Arabia controls most of the world's natural resources",
        "distractor2": "The United States is the world's leading exporter",
        "distractor3": "most nations of the world specialize in one export"
    },
    {
        "question": "Global problems of uneven economic development, environmental pollution, and hunger reflect the need for",
        "correct_answer": "increased international cooperation",
        "distractor1": "a return to policies of economic nationalism",
        "distractor2": "increased military spending by all nations",
        "distractor3": "a reduction in foreign aid provided by industrialized nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Middle East is a global importance today because it",
        "correct_answer": "provides much of the petroleum used by industrial nations",
        "distractor1": "has become a model of economic and political equality",
        "distractor2": "allows major European powers to retain their spheres of influence",
        "distractor3": "remains a primary source of uranium"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major purpose of the Organization of African Unity (OAU), the Organization of American States (OAS), and the European Union (EU) is to",
        "correct_answer": "encourage political and economic cooperation between member nations",
        "distractor1": "end colonialism in member nations",
        "distractor2": "control overpopulation in member nations",
        "distractor3": "provide military assistance to member nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the past decade, Japanese automobile manufacturers have sought to improve Japanese-American trade relations by",
        "correct_answer": "building an increasing number of Japanese automobiles in the United States",
        "distractor1": "drastically lowering the price of Japanese automobiles for American consumers",
        "distractor2": "allowing an unlimited number of American automobiles to be sold in Japan",
        "distractor3": "importing most spare parts from Mexico"
    },
    {
        "question": "In recent years, a major success of the European Union (EU) has been the",
        "correct_answer": "elimination of trade barriers",
        "distractor1": "creation of a single military force",
        "distractor2": "rejection of national sovereignty",
        "distractor3": "adoption of a single language"
    },
    {
        "question": "The major reason the Mexican Government strongly supported the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) was that this agreement would",
        "correct_answer": "promote investment and economic growth in Mexico",
        "distractor1": "raise tariffs on United States products entering Mexico",
        "distractor2": "reduce Mexico s economic dependence on Europe",
        "distractor3": "stimulate trade between Asia and Latin America"
    },
    {
        "question": "Within the past decade, the decision of the United States Government to grant China  most favored nation  status was important to China because this decision",
        "correct_answer": "increased China s ability to trade with the United States",
        "distractor1": "allowed China to join the Southeast Treaty Organization (SEATO)",
        "distractor2": "helped protect China from a possible Japanese invasion",
        "distractor3": "eliminated Russian influence in East Asia"
    },
    {
        "question": "Modern Japan must trade to maintain its industry and living standard because Japan has",
        "correct_answer": "few mineral resources",
        "distractor1": "a limited amount of investment capital",
        "distractor2": "little access to the sea",
        "distractor3": "a lack of communication systems"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which action will help slow the trend indicated by the graph?",
        "correct_answer": "using alternative energy sources",
        "distractor1": "expanding Green Revolution technology",
        "distractor2": "increasing industrialization in developing nations",
        "distractor3": "lowering worldwide oil prices"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which conclusion can be drawn from the information in the chart?",
        "correct_answer": "The nations with relatively low birthrates have relatively high per capita incomes.",
        "distractor1": "Developing countries are instituting programs to limit the growth of their populations.",
        "distractor2": "Infant mortality is a greater problem in Africa than in Asia.",
        "distractor3": "The national birthrate is determined by many different factors."
    },
    {
        "question": "In many Latin American nations, reliance on the production of a single cash crop has led to",
        "correct_answer": "economic dependence on other nations",
        "distractor1": "rapid repayment of foreign loans",
        "distractor2": "a high per capita Gross National Product",
        "distractor3": "development of a strong industrial economy"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which fact about China has been the cause of the other three?",
        "correct_answer": "China s population exceeds one billion",
        "distractor1": "the economy of China has trouble providing for all the needs of the people",
        "distractor2": "the Chinese government has set limits on the number of children families may have",
        "distractor3": "Chinese cities have a severe shortage of housing"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since the collapse of the Soviet Union in the early 1990 s, Russia has attempted to build an economic system based on",
        "correct_answer": "free-market a system",
        "distractor1": "a return to feudalism",
        "distractor2": "the ideas of Marx and Lenin",
        "distractor3": "the writings of Mao Zedong"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which conclusion is valid concerning the food shortages some nations of Africa and Asia during the 1970 s and 1980 s?",
        "correct_answer": "too few people in Africa and Asia are involved in food production",
        "distractor1": "misuse of the land has destroyed many rich food-producing regions",
        "distractor2": "acid rain has been the major cause of crop failures",
        "distractor3": "European nations stopped shipping food to these regions"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is best supported by the data in the graph?",
        "correct_answer": "Belize and Costa Rica are meeting the water needs of their urban population.",
        "distractor1": "The urban areas of Honduras and Panama require the largest supply of water in Central America.",
        "distractor2": "Urban water supplies are declining in many Central American countries.",
        "distractor3": "Most Central American countries experienced a decrease in urban population between 1980 and 1988."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Mexico and India, the Green Revolution has been successful because it has",
        "correct_answer": "increased agricultural productivity",
        "distractor1": "promoted democratic reform",
        "distractor2": "introduced western culture and values",
        "distractor3": "established economic equality among the people"
    },
    {
        "question": "The major goal of the Green Revolution has been to",
        "correct_answer": "increase agricultural output",
        "distractor1": "decrease the use of modern farm machinery",
        "distractor2": "decrease population growth",
        "distractor3": "increase the number of traditional farms"
    },
    {
        "question": "The term ?Green Revolution? is used to describe the",
        "correct_answer": "development of new types of grains and new methods of growing them",
        "distractor1": "tensions between developing and developed nations",
        "distractor2": "heavy reliance on manual labor in agriculture",
        "distractor3": "protests against environmental destruction caused by industry"
    },
    {
        "question": "The main goal of the Green Revolution was to",
        "correct_answer": "solve chronic food shortages through the use of technology",
        "distractor1": "prevent further destruction of the world?s rain forests",
        "distractor2": "expand the economies of developing nations with foreign investment",
        "distractor3": "insure that foreign aid was received by people with the greatest need"
    },
    {
        "question": "A study of the accident at the Chernobyl nuclear power plant in the Soviet Union and of severe air pollution in Mexico would lead to the conclusion that",
        "correct_answer": "technology can cause problems throughout the world",
        "distractor1": "international trade is more profitable than domestic commerce",
        "distractor2": "modern science cannot solve most political problems",
        "distractor3": "agricultural nations have caused major world environmental problems"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major environmental problem affecting Latin America, Sub-Saharan Africa, and Southeast Asia has been",
        "correct_answer": "Deforestation",
        "distractor1": "air pollution",
        "distractor2": "disposal of nuclear waste",
        "distractor3": "acid rain"
    },
    {
        "question": "Many scientist believe that the ?greenhouse effect? is the result of",
        "correct_answer": "using large amounts of gasoline, oil, and coal in developed nations",
        "distractor1": "overgrazing on land in developing nations",
        "distractor2": "testing nuclear weapons in violation of the Nuclear Test Ban Treaty",
        "distractor3": "using natural fertilizers to increase crop production"
    },
    {
        "question": "A major factor contributing to the destruction of the Amazon rain forests is the",
        "correct_answer": "need for more farmland",
        "distractor1": "movement of people from rural to urban areas",
        "distractor2": "attempt of native peoples to end illegal drug traffic",
        "distractor3": "spread of Christianity"
    },
    {
        "question": "The amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere has increased in recent years.  Environmentalists suggest this change is a direct result of the",
        "correct_answer": "overcutting of forests and the increased use of fossil fuels",
        "distractor1": "improper storage of solid and nuclear waste",
        "distractor2": "dumping of inorganic material into lakes and rivers",
        "distractor3": "use of herbicides and toxic substances such as asbestos and DDT"
    },
    {
        "question": "In developing countries, the use of wood, charcoal, and dung as major sources of energy has created an increase in",
        "correct_answer": "deforestation and other environmental problems",
        "distractor1": "economic dependence on industrialized nations",
        "distractor2": "sales an profits for international oil corporations",
        "distractor3": "nuclear waste products"
    },
    {
        "question": "A negative impact of the use of modern technology is that",
        "correct_answer": "levels of air and water pollution often increase",
        "distractor1": "economic opportunities are frequently limited",
        "distractor2": "contacts with other cultures decrease",
        "distractor3": "international trade is limited"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Latin America, the deforestation of the Amazon rain forest has led to",
        "correct_answer": "environmental dangers",
        "distractor1": "the maintenance of a traditional way of life",
        "distractor2": "the discovery of new medicines",
        "distractor3": "overpopulation in rural regions"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 1980?s, the governments of both Brazil and Malaysia supported the cutting of timber in their rain forests as a means of",
        "correct_answer": "achieving economic prosperity",
        "distractor1": "increasing the national debt",
        "distractor2": "controlling rebellions of indigenous peoples",
        "distractor3": "preventing exploitation by imperialist nations"
    },
    {
        "question": " ?What harms the victim most is not the cruelty of the oppressor, but the silence of the bystander.?",
        "correct_answer": "nations of the world must always condemn human rights violations whenever they occur",
        "distractor1": "totalitarian governments generally support civil liberties",
        "distractor2": "ethnic cleansing is not an issue to be addressed by the United Nations",
        "distractor3": "demonstrations against human rights violations are of limited value"
    },
    {
        "question": "?United States Adopts Economic Sanctions Against South Africa?  ?Chinese Dissidents Imprisoned After Student Protest? ",
        "correct_answer": "human rights violation",
        "distractor1": "imperialist expansion",
        "distractor2": "peasant revolts",
        "distractor3": "isolationist policies"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Tiananmen Square massacre in China was a reaction to",
        "correct_answer": "student demands for greater individual rights and freedom of expression",
        "distractor1": "Deng Xiaoping?s plan to revive the Cultural Revolution",
        "distractor2": "China?s decision to seek Western investors",
        "distractor3": "Great Britain?s decision to return Hong Kong to China"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes a result of the student demonstrations in Beijing?s Tiananmen Square in 1989?",
        "correct_answer": "the government further restricted freedom of expression in China",
        "distractor1": "prodemocracy protestors were successful in achieving their goals",
        "distractor2": "a state-controlled education program was begun",
        "distractor3": "collectivization programs were started in China"
    },
    {
        "question": "A common problem facing most Latin American and Eastern European nations today is that these nations",
        "correct_answer": "are struggling with a transition to democracy after experiencing years of dictatorial rule",
        "distractor1": "have little arable land and few mineral resources with which to improve their economies",
        "distractor2": "have chosen not to belong to international organizations",
        "distractor3": "are experiencing major problems with the flood of illegal immigrants entering their nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Today, human rights violations most often occur in nations in which",
        "correct_answer": "leaders have absolute control",
        "distractor1": "freedom of the press exists",
        "distractor2": "government is limited by law",
        "distractor3": "government has a multiparty system"
    },
    {
        "question": "An analysis of the Chinese student demonstrations in Tiananmen Square in 1989 would show that",
        "correct_answer": "totalitarian governments frequently survive by the use of force",
        "distractor1": "communist governments continue to have little control over the actions of their citizens",
        "distractor2": "peaceful demonstrations often succeed in achieving democratic reforms",
        "distractor3": "negative global reaction sometimes leads to economic decline"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a characteristic of Western European nations that most enabled them to establish colonies in Africa and Asia?:",
        "correct_answer": "advanced technology.",
        "distractor1": "rigid social class structures.",
        "distractor2": "frequent political revolutions.",
        "distractor3": "self-sufficienty in natural resources."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the folowing was a major result of European imperialism in sub-Saharan Africa during the late 19c and early 20c?:",
        "correct_answer": "decline of traditional African cultures.",
        "distractor1": "adoption of Islam as the dominant African religion.",
        "distractor2": "strengthening of tribal organization.",
        "distractor3": "beginning of slavery."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a major effect of European rule in Africa?:",
        "correct_answer": "improved transportation and communication systems.",
        "distractor1": "decreased dependence of African nations on imports.",
        "distractor2": "development of subsistence agriculture.",
        "distractor3": "increased use of barter as a basis of their economies."
    },
    {
        "question": "European imperialism promoted the development of nationalism in Asian and African countries by?:",
        "correct_answer": "unintentionally uniting people to oppose foreign domination.",
        "distractor1": "promoting free trade associations among the colonies.",
        "distractor2": "establishing Christianity as the common religion throughout the continent.",
        "distractor3": "discouraging patriotic feelings toward the mother country."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is an accurate statement about the partitioning of Africa by European imperialist nations during the 1800s?:",
        "correct_answer": "the cultural and ethnic diversity of the African people was disregarded.",
        "distractor1": "new nations were based on old tribal boundaries.",
        "distractor2": "the continent was divided equally among the colonial powers.",
        "distractor3": "African unity was encouraged."
    },
    {
        "question": "European imperialism in Africa in the late 19c and early 20c resulted from all of the following motives EXCEPT the?:",
        "correct_answer": "need for slaves.",
        "distractor1": "demand for raw materials.",
        "distractor2": "desire to spread Christianity.",
        "distractor3": "desire for large empires."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement BEST describes the impact of European rule on traditional African cultures?:",
        "correct_answer": "it reduced the influence of local African rulers.",
        "distractor1": "it encouraged unity among the peoples of Africa.",
        "distractor2": "it caused exports from africa to decline.",
        "distractor3": "it strengthened family ties in the villages."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Berlin Conference of 1884-1885 showed that European nations?:",
        "correct_answer": "were ready to carve up Africa among themselves.",
        "distractor1": "wanted to end the African slave trade.",
        "distractor2": "wanted to convert Africans to Christianity.",
        "distractor3": "were ready to begin exploring the interior of Africa."
    },
    {
        "question": "In the early 1800s, which two groups were competing for control of South Africa?:",
        "correct_answer": "Boers and Zulus.",
        "distractor1": "Muslims and Hausa.",
        "distractor2": "British and Germans.",
        "distractor3": "Belgians and French."
    },
    {
        "question": "Indirect rule as practiced by the British had all of the following characteristics EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "local rulers were replaced by British officials.",
        "distractor1": "British authorities made the law for the colony.",
        "distractor2": "local rulers kept some of their traditional authority.",
        "distractor3": "British authorities and considerable authority."
    },
    {
        "question": "About half of the Congo Free State died between 1885 and 1908 as a result of?:",
        "correct_answer": "brutal treatment by European companies.",
        "distractor1": "the Boer War.",
        "distractor2": "a yellow fever epidemic.",
        "distractor3": "Jihadists."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why did westerners in the early 1800s call Africa the \"Dark Continent?:\"",
        "correct_answer": "they knew very little about the land.",
        "distractor1": "they got a lot of coal from Africa.",
        "distractor2": "the sun rarely shone on Africa.",
        "distractor3": "the overgrowth in the rain forests made it dark."
    },
    {
        "question": "Discovery of a treatment for which disease allowed Europeans to venture into the African interior?:",
        "correct_answer": "malaria.",
        "distractor1": "smallpox.",
        "distractor2": "tuberculosis.",
        "distractor3": "scarlet fever."
    },
    {
        "question": "The \"Scramble for Africa\" led to the European colonication of the whole African continent EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "Liberia and Ethiopia.",
        "distractor1": "Egypt and South Africa.",
        "distractor2": "Nigeria and Morocco.",
        "distractor3": "Kenya and the Congo."
    },
    {
        "question": "Cecil Rhodes made his African fortune by?:",
        "correct_answer": "mining gold and diamonds.",
        "distractor1": "planting bananas, melons, and other exotic fruits.",
        "distractor2": "building steamships that sailed up and down the Nile River.",
        "distractor3": "planting and processing rubber."
    },
    {
        "question": "Colonial officials often discouraged native peoples from?:",
        "correct_answer": "practicing traditional customs and rituals.",
        "distractor1": "learning European languages.",
        "distractor2": "converting to Christianity.",
        "distractor3": "adopting Western lifestyles."
    },
    {
        "question": "After many Kenyans died fighting the Germans in World War I, the British?:",
        "correct_answer": "allowed European settlers to seize the land of the native Kenyans.",
        "distractor1": "granted Kenya full independence.",
        "distractor2": "asked Jomo Kenyatta to help further Kenyan nationalism.",
        "distractor3": "let Harry Thuku govern Kenya for them."
    },
    {
        "question": "Britain wanted to establish a colony in southern Africa to?:",
        "correct_answer": "protest the route to India.",
        "distractor1": "train missionaries for work in Africa.",
        "distractor2": "provide a homeland for former slaves.",
        "distractor3": "control the Dutch missionaries there."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which nation adopted and then largely abandoned the policy of assimilation in Africa?:",
        "correct_answer": "France.",
        "distractor1": "Britain.",
        "distractor2": "the United States.",
        "distractor3": "Belgium."
    },
    {
        "question": "Until the late 1800s, Europeans were discouraged from conquering Africa by all of the following EXCPEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "Social Darwinism.",
        "distractor1": "malaria.",
        "distractor2": "impassable rivers.",
        "distractor3": "powerful African armies."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following was NOT a goal of independent African explorers?:",
        "correct_answer": "stirring up political unrest so that their imperial sponsors could move in and take advantage of the resulting chaos.",
        "distractor1": "finding the source of Africa\\'s mighty rivers.",
        "distractor2": "assessing the continent\\'s possible mineral wealth.",
        "distractor3": "scouting out locations for possible Christian missions."
    },
    {
        "question": "This African kingdom conquered Egypt in the 8c BCE?:",
        "correct_answer": "Kush.",
        "distractor1": "Axum.",
        "distractor2": "Ghana.",
        "distractor3": "Zimbabwe."
    },
    {
        "question": "The mixing of Bantu and Arabic cultures resulted in the?:",
        "correct_answer": "development of Swahili.",
        "distractor1": "Bantu migrations.",
        "distractor2": "spread of iron smelting.",
        "distractor3": "rise of Great Zimbabwe."
    },
    {
        "question": "East African city-states grew wealthy primarily through?:",
        "correct_answer": "trade.",
        "distractor1": "plantation agriculture.",
        "distractor2": "manufacturing.",
        "distractor3": "military conquests."
    },
    {
        "question": "The kingdom of Ethiopia is distinctive in Africa for its?:",
        "correct_answer": "conversion to Coptic Christianity.",
        "distractor1": "early abolition of the slave trade.",
        "distractor2": "weak central government.",
        "distractor3": "very early conversion to Islam."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the main reason the city-states of East Africa became multicultural?:",
        "correct_answer": "Arab and Persian traders settled in the city-states.",
        "distractor1": "the gold trade made them rich.",
        "distractor2": "African traders sailed to the Arabian Peninsula.",
        "distractor3": "iron from the city-states became widely used in the Arabian Peninsula and South Asia."
    },
    {
        "question": "Great Zimbabwe was the?:",
        "correct_answer": "capital of a vast empire in south Africa.",
        "distractor1": "military leader who unified the Khoisan peoples.",
        "distractor2": "great temple in Timbuktu.",
        "distractor3": "military and and economic alliance of the city-states of East Africa."
    },
    {
        "question": "Axum prospered partly because it had a port on the?:",
        "correct_answer": "Red Sea.",
        "distractor1": "Atlantic Ocean.",
        "distractor2": "Mediterranean Sea.",
        "distractor3": "Zambezi River."
    },
    {
        "question": "People of the East African coastal towns who practiced various animistic religions were eventually converted to?:",
        "correct_answer": "Islam.",
        "distractor1": "Hinduism.",
        "distractor2": "Christianity.",
        "distractor3": "Judaism."
    },
    {
        "question": "A major factor in the development of 20c nationalist movements throughout Africa was a common?:",
        "correct_answer": "goal to end European rule in Africa.",
        "distractor1": "language throughout most of Africa.",
        "distractor2": "ethnic bond among the people of Sub-Saharan Africa.",
        "distractor3": "religion throughout most of Africa."
    },
    {
        "question": "The boundaries of modern African nations do not usually follow tribal boundaries mainly because?:",
        "correct_answer": "modern national boundaries tend to follow former colonial boundaries.",
        "distractor1": "African nations are trying to decrease tribal influence.",
        "distractor2": "most tribes are unwilling to cooperate with the new national governments.",
        "distractor3": "tribes have lost their importance in the lives of modern Africans."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1950s and 1960s, the history of most African countries was characterized by?:",
        "correct_answer": "the achievement of political independence.",
        "distractor1": "colonization by imperialist nations.",
        "distractor2": "a sharp decrease in the birth rate.",
        "distractor3": "the development of economic self-sufficiency."
    },
    {
        "question": "The term \"Pan-Arabism\" can best be defined as a movement whose purpose is to?:",
        "correct_answer": "promote African unity.",
        "distractor1": "encourage European investment in Africa.",
        "distractor2": "support cultural diversity.",
        "distractor3": "advocate a return to colonial conditions."
    },
    {
        "question": "The economic systems of most newly independent African nations have been characterized by?:",
        "correct_answer": "a mixture of government and private ownership.",
        "distractor1": "private ownership with a minimum of government involvement.",
        "distractor2": "a Communist model of government ownership of agriculture.",
        "distractor3": "self-sufficiency with few exports or imports."
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which Kwame Nkrumah, Jomo Kenyatta, and Patrice Lumumba are similar is that that all?:",
        "correct_answer": "played a major role in independence movements in Africa.",
        "distractor1": "supported the United States military action in the Persian Gulf War.",
        "distractor2": "rejected financial aid from the World Bank.",
        "distractor3": "opposed the Pan-African movement."
    },
    {
        "question": "\"We are Nigerians and we wish to remain so.  We have our own customs and our own traditions.  Our immediate goal should be to develop the wealth of our country and improve our standard of living.\" This quotation is an expression of?:",
        "correct_answer": "nationalism.",
        "distractor1": "mercantilism.",
        "distractor2": "totalitarianism.",
        "distractor3": "imperialism."
    },
    {
        "question": "Many modern African nations depend on foreign aid because these nations?:",
        "correct_answer": "need help in developing their economies.",
        "distractor1": "have many different ethnic groups.",
        "distractor2": "want to have power in the United Nations.",
        "distractor3": "want to establish democratic governments."
    },
    {
        "question": "What was one factor that contributed to the downfall of apartheid in the Republic of South Africa?:",
        "correct_answer": "many foreign countries boycotted South African products.",
        "distractor1": "the African National Congress was outlawed.",
        "distractor2": "Afrikaaners demanded that only they should have ruling power.",
        "distractor3": "President de Klerk and Desmond Tutu were imprisoned."
    },
    {
        "question": "Tribalism in modern African nations has frequently resulted in political?:",
        "correct_answer": "disunity.",
        "distractor1": "equality.",
        "distractor2": "interdependence.",
        "distractor3": "harmony."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement BEST describes the significance of awarding the 1984 Nobel Peace Prize to Bishop Desmund Tutu of South Africa?:",
        "correct_answer": "non-violence was recognized as a way to bring about change in South Africa.",
        "distractor1": "the world community was endorsing the apartheid practices of the old white government of South Africa.",
        "distractor2": "the European policy of remaining neutral in regard to human rights issues was reaffirmed.",
        "distractor3": "the separation of church and state was promoted as a universal concept."
    },
    {
        "question": "In most of the nations of Africa, an important economic problem has been?:",
        "correct_answer": "a lack of capital for investment.",
        "distractor1": "a shortage of unskilled labor.",
        "distractor2": "an increase in agricultural surpluses.",
        "distractor3": "excessive industrialization."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is most accurate about many African societies today?:",
        "correct_answer": "new attitudes and values often clash with traditional tribal practices.",
        "distractor1": "modern medicines have been ineffective in decreasing infant mortality throughout Africa.",
        "distractor2": "agriculture is no longer the most important economic activity in Africa.",
        "distractor3": "European influence no longer exists in the former colonial territories."
    },
    {
        "question": "Ethnicity and regionalism in Nigeria led to?:",
        "correct_answer": "a tragic civil war.",
        "distractor1": "an increase in export crops.",
        "distractor2": "widespread government corruption.",
        "distractor3": "the restoration of civilian rule."
    },
    {
        "question": "African nations organized regional groups to?:",
        "correct_answer": "encourage economic development.",
        "distractor1": "reduce the poewr of OPEC.",
        "distractor2": "support the Free World in the Cold War.",
        "distractor3": "give landlocked nations access to the sea."
    },
    {
        "question": "One result of the \"Sharpeville massacre\" was?:",
        "correct_answer": "worldwide protests against the South African government.",
        "distractor1": "the enactment of pass laws.",
        "distractor2": "the formation of the African National Congress.",
        "distractor3": "the repeal of laws that classified people by race."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Belgian Congo was renamed Zaire in order to?:",
        "correct_answer": "reject its colonial past.",
        "distractor1": "make Belgians leave.",
        "distractor2": "force the UN to recognize its independence.",
        "distractor3": "end the civil war there."
    },
    {
        "question": "Before the late 1990s, blacks in South Africa?:",
        "correct_answer": "were forced to live in Bantustans.",
        "distractor1": "could vote but could no form labor unions.",
        "distractor2": "had to vote for the African National Congress.",
        "distractor3": "could not work in industry."
    },
    {
        "question": "Cash crops are important to most African countries because these crops?:",
        "correct_answer": "can be sold abroad to bring money into the country.",
        "distractor1": "are used for food by the farmers and their families.",
        "distractor2": "sell for higher prices than machinery and oil.",
        "distractor3": "are always in great demand by other countries."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Rwanda, more than 500,000 Tusis died as a result of?:",
        "correct_answer": "massacres by Hutu extremists.",
        "distractor1": "battles in an effort to stop the invasion of their country by Somalia.",
        "distractor2": "starvation.",
        "distractor3": "being imprisoned for treason by their own government."
    },
    {
        "question": "The colonial capital of African colonies usually became the capital of an independent African nation because?:",
        "correct_answer": "all of these choices are correct.",
        "distractor1": "it was usually the largest city.",
        "distractor2": "it already had good communication and transportation facilities.",
        "distractor3": "it was the country\\'s most prosperous market."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is true regarding African nations in the United Nations?:",
        "correct_answer": "they are an important voice for other developing countries.",
        "distractor1": "they are not allowed full membership.",
        "distractor2": "they are a dividing force in the UN Security COouncil.",
        "distractor3": "they are under-represented in comparison with other regions in the world."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following countries became a battleground for the Cold War in Africa?:",
        "correct_answer": "Angola and Mozambique.",
        "distractor1": "Tanzania and Zaire.",
        "distractor2": "Kenya and Ghana.",
        "distractor3": "South Africa and Zimbabwe."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why did United Nations forces intervene in Somalia in December 1992?:",
        "correct_answer": "to help victims of famine there.",
        "distractor1": "to establish new colonies in that region.",
        "distractor2": "to defeat communist forces there.",
        "distractor3": "to stop the expansion of Somalia into Tanzania."
    },
    {
        "question": "Since the African National Congress came to power in South Africa in 1994, its primary aim has been to?:",
        "correct_answer": "unite the people of South Africa in a democratic republic.",
        "distractor1": "establish one-party rule in South Africa.",
        "distractor2": "restore Dutch influence on South African culture.",
        "distractor3": "create a homeland for white separatists."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Hausa and Ibo of Nigeria and the Hutus and the Tutsis of Rwanda are similar in that?:",
        "correct_answer": "their differences led to disastrous civil wars.",
        "distractor1": "they failed to unite to oust their colonial masters.",
        "distractor2": "their economic wealth led to declarations of independence.",
        "distractor3": "they quickly developed a common culture."
    },
    {
        "question": "Soweto referred to?:",
        "correct_answer": "a black South African township that had been the scene of many violent protests against apartheid.",
        "distractor1": "a trade union organization in South Africa.",
        "distractor2": "an opposition white political party that frequently sided with blacks in Zaire.",
        "distractor3": "the underground arm of the African National Congress."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is TRUE about sub-Saharan Africa today?:",
        "correct_answer": "many Africans still practice subsistence farming.",
        "distractor1": "national political boundaries are the same as traditional tribal boundaries.",
        "distractor2": "tribal customs are most often practiced in urban areas.",
        "distractor3": "trade with non-African countries has stopped."
    },
    {
        "question": "    When the white man came to Africa,  he had the Bible and the black man had the land.  Later the white man had the land  and the black man had the Bible.   The author of this statement above suggests that an important result of European involvement in Africa was that the?:'  ",
        "correct_answer": "Europeans exploited the Africans.",
        "distractor1": "Africans exchanged their land for Bibles.",
        "distractor2": "Africans became good Christians.",
        "distractor3": "Europeans lost their religious beliefs."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was a direct result of European slave trade in Africa?:",
        "correct_answer": "it promoted a feeling of racial superiority among Europeans.",
        "distractor1": "West African kingdoms prospered.",
        "distractor2": "Africans moved in large numbers to rural areas.",
        "distractor3": "African military forces ended the slave trade."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is most accurate about the African slave trade from the 15c through the 19c?:",
        "correct_answer": "the slave trade involved African, Arab, and European slave traders.",
        "distractor1": "the slave trade was limited to East Africa.",
        "distractor2": "the slave traders brought ivory and timber to Africa.",
        "distractor3": "most slaves were transported from Africa to Europe."
    },
    {
        "question": "The development of which of the following led to importation of large numbers of African slaves to the Americas?:",
        "correct_answer": "plantation agriculture.",
        "distractor1": "mercantilism.",
        "distractor2": "the spice trade.",
        "distractor3": "the joint stock company."
    },
    {
        "question": "The slave-gun cycle in West Africa during the 15c and 16c led to the?:",
        "correct_answer": "rise of several new, powerful African states.",
        "distractor1": "abolition of slavery.",
        "distractor2": "revival of Islam.",
        "distractor3": "growing of cash crops such as cotton."
    },
    {
        "question": "The vast majority of the African slaves were to be employed in the?:",
        "correct_answer": "coffee and sugar plantations in the Caribbean and South America.",
        "distractor1": "cotton plantations of British North America.",
        "distractor2": "gold and silver mines of the New World.",
        "distractor3": "colonial armies of the European conquerors."
    },
    {
        "question": "The African state that played a very active and profitable role in the transatlantic slave trade was the?:",
        "correct_answer": "Kingdom of Dahomey.",
        "distractor1": "Songhai Empire.",
        "distractor2": "Kingdom of Senegambia.",
        "distractor3": "Empire of Ethiopia."
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Olaudah Equiano, one of the worst sufferings the slaves endured was?:",
        "correct_answer": "separation from their loved ones.",
        "distractor1": "beatings.",
        "distractor2": "sickness.",
        "distractor3": "overcrowding in the slave ships."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which European nation first engaged in the African slave trade?:",
        "correct_answer": "Portugal.",
        "distractor1": "Spain.",
        "distractor2": "England.",
        "distractor3": "the Netherlands."
    },
    {
        "question": "Otal tradition is important in African cultures because it?:",
        "correct_answer": "allows knowledge to be passed from one generation to the next.",
        "distractor1": "led to most Africans speaking the same language.",
        "distractor2": "proves that humans originated in East Africa.",
        "distractor3": "prevented the development of written language in Africa."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is a major characteristic of traditional African art?:",
        "correct_answer": "African art contains a great deal of symbolism.",
        "distractor1": "the human form is represented very realistically in African art.",
        "distractor2": "painting is the primary medium for traditional African art.",
        "distractor3": "African art reflects a highly urban culture."
    },
    {
        "question": "The age-group system served as a method of?:",
        "correct_answer": "teaching children the values of their society.",
        "distractor1": "choosing brides for young men.",
        "distractor2": "limiting warfare among rival villages.",
        "distractor3": "encouraging cultural diffusion."
    },
    {
        "question": "Traditional African art has had the greatest influence on?:",
        "correct_answer": "20c European painting and sculpture.",
        "distractor1": "classical Roman mosaics and pottery.",
        "distractor2": "European Renaissance painting.",
        "distractor3": "medieval Islamic architecture."
    },
    {
        "question": "Diviners served an important role in some African societies because they?:",
        "correct_answer": "helped people understand the cause of disasters and acted as intermediaries to the spirits.",
        "distractor1": "were worshipped as gods.",
        "distractor2": "collected the taxes and supervised farming.",
        "distractor3": "determined which age grade a boy or girl belonged to."
    },
    {
        "question": "In many African cultures, political and social organization was based on the?:",
        "correct_answer": "village.",
        "distractor1": "emperor\\'s court.",
        "distractor2": "civil service system.",
        "distractor3": "council of ancestors."
    },
    {
        "question": "Traditional African religions emphasized?:",
        "correct_answer": "the connection of family, village, nature, and ancestors.",
        "distractor1": "belief in only one god.",
        "distractor2": "the importance of the  Qur\\'an  and daily prayer.",
        "distractor3": "loyalty to the village priests."
    },
    {
        "question": "In African societies, lineage?:",
        "correct_answer": "tied families to a common ancestor.",
        "distractor1": "allowed farmers and herders to trade more efficiently.",
        "distractor2": "gave women higher status than men.",
        "distractor3": "limited the power of the West African kingdoms."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following has been a chief reason for the changing social structure of the African tribal unit?:",
        "correct_answer": "movements to the cities.",
        "distractor1": "inter-tribal wars.",
        "distractor2": "independence and self-government.",
        "distractor3": "a decrease in tribal population."
    },
    {
        "question": "A griot\\'s role in West African society is similar to that of a?:",
        "correct_answer": "historian.",
        "distractor1": "scientist.",
        "distractor2": "musician.",
        "distractor3": "military leader."
    },
    {
        "question": "Before West African civilizations had contact with Europeans, these civilizations developed?:",
        "correct_answer": "sophisticated art works that included bronze, gold, and clay sculptures.",
        "distractor1": "economies that did not rely on trade for their wealth.",
        "distractor2": "one interconnected system of government for all of their empires.",
        "distractor3": "social systems that emphasized the nuclear family."
    },
    {
        "question": "One similarity between the ancient African kingdoms of Ghana, Mali, and Songhai is that all of these kingdoms were located?:",
        "correct_answer": "on major trading routes.",
        "distractor1": "in mountainous regions.",
        "distractor2": "in coastal areas.",
        "distractor3": "in rain forest regions."
    },
    {
        "question": "Mansa Musa\\'s journey to Mecca in the 1300s is evidence that?:",
        "correct_answer": "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire.",
        "distractor1": "the European Crusades had a great influence on western Africa.",
        "distractor2": "most African leaders were educated in the Middle East.",
        "distractor3": "European culture was superior to the cultures of western Africa."
    },
    {
        "question": "A major trading and university town in West Africa was?:",
        "correct_answer": "Timbuktu.",
        "distractor1": "Meroe.",
        "distractor2": "Kinshasa.",
        "distractor3": "Mombasa."
    },
    {
        "question": "How did the ruler of Ghana profit from the trade routes that met in his empire?:",
        "correct_answer": "by collecting a toll on all goods entering or leaving Ghana.",
        "distractor1": "by ambushing merchants and stealing their goods.",
        "distractor2": "by bribing merchants for a percentage of their profits.",
        "distractor3": "by allowing trade on only certain days of the week."
    },
    {
        "question": "The laws introduced by Askia Muhammad were based on?:",
        "correct_answer": "the teachings of the  Qur\\'an. ",
        "distractor1": "a respect for ancestor worship.",
        "distractor2": "the social code of the Berbers.",
        "distractor3": "the teachings of Sundiata."
    },
    {
        "question": "With the collapse of the trade routes across the Sahara in the 15c and 16c, political and economic power in Africa shifted to the coast of the?:",
        "correct_answer": "Atlantic Ocean.",
        "distractor1": "Red Sea.",
        "distractor2": "Indian Ocean.",
        "distractor3": "Mediterranean Sea."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement BEST describes the geography of Africa?:",
        "correct_answer": "deserts and savannas cover almost half of the continent.",
        "distractor1": "most of the continent is made up of tropical rain forests.",
        "distractor2": "most major rivers are navigable for their entire lengths.",
        "distractor3": "the irregular coastline provides many natural harbors."
    },
    {
        "question": "The major occupation of the people who live on the grasslands of Africa is?:",
        "correct_answer": "herding.",
        "distractor1": "lumbering.",
        "distractor2": "manufacturing.",
        "distractor3": "mining."
    },
    {
        "question": "The geographic features of the African continent are partly responsible for the?:",
        "correct_answer": "diversity of cultures found in Africa.",
        "distractor1": "use of French or English as the official languages of many African nations.",
        "distractor2": "decline of the slave trade in the 19c.",
        "distractor3": "recent advances in technology in African nations."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement BEST describes the effects of the geography of Africa?:",
        "correct_answer": "it has hindered economic development on the continent.",
        "distractor1": "it has stimulated political and cultural unity throughout the continent.",
        "distractor2": "it encouraged physical mobility throughout Africa.",
        "distractor3": "it resulted in most African countries having similar economic and social systems."
    },
    {
        "question": "In East Africa, east-west travel is hindered by the?:",
        "correct_answer": "Great Rift Valley.",
        "distractor1": "Zambezi River.",
        "distractor2": "savanna.",
        "distractor3": "Sahara Desert."
    },
    {
        "question": "Africa\\'s largest eastern lakes were named after?:",
        "correct_answer": "British rulers.",
        "distractor1": "German explorers.",
        "distractor2": "French missionaries.",
        "distractor3": "a famous Portuguese inventor."
    },
    {
        "question": "What percentage of Africa is really jungle/rain forest?:",
        "correct_answer": "15%.",
        "distractor1": "5%.",
        "distractor2": "35%.",
        "distractor3": "70%."
    },
    {
        "question": "Africa is called a \"tropical continent\" because of its?:",
        "correct_answer": "latitude.",
        "distractor1": "longitude.",
        "distractor2": "size.",
        "distractor3": "altitude."
    },
    {
        "question": "Most of the rivers in Africa are of little help in transporting large quantities of goods and people because these rivers?:",
        "correct_answer": "have many waterfalls and rapids.",
        "distractor1": "flow toward the mountains.",
        "distractor2": "run only north and south.",
        "distractor3": "are not long enough."
    },
    {
        "question": "India\\'s greatest value to the British was as a source of?:",
        "correct_answer": "agricultural products.",
        "distractor1": "minerals.",
        "distractor2": "cheap labor.",
        "distractor3": "ports and trade routes."
    },
    {
        "question": "All of the following are true of the Sepoy Mutiny EXCEPT that it?:",
        "correct_answer": "was successful.",
        "distractor1": "occurred during the Raj.",
        "distractor2": "was led by Indian soldiers.",
        "distractor3": "marked a turning point in Indian history."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following was a result of the Sepoy Mutiny?:",
        "correct_answer": "the British government tightened its control over India.",
        "distractor1": "the British East India Company went bankrupt.",
        "distractor2": "the British stopped trying to convert Indians to Christianity.",
        "distractor3": "British officials became more sensitive to the needs of Indians."
    },
    {
        "question": "The term  Raj  is used to refer to the period of Indian history during which India was?:",
        "correct_answer": "dominated by Britain.",
        "distractor1": "independent.",
        "distractor2": "torn apart by civil war.",
        "distractor3": "loosely ruled by the British East India Company."
    },
    {
        "question": "Britain fought for control of India with?:",
        "correct_answer": "France.",
        "distractor1": "Portugal.",
        "distractor2": "Spain.",
        "distractor3": "Hollard."
    },
    {
        "question": "British efforts to modernize Indian transportation and communication systems served to?:",
        "correct_answer": "unite the people of India.",
        "distractor1": "promote handicraft production.",
        "distractor2": "satisfy Indian nationalist demands.",
        "distractor3": "encourage population growth."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Indian Civil Service was designed to?:",
        "correct_answer": "provide trained Indian administrators.",
        "distractor1": "open high-level posts in Britain to educated Indians.",
        "distractor2": "modernize Indian transportation.",
        "distractor3": "encourage British emigration to India."
    },
    {
        "question": "What caused the collapse of India\\'s textile industry?:",
        "correct_answer": "the importation of British cloth to India.",
        "distractor1": "an Indian boycott of British goods.",
        "distractor2": "high taxes paid by the Indians to Great Britain.",
        "distractor3": "an increase in the price of cotton."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following was a primary goal of the British government after making India a part of the empire?:",
        "correct_answer": "to improve transportation and communication in India.",
        "distractor1": "to reestablish the East India Company.",
        "distractor2": "to eliminate the caste system.",
        "distractor3": "to unite the people of India."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following was a result of the Sepoy Rebellion?:",
        "correct_answer": "the British East India Company was abolished.",
        "distractor1": "the British East India Company took over many Indian kingdoms.",
        "distractor2": "Indian nationalist realized that the British provided needed leadership in India.",
        "distractor3": "the Mughal emperor\\'s power increased."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Buddha taught that people suffered in life because of a?:",
        "correct_answer": "desire for happiness and riches.",
        "distractor1": "belief in  nirvana .",
        "distractor2": "refusal to obey the gods.",
        "distractor3": "belief in  kama ."
    },
    {
        "question": "Buddha\\'s Four Noble Truths stress the point that?:",
        "correct_answer": "worldly sorrow and misery could be ended only by a life of selflessness.",
        "distractor1": "an individual commitment to involve oneself in the political aspects of life.",
        "distractor2": "only members of the highest class could achieve salvation because only they could do the things required in the Eightfold Path.",
        "distractor3": "that sorrow and misery did not exist."
    },
    {
        "question": "Buddhists reject the idea that?:",
        "correct_answer": "only Brahmins can show people the way to  nirvana .",
        "distractor1": "there are no gods.",
        "distractor2": "all people can achieve salvation.",
        "distractor3": "the ultimate goal of life is escape from desire."
    },
    {
        "question": "The teachings of the Buddha include all of the following EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "life\\'s cycle of pain ends at death.",
        "distractor1": "people\\'s purpose should be to attain  nirvana .",
        "distractor2": "people\\'s desire for pleasure actually causes pain.",
        "distractor3": "the way to escape life\\'s cycle of pain is be seeking wisdom."
    },
    {
        "question": "What happened to Buddhism in India?:",
        "correct_answer": "it was absorbed back into Hinduism.",
        "distractor1": "it became the majority religion of the subcontinent.",
        "distractor2": "it gained few converts.",
        "distractor3": "eventually about half of the people of India became Buddhists."
    },
    {
        "question": "The teachings of Buddha challenged the power of the?:",
        "correct_answer": "Brahmin priests.",
        "distractor1": "Hindu warrior caste.",
        "distractor2": "Persians.",
        "distractor3": "Dravidians."
    },
    {
        "question": "Buddha left his family and wealth in order to?:",
        "correct_answer": "explore the roots of human suffering.",
        "distractor1": "discover the secret of eternal life.",
        "distractor2": "rediscover his Aryan roots.",
        "distractor3": "sit under  bodhi  trees."
    },
    {
        "question": "One important difference between Hinduism and Buddhism is that?:",
        "correct_answer": "Buddhists believe a person can gain enlightenment in a single lifetime.",
        "distractor1": "Hindus worship only one God.",
        "distractor2": "Buddhists believe that human suffering is unnecessary.",
        "distractor3": "Hindus do not accept the concept of a \"world spirit\" or Brahman."
    },
    {
        "question": "The main belief of Mahayan Buddhism was that?:",
        "correct_answer": " bodhisatvas  have postponed nirvana to help others achieve enlightenment.",
        "distractor1": "life was suffering.",
        "distractor2": "all should worship in their own language and according to their customs.",
        "distractor3": "monks should travel around converting many people to Buddhism."
    },
    {
        "question": "Buddha taught that by rejecting desire people could attain  nirvana , or?:",
        "correct_answer": "a state of perfect peace.",
        "distractor1": "a state of self-denial.",
        "distractor2": "oneness with Brahma.",
        "distractor3": "a mystical union with nature."
    },
    {
        "question": "In its earliest days, Buddhism was very popular among which of the following groups in India?:",
        "correct_answer": "warriors.",
        "distractor1": "the Brahmins.",
        "distractor2": "the  Sudras .",
        "distractor3": "the Untouchables."
    },
    {
        "question": "The philosophies of Confucius and Mao Zedong both emphasized?:",
        "correct_answer": "group rather than individual welfare.",
        "distractor1": "individual rather than cooperative gain.",
        "distractor2": "industry rather than agriculture.",
        "distractor3": "religious values rather than economic profits."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Chinese Communists were successful in their revolution during the 1930s and 1940s mainly because the Communists?:",
        "correct_answer": "emphasized the needs of the rural peasant population.",
        "distractor1": "gave factory workers leadership positions in the Communist Party.",
        "distractor2": "accepted advanced military technology from Western nations.",
        "distractor3": "provided for universal suffrage and free elections."
    },
    {
        "question": "In 1958, China\\'s Great Leap Forward called for programs designed to?:",
        "correct_answer": "increase both industrial and agricultural production.",
        "distractor1": "break up the communal farm system.",
        "distractor2": "slow down industrial expansion and devote more resources to agricultural growth.",
        "distractor3": "restore a capitalist economic system."
    },
    {
        "question": "To improve economic conditions during the late 1980s and early 1990s, China adopted policies that?:",
        "correct_answer": "moved China toward a modified form of private enterprise.",
        "distractor1": "restricted agricultural and industrial exports.",
        "distractor2": "led to a Chinese military invasion of Korea.",
        "distractor3": "prohibited involvement by foreign corporations in Chinese industries."
    },
    {
        "question": "In present-day China, the major goal of the government is to?:",
        "correct_answer": "reduce its control over the economy.",
        "distractor1": "increase the freedom of the Chinese press.",
        "distractor2": "decrease Chinese trade with the United States.",
        "distractor3": "increase Chinese control over Southeast Asia."
    },
    {
        "question": "A major cause of the Tiananmen Square demonstrations in June 1989 was the?:",
        "correct_answer": "influence of Western ideas on university students.",
        "distractor1": "memories of the Japanese invasion of China.",
        "distractor2": "teachings of Confucius.",
        "distractor3": "Chinese tradition of youthful rebellion."
    },
    {
        "question": "In China and the former Soviet Union, the Communist governments discouraged organized religion because religions?:",
        "correct_answer": "compete for the loyalties of the people.",
        "distractor1": "support the principles of laissez faire.",
        "distractor2": "avor anarchy over organized government.",
        "distractor3": "stress economic rather than political values."
    },
    {
        "question": "In China during the 1980s, government efforts to adapt Western economic ideas resulted in?:",
        "correct_answer": "increased trade with many industrialized nations.",
        "distractor1": "increased dependence on the Soviet Union.",
        "distractor2": "a slowdown of economic growth.",
        "distractor3": "military confrontations with other Asian nations."
    },
    {
        "question": "An immediate result of the Cultural Revolution in China was that it?:",
        "correct_answer": "disrupted China\\'s economic and educational systems.",
        "distractor1": "helped to establish democracy in urban centers in China.",
        "distractor2": "led to economic cooperation with Japan and South Korea.",
        "distractor3": "strengthened political ties with the United States."
    },
    {
        "question": "Since the death of Mao Zedong, relations between China and the United States have improved because?:",
        "correct_answer": "both nations see an economic advantage to increased trade.",
        "distractor1": "the new Chinese leadership has adopted a democratic government.",
        "distractor2": "illegal Chinese immigration to the United States has decreased.",
        "distractor3": "the United States has increased oil imports from China."
    },
    {
        "question": "Mao launched the Cultural Revolution in order to?:",
        "correct_answer": "promote a revolutionary spirit among young Chinese.\t",
        "distractor1": "spread the responsibility system throughout China.",
        "distractor2": "weaken the influence of the communes.",
        "distractor3": "preserve traditional Chinese culture and customs."
    },
    {
        "question": "After 1949, the lives of Chinese women changed because they?:",
        "correct_answer": "were guaranteed equality under the law.",
        "distractor1": "had to work in the fields for the first time.",
        "distractor2": "were allowed to have only two children.",
        "distractor3": "were forbidden to marry until they were 25 years old."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Chinese history, the dynastic cycle represents a continual process of?:",
        "correct_answer": "death and rebirth.",
        "distractor1": "strength and prosperity.",
        "distractor2": "marriage and divorce.",
        "distractor3": "corruption and decline."
    },
    {
        "question": "Under the Han dynasty, China?:",
        "correct_answer": "set up a bureaucratic system of government.",
        "distractor1": "sent out armies to conquer the Roman Empire.",
        "distractor2": "forbade all trade with other lands.",
        "distractor3": "outlawed the teachings of Confucius."
    },
    {
        "question": "Goods traveled from China to Greece and Rome in the West on the Silk Road by?:",
        "correct_answer": "land across central Asia.",
        "distractor1": "sea around the coast of India.",
        "distractor2": "land across northeastern China.",
        "distractor3": "water along the Yangtze River."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Chinese believed a ruler kept the Mandate of Heaven by?:",
        "correct_answer": "governing wisely.",
        "distractor1": "abolishing ancestor worship.",
        "distractor2": "ending slavery.",
        "distractor3": "conquering new lands."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Han dynasty, the Chinese invented?:",
        "correct_answer": "paper.",
        "distractor1": "drama.",
        "distractor2": "bronze.",
        "distractor3": "the arch."
    },
    {
        "question": "Candidates for the Chinese civil service needed a thorough knowledge of?:",
        "correct_answer": "the Confucian classics.",
        "distractor1": "the teachings of Buddha.",
        "distractor2": "science and mathematics.",
        "distractor3": "world geography."
    },
    {
        "question": "Han rulers encouraged education in order to?:",
        "correct_answer": "train government officials.",
        "distractor1": "increase the number of chinese inventions.",
        "distractor2": "improve the life of the common people.",
        "distractor3": "spread Buddhist ideas."
    },
    {
        "question": "The greatest problem faced by the later Han emperors was?:",
        "correct_answer": "peasant upheavals.",
        "distractor1": "foreign invasion.",
        "distractor2": "succession crises.",
        "distractor3": "urban poverty."
    },
    {
        "question": "the Great Silk Road reached from China to?:",
        "correct_answer": "Persia.",
        "distractor1": "India.",
        "distractor2": "Syria and Asia Minor.",
        "distractor3": "Mongolia."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Han era is considered a golden age in China for all of the following reasons EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "the defeat of the barbarians.",
        "distractor1": "the revival of learning.",
        "distractor2": "the development of trade.",
        "distractor3": "the influence of Confucius\\' ideas."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 19c, Western nations were able to gain control over parts of China mainly because?:",
        "correct_answer": "China lacked the military technology needed to stop these ventures.",
        "distractor1": "the CHinese had a strong tradition of non-violence.",
        "distractor2": "China was promised aid for its industries.",
        "distractor3": "the Chinese lacked a strong cultural identity."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Boxer Rebellion of the early 20c was an attempt to?:",
        "correct_answer": "remove foreign influences from China.",
        "distractor1": "eliminate poverty among the Chinese peasants.",
        "distractor2": "bring Western-style democracy to China.",
        "distractor3": "restore trade between China and European nations."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the late 1800s, imperialistic nations divided China into?:",
        "correct_answer": "spheres of influence.",
        "distractor1": "plantations.",
        "distractor2": "independent city-states.",
        "distractor3": "communes."
    },
    {
        "question": "After the Revolution of 1911, Sun Yixian [Sun Yat-sen] was unable to achieve his goals for China because?:",
        "correct_answer": "civil war broke out.",
        "distractor1": "Japan conquered China.",
        "distractor2": "the Communists took over.",
        "distractor3": "the empress Cixi opposed any changes."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Long March occurred as a result of?:",
        "correct_answer": "Jiang Jieshi\\'s efforts to wipe out the Communists.",
        "distractor1": "the ouitbreak of World War II.",
        "distractor2": "the Boxers\\' determination to win control of China.",
        "distractor3": "Chinese efforts to settle the interior."
    },
    {
        "question": "The right of extraterritoriality in the 19c and early 20c allowed the Westerner in China to?:",
        "correct_answer": "be tried for crime under laws of his own country.",
        "distractor1": "establish an import-export business.",
        "distractor2": "take out temporary Chinese citizenship.",
        "distractor3": "serve as an advisor to the Chinese government."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Open Door Policy?:",
        "correct_answer": "urged that all Western powers have equal trading rights in China.",
        "distractor1": "warned Western powers to leave China alone.",
        "distractor2": "divided China into four shperes of influence.",
        "distractor3": "established a trade agreement between China and Japan."
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the results of the Treaty of Nanjing of 1842 was that?:",
        "correct_answer": "China gave Hong Kong to the British.",
        "distractor1": "the East India Company was established.",
        "distractor2": "China increased the tariff on British goods.",
        "distractor3": "the British paid damages for opium they destroyed."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1800s, the British were interested in China mainaly as a?:",
        "correct_answer": "market for opium.",
        "distractor1": "market for sugar and coffee.",
        "distractor2": "source of rubber and ginseng.",
        "distractor3": "source of raw cotton."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Taiping Rebellion was caused in part by the?:",
        "correct_answer": "demand for peasants for land.",
        "distractor1": "war between China and Japan.",
        "distractor2": "death of the Empress Cixi.",
        "distractor3": "reforms of Kuang Hsu."
    },
    {
        "question": "A basic of Sun Yixian [Sun Yat-sen] was to?:",
        "correct_answer": "implement The Three Principles of the People.",
        "distractor1": "declare war on Japan.",
        "distractor2": "execute Chinese missionaries.",
        "distractor3": "overthrow the Empress Cixi."
    },
    {
        "question": "In 1911, nationalism in China was the main reason for the struggle to?:",
        "correct_answer": "overthrow the Manchus.",
        "distractor1": "capture Beijing.",
        "distractor2": "conquer the Japanese.",
        "distractor3": "complete the Long March."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Yanan, long after the Long March, the Chinese communists continued to fight Jiang Jieshu [Chiang Kai-shek] with the support of the?:",
        "correct_answer": "Chinese peasants.",
        "distractor1": "Soviets.",
        "distractor2": "Manchus.",
        "distractor3": "Japanese."
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Three Principles of the People, Sun Yixian [Sun Yat-sen] declared that?:",
        "correct_answer": "China should be thoroughly reorganized in order to become a strong modern nation based on Western democratic principles.",
        "distractor1": "the Chinese should organize a new government based on the teachings of Confucius.",
        "distractor2": "the Kuomintang had the Mandate of Heaven.",
        "distractor3": "the CHinese should reject all western ideas."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which best accounts for the lack of political unity in China between 1912 and 1937?:",
        "correct_answer": "little popular loyalty to the central government in Nanjing.",
        "distractor1": "religious warfare.",
        "distractor2": "nonrecognition of the Chinese government by foreign powers.",
        "distractor3": "the declining strength of Chinese communism."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Long March was the journey undertaken by?:",
        "correct_answer": "Chinese Communists fleeing the Kuomintang.",
        "distractor1": "Armenians fleeing Turkish persecution.",
        "distractor2": "Indians protesting British rule.",
        "distractor3": "Tibetans fighting Chinese rule."
    },
    {
        "question": "Manchuria was a region of conflict between foreign powers because of?:",
        "correct_answer": "its coal and iron mines.",
        "distractor1": "its strategic location.",
        "distractor2": "the rich farmlands there.",
        "distractor3": "its important seaport and transportation routes."
    },
    {
        "question": "Mao Zedong\\'s goals included all of the following EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "launching a non-corrupt, Western-style democracy.",
        "distractor1": "overthrowing the Chinese Nationalists.",
        "distractor2": "starting a Communist revolution led by the peasants.",
        "distractor3": "driving the Japanese out of Chinese territory."
    },
    {
        "question": "Confucianism encouraged its followers to?:",
        "correct_answer": "respect traditional customs.",
        "distractor1": "travel to foreign countries.",
        "distractor2": "experiment with science.",
        "distractor3": "conquer East Asia."
    },
    {
        "question": "In ancient China, one effect on government of the teachings of Confucius was the high status of?:",
        "correct_answer": "scholars.",
        "distractor1": "soldiers.",
        "distractor2": "merchants.",
        "distractor3": "farmers."
    },
    {
        "question": "A goal common to Confucianism, Taoism, and Buddhism is to?:",
        "correct_answer": "establish peace and harmony in this life.",
        "distractor1": "provide the basis for democratic government.",
        "distractor2": "return the power of the emperors.",
        "distractor3": "promote individual artistic creativity."
    },
    {
        "question": "Yin and yang represented?:",
        "correct_answer": "balance in all of nature.",
        "distractor1": "political conflict.",
        "distractor2": "domination of good over evil.",
        "distractor3": "chaos in society."
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Confucius, the best government was one which?:",
        "correct_answer": "set a good example for the people it ruled.",
        "distractor1": "established laws and punishments which made men moral.",
        "distractor2": "took measures to insure economic growth.",
        "distractor3": "maintained a well-equipped army to keep Westerners out of China."
    },
    {
        "question": "Mencius gave the Chinese people a \"safety valve\" or way of getting rid of corrupt, evil dynasties.  This was called?:",
        "correct_answer": "Mandate of Heaven.",
        "distractor1": "calligraphy.",
        "distractor2": "feudalism.",
        "distractor3": "filial piety."
    },
    {
        "question": "Confucius believed that a good society was one that?:",
        "correct_answer": "preserved peace and order.",
        "distractor1": "produced great philosophers.",
        "distractor2": "was run according to Buddhist principles.",
        "distractor3": "protected the rights of individuals."
    },
    {
        "question": "Legalism was based on a view of human nature as?:",
        "correct_answer": "selfish and untrustworthy.",
        "distractor1": "balanced by yin and yang.",
        "distractor2": "independent of outside influences.",
        "distractor3": "well-ordered and rigid."
    },
    {
        "question": "Confucius believed the best ruler was?:",
        "correct_answer": "a virtuous man who led by example.",
        "distractor1": "someone who would pass strict laws.",
        "distractor2": "a man with little education.",
        "distractor3": "a great military hero."
    },
    {
        "question": "Confucius defined the rights and responsibilities of the citizens of imperial China by?:",
        "correct_answer": "developing a code of ethical conduct.",
        "distractor1": "formulating a law code.",
        "distractor2": "writing rules for elections.",
        "distractor3": "drawing up lists of candidates for public office."
    },
    {
        "question": "In traditional Chinese culture, which philosophy had the greatest influence on the development of social order and political organization?:",
        "correct_answer": "Confucianism.",
        "distractor1": "Taoism.",
        "distractor2": "Hinduism.",
        "distractor3": "Shintoism."
    },
    {
        "question": "Confucianism emphasizes the idea that?:",
        "correct_answer": "each person has an important responsibility to family and society.",
        "distractor1": "government should own the means of production.",
        "distractor2": "economic success is more desirable than knowledge and learning.",
        "distractor3": "an individual\\'s personal goals are more important than the goals of the group."
    },
    {
        "question": "Unlike Confucianism, Taoism emphasized?:",
        "correct_answer": "seeking ways to live in harmony with nature.",
        "distractor1": "getting a good education.",
        "distractor2": "enforcing strict rules and laws.",
        "distractor3": "adapting new ideas from non-Chinese cultures."
    },
    {
        "question": "Many Chinese were attracted to Buddhism because it?:",
        "correct_answer": "offered comfort to the poor and suffering.",
        "distractor1": "glorified the emperor.",
        "distractor2": "taught respect for foreigners.",
        "distractor3": "encouraged peasants to revolt."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following traditional Chinese philosophies would be most sympathetic to dictatorial, authoritarian goverments?:",
        "correct_answer": "Legalism.",
        "distractor1": "Taoism.",
        "distractor2": "Buddhism.",
        "distractor3": "Confucianism."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Chinese attitude toward religion?:",
        "correct_answer": "enabled many Chinese to practice more than one religion at the same time.",
        "distractor1": "dictated strict adherence to one religion.",
        "distractor2": "prevented the Chinese from adopting Buddhism.",
        "distractor3": "all of these choices are correct."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why did the Chinese honor their ancestors\\' spirits?:",
        "correct_answer": "they believed that their ancestors\\' spirits could bring good fortune to their families.",
        "distractor1": "they believed that their ancestors became part of Shang Di when they died.",
        "distractor2": "honoring their ancestors would help maintain the balance of yin and yang.",
        "distractor3": "honoring their ancestors would improve their own afterlife."
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Legalism, the way to achieve order was to?:",
        "correct_answer": "pass strict laws and enforce them with harsh punishments.",
        "distractor1": "provide a ruler who set a good moral example.",
        "distractor2": "appeal to man\\'s natural goodness.",
        "distractor3": "live by the natural balance of yin and yang."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Confucian thought, the ruler-subject relationship was modeled after?:",
        "correct_answer": "the father-son relationship.",
        "distractor1": "the mother-daughter relationship.",
        "distractor2": "the father-daughter relationship.",
        "distractor3": "the older brother-younger brother relationship."
    },
    {
        "question": "A sincere follower of Confucius would be in most disagreement with which of the following statements?:",
        "correct_answer": " I am the captain of my fate, I am the master of my soul. ",
        "distractor1": " Let the ruler be a ruler and a subject be a subject. ",
        "distractor2": " The Superior Man should spend his hours searching for the ways of Heaven and the truths taught by the past. ",
        "distractor3": " Knowing your place in life will bring much happiness. "
    },
    {
        "question": "Shi Huang Di, the First Emperor, united China by?:",
        "correct_answer": "enforcing strict Legalist principles.",
        "distractor1": "importing European weapons.",
        "distractor2": "encouraging Confucian teachings.",
        "distractor3": "setting up the civil service examination."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Chinese, like many other peoples, have often been considered ethnocentric.  They have shown ethnocentric attitudes in the past by?:",
        "correct_answer": "considering outsiders less civilized than themselves.",
        "distractor1": "following a non-religious way of life.",
        "distractor2": "failing to develop any long lasting cultural contributions until the West came to China.",
        "distractor3": "refusing to follow the tribute system."
    },
    {
        "question": "The first unified Chinese empire came under which of the following dynasties?:",
        "correct_answer": "Ch\\'in.",
        "distractor1": "Chou.",
        "distractor2": "Han.",
        "distractor3": "Shang."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following caused the decline of the Chou (Zhou) dynasty?:",
        "correct_answer": "feudal warfare.",
        "distractor1": "ancestor worship.",
        "distractor2": "economic growth.",
        "distractor3": "foreign invasion."
    },
    {
        "question": "Hatred of the Ch\\'in (Qin) was fostered by all of the following EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "widespread confiscation of peasant lands.",
        "distractor1": "the staggering tax burden.",
        "distractor2": "forced labor on such projects as the Great Wall.",
        "distractor3": "the ruthless suppression of Confucianism."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Chou (Zhou) times, the Chinese state was?:",
        "correct_answer": "feudal in nature.",
        "distractor1": "highly centralized.",
        "distractor2": "an absolute monarchy.",
        "distractor3": "a loose confederation."
    },
    {
        "question": "China\\'s most valuable commodity was?:",
        "correct_answer": "silk.",
        "distractor1": "tea.",
        "distractor2": "porcelain.",
        "distractor3": "opium."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Great Wall of China was begun in 214 BCE to?:",
        "correct_answer": "guard against nomadic invasions.",
        "distractor1": "keep cattle from straying from Chinese territories.",
        "distractor2": "keep Chinese convicts from escaping their prisons in northern China.",
        "distractor3": "all of these choices are correct."
    },
    {
        "question": "The most important factor in developing agriculture in China was?:",
        "correct_answer": "controlling the floods of the Huang-He [Yellow] River.",
        "distractor1": "irrigating dry sections of the Gobi Desert.",
        "distractor2": "predicting when the seasonal rains would fall.",
        "distractor3": "protecting China Proper from foreign invasion."
    },
    {
        "question": "The amount of land in China that is arable land is approximately?:",
        "correct_answer": "10%.",
        "distractor1": "40%.",
        "distractor2": "25%.",
        "distractor3": "50%."
    },
    {
        "question": "In China, the development of ethnocentrism was most influenced by?:",
        "correct_answer": "its geographic isolation.",
        "distractor1": "its historic reliance on foreign nations.",
        "distractor2": "a long history of democratic government.",
        "distractor3": "a strong belief in Christianity."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following geographic features would have the greatest effect on the lives of the Chinese people?:",
        "correct_answer": "monsoons.",
        "distractor1": "mountains.",
        "distractor2": "deserts.",
        "distractor3": "North Current."
    },
    {
        "question": "As a person travels WEST in China, he/she is most likely to find?:",
        "correct_answer": "mountains and deserts.",
        "distractor1": "densely populated cities.",
        "distractor2": "large agricultural areas.",
        "distractor3": "dry plains."
    },
    {
        "question": "The best way to discuss the climate of China is to?:",
        "correct_answer": "compare the differences between North and South China.",
        "distractor1": "study the entire country because there are few variations.",
        "distractor2": "compare the differences between China and Southeast Asia.",
        "distractor3": "study only the southern area because most of the Chinese live there."
    },
    {
        "question": "Shan : China  ::          ?        : India",
        "correct_answer": "ghats.",
        "distractor1": "loess.",
        "distractor2": "Kuo.",
        "distractor3": "arigato."
    },
    {
        "question": "The only answer to northern China\\'s agricultural problems is?:",
        "correct_answer": "reforestation.",
        "distractor1": "building more canals.",
        "distractor2": "crop rotation.",
        "distractor3": "terrace farming."
    },
    {
        "question": "The term \"China\\'s Sorrow\" refers to?:",
        "correct_answer": "the violent flooding of the Yellow River.",
        "distractor1": "the oppression of the First Emperor.",
        "distractor2": "the constant invasions by nomadic tribes.",
        "distractor3": "the burning of Confucian writings."
    },
    {
        "question": "One major change in China during the Ming dynasty was?:",
        "correct_answer": "ending naval expeditions and foreign trade.",
        "distractor1": "giving peasants more power.",
        "distractor2": "repudiating Confucian ideas.",
        "distractor3": "establishing colonies overseas."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Tang strengthened the government by?:",
        "correct_answer": "reintroducing the civil service examination.",
        "distractor1": "extending the Grand Canal into Korea.",
        "distractor2": "giving up the Mandate of Heaven.",
        "distractor3": "appointing a shogun to rule."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Chinese innovations of paper money and banking were the result of increased trade and?:",
        "correct_answer": "the invention of printing.",
        "distractor1": "political centralizatio.",
        "distractor2": "agricultural productivity.",
        "distractor3": "exposure to similar European practices."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1400s, the Grand Fleet of Cheng Ho sailed from China all the way to?:",
        "correct_answer": "the east coast of Africa.",
        "distractor1": "India.",
        "distractor2": "the Persian Gulf.",
        "distractor3": "the East Indies."
    },
    {
        "question": "Footbinding was primarily practiced on?:",
        "correct_answer": "elite, upper class women.",
        "distractor1": "working women.",
        "distractor2": "poor women.",
        "distractor3": "just unmarried women."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Chinese viewed the first Europeans to arrive in the 16c?:",
        "correct_answer": "as just another group of unruly barbarian pirates.",
        "distractor1": "with awe and fear.",
        "distractor2": "with eagerness to learn the latest Western science and technology.",
        "distractor3": "with eagerness to open new trade relations."
    },
    {
        "question": "Probably the best known aspect of Tang art was?:",
        "correct_answer": "glazed pottery figurines.",
        "distractor1": "delicate flower arranging.",
        "distractor2": "silk-screening of scenes from daily life.",
        "distractor3": "elaborate decorative mosaics."
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 15c through the 18c, China\\'s ethnocentric concept of itself as the \"Middle Kingdom\" led to?:",
        "correct_answer": "a lack of interest in trade with European nations.",
        "distractor1": "renewed attempts at Mediterranean conquest.",
        "distractor2": "religious missionary expeditions to the New World.",
        "distractor3": "granting independence to its tributary states in Southeast Asia."
    },
    {
        "question": "The civil service of the Song period was?:",
        "correct_answer": "recruited through competitive examinations.",
        "distractor1": "chosen from the hereditary aristocracy.",
        "distractor2": "had little power and influence.",
        "distractor3": "highly illiterate and corrupt."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement BEST describes an effect of the civil service system in China?:",
        "correct_answer": "the exam ensured that officials shared Confucian values and traditions.",
        "distractor1": "only the sons of gentry could take the exam.",
        "distractor2": "the exam tested young men on their knowledge of mathematics, science, and history.",
        "distractor3": "the exam protected China from corrupt officials."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Chinese society, the practice of foot-binding was a symbol of the?:",
        "correct_answer": "inferior place of women.",
        "distractor1": "harshness of lower class life.",
        "distractor2": "influence of Taoism (Daoism).",
        "distractor3": "importance of the family."
    },
    {
        "question": "In their painting and poetry, the Chinese?:",
        "correct_answer": "expressed respect for nature.",
        "distractor1": "copied Indian artistic styles.",
        "distractor2": "showed their dislike of foreigners.",
        "distractor3": "emphasized the importance of the individual."
    },
    {
        "question": "The T\\'ang and Sung dynasties are considered Golden Ages of China in part because?:",
        "correct_answer": "the economy prospered and the arts flourished.",
        "distractor1": "new gold and silver mines were discovered.",
        "distractor2": "everyone learned to read and write.",
        "distractor3": "China conquered Korea, Japan, and Southeast Asia."
    },
    {
        "question": "How did the Sung emperors try to keep peace with their fierce northern neighbors, the Tatars?:",
        "correct_answer": "by giving them expensive gifts.",
        "distractor1": "by keeping a large army.",
        "distractor2": "by building a huge wall.",
        "distractor3": "by conquering them."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following would an artist in China in 1000 most likely have chosen to paint?:",
        "correct_answer": "a tree.",
        "distractor1": "children.",
        "distractor2": "a king.",
        "distractor3": "a table."
    },
    {
        "question": "Genghis Khan is remembered as a famous conqueror who?:",
        "correct_answer": "united CHina under Mongol rule.",
        "distractor1": "created the basic philosophy of China.",
        "distractor2": "introduced Buddhism into China.",
        "distractor3": "isolated China from the outside world."
    },
    {
        "question": "All of these statements about the Mongols\\' way of life are true EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "they were peaceful herders.",
        "distractor1": "they were nomads from the central Asian steppes.",
        "distractor2": "they herded horses, cattle, and yaks.",
        "distractor3": "they were skilled horsemen and fierce warriors."
    },
    {
        "question": "To keep Mongols from being absorbed into Chinese civilization, Kublai Khan?:",
        "correct_answer": "reserved government jobs for Mongols.",
        "distractor1": "banned foreigners from China.",
        "distractor2": "welcomed foreigners to his court.",
        "distractor3": "allowed Chinese in the military."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Mongol conquest of China resulted in?:",
        "correct_answer": "increased contact between China and the Western world.",
        "distractor1": "a revival of Chinese arts and literature.",
        "distractor2": "a lack of political stability.",
        "distractor3": "persecution of Muslims and Christians."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Zealots?:",
        "correct_answer": "wanted to expel the Romans from Judea.",
        "distractor1": "believed that Jesus was the Messiah.",
        "distractor2": "were followers of a new Roman mystery religion.",
        "distractor3": "felt Christ\\'s message applied only to the Jews."
    },
    {
        "question": "Jewish leaders of the 1c?:",
        "correct_answer": "were unsure about Jesus, with some supporting him and the priests of the Temple criticizing him.",
        "distractor1": "at first were pleased to see in Jesus a rebel leader that would push for the end of Roman rule in Judea.",
        "distractor2": "were satisfied at least that Jesus emphasized complete respect for Sabbath traditions.",
        "distractor3": "viewed Jesus as one of many who had already claimed to be the Messiah."
    },
    {
        "question": "Many people were attracted to Christianity because?:",
        "correct_answer": "it taught that anyone could achieve salvation.",
        "distractor1": "it did not require people to obey any special laws.",
        "distractor2": "its teachings grew out of Judaism.",
        "distractor3": "it allowed people to keep their traditional beliefs along with Christian teachings."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following was a factor in the spread of Christianity?:",
        "correct_answer": "system of Roman roads.",
        "distractor1": "discontent with Muslim rule.",
        "distractor2": "widespread use of the Hebrew language.",
        "distractor3": "popularity of the Pope."
    },
    {
        "question": "Bishops in the Christian Church?:",
        "correct_answer": "decided on matters of Christian beliefs.",
        "distractor1": "did not believe in the sacred Trinity.",
        "distractor2": "led Christian armies against the Roman emperors.",
        "distractor3": "translated the Bible into Greek."
    },
    {
        "question": "The new religion of Christianity appealed particularly to?:",
        "correct_answer": "people with low status in the Roman Empire.",
        "distractor1": "people who sought political independence from Rome.",
        "distractor2": "people who opposed Rome\\'s treatment of the Jews.",
        "distractor3": "people who sought to acquire great wealth."
    },
    {
        "question": "The teachings of the Christian religion include all of the following EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "that only certain people could become Christians and be saved.",
        "distractor1": "belief in a Kingdom of God.",
        "distractor2": "that people should live by the Golden Rule.",
        "distractor3": "that Jesus is the Messiah promised by God."
    },
    {
        "question": "Many Romans accused early Christians of treason because they?:",
        "correct_answer": "refused to honor the Roman Emperor as a god and rejected military service.",
        "distractor1": "said that Jesus was the Son of God.",
        "distractor2": "tried to start a church in Rome.",
        "distractor3": "encouraged the poor to rebel against the Roman Emperor."
    },
    {
        "question": "The most important source for our knowledge of early Hebrew society has been?:",
        "correct_answer": "the Bible.",
        "distractor1": "personal letters and diaries.",
        "distractor2": "government records.",
        "distractor3": "cuneiform tablets."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Hebrews believed that God would protect them if they?:",
        "correct_answer": "obeyed the Ten Commandments.",
        "distractor1": "conquered Palestine.",
        "distractor2": "placed their capital at Jerusalem.",
        "distractor3": "revolted against Roman rule."
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Hebrew tradition, a \"covenant\" is?:",
        "correct_answer": "an agreement between God and man.",
        "distractor1": "a prophecy about the future.",
        "distractor2": "a law handed down by God to men.",
        "distractor3": "an ornamental chest for storing religious documents."
    },
    {
        "question": "Mosaic law differed from earlier ancient law codes because of?:",
        "correct_answer": "the value it placed on individual human life.",
        "distractor1": "the harshness of its punishments.",
        "distractor2": "its outlawing of slavery.",
        "distractor3": "its emphasis on polytheism."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about the ancient kingdom of Israel is accurate?:",
        "correct_answer": "it lasted only a short time, but its religious believs had a major impact on the world.",
        "distractor1": "its rulers appointed governors to administer each province and enforce the law.",
        "distractor2": "it extended over a vast area from the Nile Valley to the Fertile Crescent.",
        "distractor3": "King David helped the Hebrews return from the  diaspora ."
    },
    {
        "question": "How did the Jewish view of God differ from the beliefs of most people in the ancient world?:",
        "correct_answer": "Jews believed in only one God.",
        "distractor1": "Jews believed in many gods who shared equal power in the heavens.",
        "distractor2": "Jews believed in one main god with several minor gods and goddesses.",
        "distractor3": "Jews believed in no gods, but believed in sacred spirits in all of nature."
    },
    {
        "question": "Many Hebrews resented Solomon for all of the following reasons EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "his failure to create a united Jewish Empire.",
        "distractor1": "his acceptance of other religions.",
        "distractor2": "his use of forced labor to build his Palace.",
        "distractor3": "higher taxes."
    },
    {
        "question": "King David was best known for which of the following accomplishments?:",
        "correct_answer": "establishing Jerusalem as the capital of Israel.",
        "distractor1": "continued to consolidate Israel\\'s power throughout Persia.",
        "distractor2": "destroying the Ark of the Covenant.",
        "distractor3": "splitting Israel into two separate nations."
    },
    {
        "question": "To identify the location of a place, you would most likely describe its?:",
        "correct_answer": "latitude and longitude.",
        "distractor1": "culture.",
        "distractor2": "vegetation.",
        "distractor3": "exports and imports."
    },
    {
        "question": "Altitude affects the climate of some regions because?:",
        "correct_answer": "temperatures are cooler at higher elevations.",
        "distractor1": "low-lying regions have lower temperatures.",
        "distractor2": "more rain falls at lower elevations.",
        "distractor3": "highlands have more rivers than lowlands."
    },
    {
        "question": " Heavy rainfall and high temperatures are constant throughout the year in the Zaire Basin.   Which climate does this describe?:",
        "correct_answer": "tropical rainy.",
        "distractor1": "Mediterranean.",
        "distractor2": "savanna.",
        "distractor3": "tropical desert."
    },
    {
        "question": "Two major factors that affect the climate of a place are?:",
        "correct_answer": "altitude and latitude.",
        "distractor1": "population and culture.",
        "distractor2": "resources and vegetation.",
        "distractor3": "longitude and landforms."
    },
    {
        "question": "Desertification is caused by?:",
        "correct_answer": "overgrazing, deforestation, and over-cultivating.",
        "distractor1": "flooding of low lying plains.",
        "distractor2": "strip mining for gold.",
        "distractor3": "heavy rainfall."
    },
    {
        "question": "A geographer studies all of the following EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "primary and secondary school enrollment data.",
        "distractor1": "topography.",
        "distractor2": "climate.",
        "distractor3": "distribution of flora and fauna."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is geography important to history?:",
        "correct_answer": "it shows us the connections between people, places, and events.",
        "distractor1": "it helps us predict the future.",
        "distractor2": "it tells us when events took place.",
        "distractor3": "it uncovers artifacts left by early people."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why are the Suez Canal, the Strait of Hormuz, the Dardanelles, and the Bosporus strategic waterways?:",
        "correct_answer": "the nation that controls these waterways can have economic control over other nations.",
        "distractor1": "they are natural geographic boundaries and have often separated warring nations.",
        "distractor2": "they are located along the Tropic of Cancer, the Equator, or the Tropic of Capricorn.",
        "distractor3": "the nations that adjoin these waterways depend on them as a source of fresh water."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why type of map would focus on showing land forms?:",
        "correct_answer": "physical features map.",
        "distractor1": "climatic patterns map.",
        "distractor2": "political boundaries map.",
        "distractor3": "weather cycles map."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about the impact of geography on the development of a region\\'s culture is most accurate?:",
        "correct_answer": "geographic diversity often leads to cultural diversity.",
        "distractor1": "geography has little impact on culture.",
        "distractor2": "geography rarely affects the development of early civilizations.",
        "distractor3": "geographic isolation encourages cultural diffusion."
    },
    {
        "question": "An anthropologist working in a traditional African village would most probably engage in which activity?:",
        "correct_answer": "studying the language and marriage patterns of the people.",
        "distractor1": "assisting in setting up an irrigation project.",
        "distractor2": "working to set up a village legal system.",
        "distractor3": "helping to implement a family planning program."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is the most fundamental economic question for every society?:",
        "correct_answer": "How should goods and services be produced and distributed?",
        "distractor1": "What form of currency should be used?",
        "distractor2": "Wich which nations should the society trade?",
        "distractor3": "What level of personal income is appropriate?"
    },
    {
        "question": "Nationalism is most likely to develop in areas where people have?:",
        "correct_answer": "a common language and system of laws.",
        "distractor1": "strong local traditions.",
        "distractor2": "little contact with the outside world.",
        "distractor3": "an economy based on subsistence agriculture."
    },
    {
        "question": "A historian would most likely agree with which of the following statements?:",
        "correct_answer": "primary sources are subject to different interpretations.",
        "distractor1": "secondary sources are of little value in historical research.",
        "distractor2": "primary sources are effective only if accompanied by a written account by a contemporary author.",
        "distractor3": "secondary sources should primarily be used in studies of political institutions."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which situation BEST illustrates the concept of the interdependence among nations?:",
        "correct_answer": "sales of goods by one nation to obtain scarce resources from another nation.",
        "distractor1": "adoption of a policy of economic nationalism.",
        "distractor2": "establishment by a nation of a system of high protective tariffs.",
        "distractor3": "expansion of international sporting events."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is the most valid statement about customs, religion, and family structure?:",
        "correct_answer": "they are forms of social control.",
        "distractor1": "their main purpose is to prevent social change.",
        "distractor2": "they are seldom influenced by the existing economic system.",
        "distractor3": "they are often changed by political events."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which situation is most characteristic of a traditional society?:",
        "correct_answer": "a boy learns his father\\'s craft or occupation.",
        "distractor1": "college students protest an administration decision.",
        "distractor2": "a local farmer purchases chemical fertilizer.",
        "distractor3": "men and women possess full social equality."
    },
    {
        "question": "The study of the art, music, and literature of a nation helps us better to understand the nation\\'s?:",
        "correct_answer": "cultural values.",
        "distractor1": "economic progress.",
        "distractor2": "political development.",
        "distractor3": "technological advancement."
    },
    {
        "question": "The MOST valid statement concerning societies which have had a \"Golden Age\" is that during these periods they?:",
        "correct_answer": "possessed great quantities of natural resources.",
        "distractor1": "surpassed all preceding cultures in scientific advances.",
        "distractor2": "experienced major accomplishments in the arts, sciences, and literature.",
        "distractor3": "developed democratic governments."
    },
    {
        "question": "Social mobility would most likely take place in a society where social class is based on?:",
        "correct_answer": "accumulation of weath.",
        "distractor1": "inherited occupations.",
        "distractor2": "racial characteristics.",
        "distractor3": "religious beliefs."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is generally characteristic of a nation undergoing the process of industrialization?:",
        "correct_answer": "conflicts between modern ideas and traditional ways of life.",
        "distractor1": "less opportunity for social mobility.",
        "distractor2": "shifts in the population from urban to rural areas.",
        "distractor3": "increased reliance on the extended family to supply society\\'s basic needs."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which best defines the term \"culture?:\"",
        "correct_answer": "the total learned heritage of a people.",
        "distractor1": "the interaction of peoples within their environment.",
        "distractor2": "the acceptance by one ethnic group of another ethnic group\\'s values and customs.",
        "distractor3": "the adaptation by a less advanced people of the customs and values of a more advanced group."
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Hinduism, the goal of life should be to?:",
        "correct_answer": "free the soul from the cucle of reincarnation.",
        "distractor1": "memorize all prayers in the  Vedas .",
        "distractor2": "worship Vishnu above all other gods.",
        "distractor3": "obey the laws set out by Siddhartha Gautama."
    },
    {
        "question": "Belief in  karma  affects Hindus because it holds that?:",
        "correct_answer": "one\\'s deeds in a current life affects a person\\'s fate in a future life.",
        "distractor1": "only men can achieve  nirvana .",
        "distractor2": "by following the Eighthfold Path, a person will rise in caste status.",
        "distractor3": "the soul is reincarnated many times."
    },
    {
        "question": "Muslims could not understand the Hindu caste system because they believed that?:",
        "correct_answer": "all followers are equal in the eyes of God.",
        "distractor1": "everyone should receive an equal piece of land.",
        "distractor2": "women have the same rights as men.",
        "distractor3": "the state should own all means of making goods."
    },
    {
        "question": "The religious importance of the story of Krishna in the  Bhagavad-Gita  is?:",
        "correct_answer": "that it explains the idea of deliverance from the wheel of rebirth by obeying one\\'s  dharma .",
        "distractor1": "that it tells how to be a good Buddhist.",
        "distractor2": "the explanation of the orirings of the gods.",
        "distractor3": "the explanation of the decline of the caste system."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Hindu religion is based on the traditions of which people?:",
        "correct_answer": "Aryans.",
        "distractor1": " Vaishyas .",
        "distractor2": "Persians.",
        "distractor3": "Greeks."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why do Hindus believe it is important to follow the path of non-violence?:",
        "correct_answer": "all people and things are aspects of Brahman and should be respected.",
        "distractor1": "practicing non-violence allows them to escape the wheel of fate.",
        "distractor2": "it reinforces the importance of duty.",
        "distractor3": "practicing non-violence improves meditation."
    },
    {
        "question": "In addition to providing water for Indian agriculture, the Ganges River remains important to India because it is?:",
        "correct_answer": "a sacred river for the Hindu population.",
        "distractor1": "the only source of Indian hydroelectric power.",
        "distractor2": "the birthplace of Hindu civilization.",
        "distractor3": "an unofficial boundary between the Hindus and Muslims."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements about Hinduism is an opinion rather than a fact?:",
        "correct_answer": "in South Asia, Hindus have stricter beliefs than Muslims.",
        "distractor1": "Hindus worship thousands of gods, even though they are all different manifestations of Brahman.",
        "distractor2": "the majority of people in South Asia are Hindu.",
        "distractor3": "today, as in the past, Hinduism helps shape Indian culture."
    },
    {
        "question": "A similarity between Hinduism and Buddhism is that both?:",
        "correct_answer": "accept the idea of samsara.",
        "distractor1": "support the caste system.",
        "distractor2": "are monotheistic.",
        "distractor3": "were founded by respected Brahmans."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is a specific stage of life for the Hindu?:",
        "correct_answer": "student.",
        "distractor1": " ahimsa .",
        "distractor2": " moksha .",
        "distractor3": " satyagraha ."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement BEST explains why British India was partitioned in 1947?:",
        "correct_answer": "religious differences led to political division.",
        "distractor1": "the British feared a united India.",
        "distractor2": "one region of India wanted to remain under British control.",
        "distractor3": "Communist forces refused to participate in a centralized Indian government."
    },
    {
        "question": "In India, the Sikh struggle for independence for the Punjab State and the disagreement between Muslims and Hindus in Kashmir show that?:",
        "correct_answer": "religious conflicts can often divide people.",
        "distractor1": "the economy rarely affects politics.",
        "distractor2": "India\\'s non-alignment policy will resolve these conflicts.",
        "distractor3": "foreign influence can help people solve their problems."
    },
    {
        "question": "In India, Mohandas Gandhi\\'s support for the rights of women and Harijans illustrates Gandhi\\'s?:",
        "correct_answer": "willingness to break caste rules in the pursuit of justice.",
        "distractor1": "ability to reach agreement with Muslim leaders.",
        "distractor2": "rejection of Western values.",
        "distractor3": "commitment to a policy of non-alignment in world affairs."
    },
    {
        "question": "Since the 1950s, India has experienced conflict with both Pakistan and China over?:",
        "correct_answer": "borders and related territorial issues.",
        "distractor1": "United Nations peacekeeping efforts in the region.",
        "distractor2": "India\\'s incrasing trade with Korea.",
        "distractor3": "the interpretation of common religious works."
    },
    {
        "question": "The nation of Bangladesh was created as a result of the?:",
        "correct_answer": "cultural and economic differences between East Pakistan and West Pakistan.",
        "distractor1": "breakup of the East India Company.",
        "distractor2": "fighting between Hindu and Muslim factors in Nepal.",
        "distractor3": "human rights policy of the United Nations."
    },
    {
        "question": "Under its policy of non-alignment, India?:",
        "correct_answer": "accepted aid from both the United States and the Soviet Union during the Cold War era.",
        "distractor1": "refused to join the United Nations.",
        "distractor2": "signed the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty.",
        "distractor3": "supported East Pakistan in its civil war with West Pakistan."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980s, a major problem in India was?:",
        "correct_answer": "violence resulting from cultural differences.",
        "distractor1": "widespread rejection of the policy of non-alignment.",
        "distractor2": "the increase in Christian missionary activities in Calcutta and Bombay.",
        "distractor3": "the threat of invasion from Pakistan."
    },
    {
        "question": "In India, the Green Revolution led directly to?:",
        "correct_answer": "an increase in food production.",
        "distractor1": "the creation of a democratic government.",
        "distractor2": "the spread of Buddhism.",
        "distractor3": "the mass migration of people to rural areas."
    },
    {
        "question": "Throughout most of its independent existence, Pakistan has been governed by?:",
        "correct_answer": "a military dictatorship.",
        "distractor1": "Muhammed Ali Jinnah.",
        "distractor2": "a functioning parliamentary system.",
        "distractor3": "Islamic clerics."
    },
    {
        "question": "Many of India\\'s educated professionals have migrated to Europe and the United States.  How has India been affected by this migration?:",
        "correct_answer": "it has lost the services of many talented doctors and engineers.",
        "distractor1": "many of its students are studying for advanced degrees in architecture.",
        "distractor2": "its exports to Western nations have decreased.",
        "distractor3": "its citizens have been encouraged to return to their farming villages. "
    },
    {
        "question": "The problem over Kashmir has brought India into conflict with?:",
        "correct_answer": "Pakistan.",
        "distractor1": "Afghanistan.",
        "distractor2": "China.",
        "distractor3": "Vietnam."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which factor has contributed most to the social and cultural identity of the Middle East?:",
        "correct_answer": "the strong influence of Islam on the region.",
        "distractor1": "the political stability of the region.",
        "distractor2": "a lack of foreign involvement in the region.",
        "distractor3": "the ability of the region to export oil."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which BEST describes a characteristic of Islam?:",
        "correct_answer": "Islam, like other major religions, is composed of sects which sometimes disagree on beliefs and practices.",
        "distractor1": "Islam has largely lost its influence on the daily lives of its followers.",
        "distractor2": "a major goal of Islamic religious leaders is the adaptation of Western cultural ideas.",
        "distractor3": "separation of church and state is a fundamental belief of Islam."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about women under Islam is CORRECT?:",
        "correct_answer": "women were expected to be modest and to obey their fathers or husbands.",
        "distractor1": "according to the  Quran , women had no legal rights.",
        "distractor2": "in farming villages, women were forbidden to work in the fields.",
        "distractor3": "women had less rights after the spread of Islam than they had before."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement BEST describes Islamic art and architecture?:",
        "correct_answer": "the architecture of the Islamic world blended Greek, Roman, Persian, and Islamic traditions.",
        "distractor1": "most Islamic art and architecture used only Arab designs and styles.",
        "distractor2": "Islamic architects built mosques but were forbidden to design palaces.",
        "distractor3": "the Islamic world produced little art and architecture because the  Qur\\'an  forbade it."
    },
    {
        "question": "Before the appearance of Muhammed in Arabia, life in that area was organized along which of the following lines?:",
        "correct_answer": "tribal nomadic societies and small trade towns.",
        "distractor1": "sheikhs ruling each city in Arabia.",
        "distractor2": "a strict rule by one Arabian king.",
        "distractor3": "a central government at Medina."
    },
    {
        "question": "A good Muslim does all of the following EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "goes to pray in a group at the mosque on Saturday.",
        "distractor1": "believe that Muhammed was God\\'s messenger.",
        "distractor2": "reads his holy book, the  Qur\\'an .",
        "distractor3": "fasts and makes a pilgrimage to Mecca at least once in his lifetime."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT closely related to the other three?:",
        "correct_answer": "the Dome of the Rock.",
        "distractor1": " Kaabah .",
        "distractor2": "Mecca.",
        "distractor3": " Hadj ."
    },
    {
        "question": "Saturday : Judaism ::   _____?_____  : Islam",
        "correct_answer": "Friday.",
        "distractor1": "Sunday.",
        "distractor2": "Saturday.",
        "distractor3": "Monday."
    },
    {
        "question": "Islam changed the status of women by?:",
        "correct_answer": "giving them some legal and economic rights.",
        "distractor1": "permitting them to enter convents while still pre-teens.",
        "distractor2": "forbidding them to learn Arabic.",
        "distractor3": "making them equal to men."
    },
    {
        "question": "Muslims consider the  Qur\\'an  the greatest written work in Arabic mainly because it?:",
        "correct_answer": "is believed to be the word of  Allah .",
        "distractor1": "tells of the life of Muhammed.",
        "distractor2": "protects the \"People of the Book.\"",
        "distractor3": "establishes a system of law, the  Shariah ."
    },
    {
        "question": "The split between Sunni and Shi\\'ite Muslims began with disagreements over?:",
        "correct_answer": "the choice of caliph.",
        "distractor1": "acceptance of the  Qur\\'an  as the Muslim book of sacred scriptures.",
        "distractor2": "a belief in one God.",
        "distractor3": "the required pilgrimage to Mecca."
    },
    {
        "question": "All of the following are \"Pillars\" of Islam EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "making apilgrimage to Medina at least once in a Muslim\\'s lifetime.",
        "distractor1": "the  shahada .",
        "distractor2": "fasting during  Ramadan .",
        "distractor3": "almsgiving."
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Middle East, during the Golden Age of Muslim culture, scholars were encouraged to?:",
        "correct_answer": "preserve and expand ancient Greek and Roman learning.",
        "distractor1": "reject all knowledge that was Western European in origin.",
        "distractor2": "ignore the achievements of Chinese culture.",
        "distractor3": "accept medieval Western European religious ideas."
    },
    {
        "question": "Ramadan : Islam ::   _____?_____   : Roman Catholicism",
        "correct_answer": "Lent.",
        "distractor1": "Palm Sunday.",
        "distractor2": "Christmas.",
        "distractor3": "Easter."
    },
    {
        "question": "The \\'Umayyads were able to conquer only one region in Europe. That region was?:",
        "correct_answer": "Spain.",
        "distractor1": "France.",
        "distractor2": "Russia.",
        "distractor3": "southern Britain."
    },
    {
        "question": "Generally Christians conquered by the Muslims were permitted to live in peace, but they were forbidden from doing all of the following EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "paying taxes.",
        "distractor1": "trying to convert Muslims to Christianity.",
        "distractor2": "intermarriage with Muslims.",
        "distractor3": "attending the same schools as Muslims."
    },
    {
        "question": "Muslim artists and scientists developed and excelled in all of the following crafts EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "religious sculpture and paintings.",
        "distractor1": "mosaics.",
        "distractor2": "calligraphy.",
        "distractor3": "arabesque design."
    },
    {
        "question": "The economic prosperity of the Islamic Empire was due largely to?:",
        "correct_answer": "trade and commerce.",
        "distractor1": "the development of a feudal manorial economy system.",
        "distractor2": "the spoils of war.",
        "distractor3": "the manufacture of steel swords sold to the Chinese and to the Western Europeans."
    },
    {
        "question": "For Jews living under Islam?:",
        "correct_answer": "they participated fully in commercial and professional activities and some even became advisors to the caliphs.",
        "distractor1": "their situation was similar to that of Jews living in Christian Europe.",
        "distractor2": "their status was considerably lower than that of Christians.",
        "distractor3": "they frequently found themselves subject to violent oppression by Muslim governments."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Japan, a major economic problem has been the lack of?:",
        "correct_answer": "natural resources.",
        "distractor1": "skilled labor.",
        "distractor2": "investment capital.",
        "distractor3": "experienced management."
    },
    {
        "question": "Only a small portion of Japan is suitable for agriculture because much of the land?:",
        "correct_answer": "is too mountainous.",
        "distractor1": "is covered by rain forests.",
        "distractor2": "lies near the Arctic Circle.",
        "distractor3": "does not receive enough rainfall."
    },
    {
        "question": "The rivers of Japan?:",
        "correct_answer": "are important for hydro-electricity.",
        "distractor1": "originate near the sea coast.",
        "distractor2": "all flow northward.",
        "distractor3": "serve as ocean highways for many miles up-river."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following natural disasters strikes Japan frequently?:",
        "correct_answer": "earthquakes.",
        "distractor1": "blizzards.",
        "distractor2": "drought.",
        "distractor3": "dust storms."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT an archipelago?:",
        "correct_answer": "Taiwan.",
        "distractor1": "Japan.",
        "distractor2": "Indonesia.",
        "distractor3": "the Philippines."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following Japanese islands is most likely to receive a lot of snowfall in the winter?:",
        "correct_answer": "Hokkaido.",
        "distractor1": "Kyushu.",
        "distractor2": "Shikoku.",
        "distractor3": "Honshu."
    },
    {
        "question": "In terms of resources for industrial use, Japan is most lacking in?:",
        "correct_answer": "petroleum.",
        "distractor1": "hydro-electric power.",
        "distractor2": "coal.",
        "distractor3": "lumber."
    },
    {
        "question": "Because most of Japan is mountainous, its people lived mostly?:",
        "correct_answer": "in river valleys and coastal plains.",
        "distractor1": "in the mountains.",
        "distractor2": "on the smallest islands.",
        "distractor3": "in houseboats on Japan\\'s major rivers."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following has the most tropical climate?:",
        "correct_answer": "Kyushu.",
        "distractor1": "Honshu.",
        "distractor2": "Shikoku.",
        "distractor3": "Hokkaido."
    },
    {
        "question": "One effect of Japan\\'s geographic isolation was that?:",
        "correct_answer": "writing developed later there than in China.",
        "distractor1": "the Japanese people developed no religion of their own.",
        "distractor2": "the people developed a highly centralized social and political life from the beginning.",
        "distractor3": "writing developed earlier than in China."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1930s, Japan\\'s foreign policy was based on the strategy of?:",
        "correct_answer": "territorial expansion.",
        "distractor1": "rapid consumer growth.",
        "distractor2": "economic isolation.",
        "distractor3": "democratic alliance."
    },
    {
        "question": "Between the Meiji Restoration and World War II, Japan tried to solve the problem of its scarcity of natural resources by?:",
        "correct_answer": "exporting agricultural products in exchange for new technology.",
        "distractor1": "establishing a policy of imperialism.",
        "distractor2": "building nuclear power plants.",
        "distractor3": "cooperating with the Soviet Union to gain needed resources."
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason for Japanese expansion in Asia in the early 1900s was its desire to?:",
        "correct_answer": "gain equal status with western imperial powers.",
        "distractor1": "increase the power of the zaibatsu.",
        "distractor2": "attract foreign investment capital.",
        "distractor3": "reduce the power of the military."
    },
    {
        "question": "The military gained influence in Japan as a result of the?:",
        "correct_answer": "depression of 1929.",
        "distractor1": "burning of the Japanese Parliament.",
        "distractor2": "assassination of Emperor Hirohito.",
        "distractor3": "the Long March."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was the chief victim of Japan\\'s imperialistic aggression in Asia during the years 1915-1939?:",
        "correct_answer": "China.",
        "distractor1": "Thailand.",
        "distractor2": "Japan.",
        "distractor3": "the U. S. S. R."
    },
    {
        "question": "In the 1930s, Manchuria became a symbol of Japan\\'s?:",
        "correct_answer": "desire for empire.",
        "distractor1": "attempts to aid underdeveloped regions.",
        "distractor2": "religious conversion to Christianity.",
        "distractor3": "experimentation with a socialist government."
    },
    {
        "question": "Japan was recognized to be a world power as a result of?:",
        "correct_answer": "defeating Russia in 1905.",
        "distractor1": "adoption of a new constitution.",
        "distractor2": "ending feudalism in 1871.",
        "distractor3": "returning Taiwan to China."
    },
    {
        "question": "One factor which contributed to the poor relations between the United States and Japan in the early part of the 20c was?:",
        "correct_answer": "the US racial policies and practics against Oriental immigrants.",
        "distractor1": "the US alliance with the Soviet Union and Germany.",
        "distractor2": "the US refusal to participate in the Washington Naval Conference.",
        "distractor3": "the practice of taking over control of the zaibatsu."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Greater East Asia Co-Prosperity Sphere was the label given to?:",
        "correct_answer": "Japan\\'s plan for her economic and political control of East Asia.",
        "distractor1": "Japan\\'s puppet kingdom in Manchuria.",
        "distractor2": "Japan\\'s new capital.",
        "distractor3": "the military dominated zaibatsu."
    },
    {
        "question": "Under the militarists, the Japanese government taught schoolchildren?:",
        "correct_answer": "service to the state.",
        "distractor1": "Western ideas.",
        "distractor2": "communist ideology.",
        "distractor3": "independent thinking."
    },
    {
        "question": "During World War I, Japan declared itself?:",
        "correct_answer": "against Germany to advance its interests in East Asia.",
        "distractor1": "allied with Germany to take control of the seas from Great Britain.",
        "distractor2": "against the United States for ideological reasons.",
        "distractor3": "neutral to continue to trade with both sides."
    },
    {
        "question": "Between the World Wars, Japanese politics?:",
        "correct_answer": "were characterized by militarism and assassination.",
        "distractor1": "were controlled by the absolutist emperor.",
        "distractor2": "became increasingly liberalized and democratic.",
        "distractor3": "adhered to pacifist public opinion."
    },
    {
        "question": "After the Manchurian [Mukden] Incident and the invasion of China, Japanese military leaders accurately concluded that?:",
        "correct_answer": "neither the League of Nations, Great Britain, France, nor the United States was willing to take forceful steps to stop Japanese aggression.",
        "distractor1": "they had better retreat from their expansionist goals because of international opposition.",
        "distractor2": "they had accomplished all of their objectives.",
        "distractor3": "they had better launch an immediate attack on Germany."
    },
    {
        "question": "By late 1941, the Japanese government was under the leadership and control of?:",
        "correct_answer": "General Tojo.",
        "distractor1": "Premier Hara.",
        "distractor2": "zaibatsu leaders.",
        "distractor3": "the major political parties."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Japan, the samurai code of Bushido helped bring about?:",
        "correct_answer": "a culture that accepted militarism.",
        "distractor1": "equality among Japanese citizens.",
        "distractor2": "peaceful relations with other nations.",
        "distractor3": "an increased interest in science and technology."
    },
    {
        "question": "Japanese Emperors claimed to be descended from?:",
        "correct_answer": "the sun goddess, Amaterasu.",
        "distractor1": "the Buddha.",
        "distractor2": "the Ainu.",
        "distractor3": "the first Chinese Emperor."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 600s and 700s, the Japanese adapted many ideas from?:",
        "correct_answer": "China.",
        "distractor1": "India.",
        "distractor2": "Islam.",
        "distractor3": "the Mongols."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the feudal periods in Japan and Europe, a family\\'s wealth was mainly determined by the?:",
        "correct_answer": "amount of land the family controlled.",
        "distractor1": "number of children in the family.",
        "distractor2": "size of the castles built by the family.",
        "distractor3": "value of the family\\'s gifts to religious leaders."
    },
    {
        "question": "Japan\\'s location influenced its early history in part because it?:",
        "correct_answer": "protected Japan from invasion.",
        "distractor1": "encouraged close ties with India.",
        "distractor2": "helped Japan control most of Asia.",
        "distractor3": "protected Japan from earthquakes."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which has been most consistently true of Japanese emperors throughout history?:",
        "correct_answer": "they have continued to occupy the throne, but at times with little power.",
        "distractor1": "they have ruled Japan with absolute power.",
        "distractor2": "they have periodically been elected by the people.",
        "distractor3": "they have headed parliamentarly governments."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which figure would compare best to feudal Japan\\'s shogun?:",
        "correct_answer": "a military dictator.",
        "distractor1": "a president of a modern corporation.",
        "distractor2": "the Prime Minister of England.",
        "distractor3": "a Christian missionary."
    },
    {
        "question": "Yoritomo, who became the first Shogun?:",
        "correct_answer": "took political power away from the emperor.",
        "distractor1": "outlawed further cultural borrowing from China.",
        "distractor2": "helped establish Christianity as a major religion.",
        "distractor3": "began to build Japan into a modern industrial nation."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Kamakura Shogunate began after the?:",
        "correct_answer": "end of the Heian period.",
        "distractor1": "Mongol invasion.",
        "distractor2": "fall of the Manchu Dynasty in China.",
        "distractor3": "reign of Ieyasu."
    },
    {
        "question": "The samurai code of Bushido stressed?:",
        "correct_answer": "loyalty and indifference to pain.",
        "distractor1": "individualism and self-interest.",
        "distractor2": "generosity and social reform.",
        "distractor3": "scholarship and gentility."
    },
    {
        "question": "The shoen was they?:",
        "correct_answer": "land and the corresponding right to its income held by feudal lords in Japan.",
        "distractor1": "highly stylized theater popular in Tokugawa Japan.",
        "distractor2": "traditional form of dress worn by the samurai warrior.",
        "distractor3": "complex relationship between the emperor and shogunate established by Tokugawa Ieyasu."
    },
    {
        "question": "Upper class women played an important role in Japanese?:",
        "correct_answer": "literary development.",
        "distractor1": "religious teachings.",
        "distractor2": "govenrment.",
        "distractor3": "economic growth."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following BEST characterizes the government of early Heian Japan?:",
        "correct_answer": "a strong central government.",
        "distractor1": "local governments that had strong authority.",
        "distractor2": "a democracy with an assembly of citizens.",
        "distractor3": "a separate empire in each of the Japanese islands."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Japanese learned all of these from China EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "the belief that the emperor was divine and could do no wrong.",
        "distractor1": "the Confucian stress on forms of behavior and ancestor worship.",
        "distractor2": "central government administraiton.",
        "distractor3": "Buddhism."
    },
    {
        "question": "Japan\\'s closeness to the Asian mainland resulted in the Japanese borrowing the?:",
        "correct_answer": "Chinese writing system.",
        "distractor1": "tomb culture from China.",
        "distractor2": "Indian caste system.",
        "distractor3": "Shinto religion from Korea."
    },
    {
        "question": "A samurai committed seppuku?:",
        "correct_answer": "all of these choices are correct.",
        "distractor1": "when he wished to avoid surrender.",
        "distractor2": "to make up for a mistake or a crime.",
        "distractor3": "when his actions had been questioned."
    },
    {
        "question": "A major difference between the societies of the United States and Japan is the presence in the United States of a higher degree of?:",
        "correct_answer": "cultural diversity.",
        "distractor1": "religious conformity.",
        "distractor2": "economic security.",
        "distractor3": "access to elementary education."
    },
    {
        "question": "In the period since World War II, Japan has dealt with its shortage of natural resources mainly by following a policy of?:",
        "correct_answer": "developing many industrial products for export.",
        "distractor1": "becoming an agriculturally oriented nation.",
        "distractor2": "enforcing a program of austerity for its civilian population.",
        "distractor3": "attempting to take over nearby resource-rich nations."
    },
    {
        "question": "An accurate description of life in Japan today is that the Japanese people have?:",
        "correct_answer": "blended traditional ways with Western ways to meed the needs of modern life.",
        "distractor1": "remained a largely rural, agricultural society.",
        "distractor2": "isolated themselves from Western culture.",
        "distractor3": "achieved their goal of a classless society in which all people benefit from economic progress."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is the best explanation for Japan\\'s current industrial success?:",
        "correct_answer": "the government\\'s role in setting and supporting national goals.",
        "distractor1": "need to support heavy military expenses.",
        "distractor2": "vast reserves of raw materials and fossil fuels.",
        "distractor3": "emphasis on individual achievement rather than group effort."
    },
    {
        "question": "Growth in the Japanese economy since World War II has been accomplished despite the fact that Japan has?:",
        "correct_answer": "few natural resources.",
        "distractor1": "little modern technology.",
        "distractor2": "high unemployment.",
        "distractor3": "low worker productivity."
    },
    {
        "question": "Even though Japan has few natural resources, it has a high standard of living mainly because it has?:",
        "correct_answer": "developed technology that can be exchanged for the resources it needs.",
        "distractor1": "printed more money whenever living standards have started to decline.",
        "distractor2": "imported manufactured goods.",
        "distractor3": "produced goods and services without obtaining resources."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which reform took place in Japan after World War II?:",
        "correct_answer": "Japan became a representative democracy.",
        "distractor1": "Japan\\'s industrial capability was greatly reduced.",
        "distractor2": "the emperor\\'s position was abolished.",
        "distractor3": "labor unions were declared illegal."
    },
    {
        "question": "In recent years, which factor has been a major reason for the economic tensions between the United States and Japan?:",
        "correct_answer": "the United States imported more from Japan than it exported to Japan.",
        "distractor1": "Japan\\'s trade deficit with the United States was very high.",
        "distractor2": "the United States refused to place quotas on Japanese goods.",
        "distractor3": "Japan lowered tariffs on goods imported from the United States."
    },
    {
        "question": "                     \"Tokyo Stock Market Drops 130 Points\"                      \"London Exchange Falls Following Japanese Drop\" These headlines reflect?:",
        "correct_answer": "global interdependence in economic matters.",
        "distractor1": "an attitude of ethnocentrism on the part of the European nations.",
        "distractor2": "the growth of socialism in Europe and Asia.",
        "distractor3": "the problems arising from a positionn of non-alignment."
    },
    {
        "question": "The government of Japan is best described as?:",
        "correct_answer": "a parliamentary system.",
        "distractor1": "a military dictatorship.",
        "distractor2": "an absolute monarchy.",
        "distractor3": "a Communist dictatorship."
    },
    {
        "question": "A major goal of the Christian Church during the Crusades [1096-1291] was to?:",
        "correct_answer": "capture the Holy Land from Islamic rulers.",
        "distractor1": "establish Christianity in Western Europe.",
        "distractor2": "unite warring Arab peoples.",
        "distractor3": "strengthen English dominance in the Arab world."
    },
    {
        "question": "A major result of the Crusades was the?:",
        "correct_answer": "growth of trade between Europe and Asia.",
        "distractor1": "conversion of the majority of Europeans to Protestantism.",
        "distractor2": "weakening of the power of the middle class in the Ottoman Empire.",
        "distractor3": "development of feudalism in Africa."
    },
    {
        "question": "One way in which the Seljuk Turks and Mongols were similar is that they both?:",
        "correct_answer": "emerged from Central Asia.",
        "distractor1": "were defeated by the Byzantine Empire.",
        "distractor2": "traded along the sea routes of the Mediterranean with Rome.",
        "distractor3": "developed unique forms of Christianity."
    },
    {
        "question": "An observation about the Ottoman Empire in the 15c and 16c is that the Empire?:",
        "correct_answer": "had a strategic location between Europe and Asia.",
        "distractor1": "originated in Hungary.",
        "distractor2": "was totally landlocked.",
        "distractor3": "had control over most of Western Europe."
    },
    {
        "question": "The rivalry between Ottoman and Safavid Empires was fueled in par by differences over?:",
        "correct_answer": "religion.",
        "distractor1": "whether to recognize European diplomats in their courts.",
        "distractor2": "language.",
        "distractor3": "who should control the Bosphorus Straits."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about the Ottoman Empire is supported by the facts?:",
        "correct_answer": "the Ottomans were generally tolerant of the diverse peoples in their empire.",
        "distractor1": "the Ottomans destroyed the Arab Empire.",
        "distractor2": "the Ottoman Empire ruled the Middle East during the Golden Age of Islam.",
        "distractor3": "Ottoman rulers relied on the Persians to enforce their control over the Middle East."
    },
    {
        "question": "The elite army corps composed primarily of Christian slaves was known as the?:",
        "correct_answer": "janissaries.",
        "distractor1": "ghazis.",
        "distractor2": "pashas.",
        "distractor3": "sahibs."
    },
    {
        "question": "The final collapse of the Byzantine and Arab Islamic empires was caused by?:",
        "correct_answer": "the conquests of the Ottoman Turks.",
        "distractor1": "the revival of the Roman Empire in Western Europe.",
        "distractor2": "the success of Slavic invasions of the Balkan Peninsula.",
        "distractor3": "their defeat by the Seljuk Turks."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Ottoman and Safavid empires shared the Muslim tradition of?:",
        "correct_answer": "the  Sharia. ",
        "distractor1": "peaceful non-violent protests by the people against their government.",
        "distractor2": "religious intolerance.",
        "distractor3": "massive, gaudy architectural styles."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Ottoman Empire reached its Golden Age during the reign of?:",
        "correct_answer": "Suleiman the Great.",
        "distractor1": "Abu Bakr.",
        "distractor2": "Mehmet I.",
        "distractor3": "Osman."
    },
    {
        "question": "In 1453, the Ottomans captured which of the following cities?:",
        "correct_answer": "Constantinople.",
        "distractor1": "Isfahan.",
        "distractor2": "Baghdad.",
        "distractor3": "Cairo."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which event brought about the breakup of the Ottoman Empire?:",
        "correct_answer": "World War I.",
        "distractor1": "Six-Day War.",
        "distractor2": "the Crusades.",
        "distractor3": "World War II."
    },
    {
        "question": "A major threat to the Ottoman Empire in the 1800s was?:",
        "correct_answer": "nationalism.",
        "distractor1": "socialism.",
        "distractor2": "anti-Semitism.",
        "distractor3": "industrialization."
    },
    {
        "question": "Ataturk is best remembered for?:",
        "correct_answer": "modernizing Turkey.",
        "distractor1": "overthrowing the Safavid Shahs.",
        "distractor2": "ending European imperialism in Egypt.",
        "distractor3": "forcing the British to leave Jerusalem."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Zionist movement primarily desired to?:",
        "correct_answer": "create a Jewish homeland in Palestine.",
        "distractor1": "stop the persecution of Jews in England.",
        "distractor2": "free Jerusalem from Arab control.",
        "distractor3": "fight against the Ottoman Turks."
    },
    {
        "question": "Under the League of Nations, the former colonies of the Ottoman and German empires were to be assisted in forming their own government.  The result of this new mandate system was to?:",
        "correct_answer": "put the former colonial peoples on the road to self-government.",
        "distractor1": "establish dictatorships in the mandated countries.",
        "distractor2": "prohibit the colonization of these territories.",
        "distractor3": "take economic advantage of the former colonies."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Sykes-Picot Agreement and the Balfour Declaration ignored the nationalistic feelings of the?:",
        "correct_answer": "Arab people.",
        "distractor1": "African people.",
        "distractor2": "Iranian people.",
        "distractor3": "Turkish people."
    },
    {
        "question": "The primary cause of the Armenian Massacres of 1915 was?:",
        "correct_answer": "Turkish fears that Armenians might be conspiring with the Russians.",
        "distractor1": "Armenian aid to the Germans during World War I.",
        "distractor2": "the refusal of the Armenians to sell oil to the Central Powers.",
        "distractor3": "centuries long Russian hatred toward the Armenians."
    },
    {
        "question": "In 1907, Persia was divided into spheres of influence by?:",
        "correct_answer": "Russia and Britain.",
        "distractor1": "France and the United States.",
        "distractor2": "the United States and Russia.",
        "distractor3": "Afghanistan and the Ottoman Empire."
    },
    {
        "question": "A major result of the growth of Zionism in the late 1800s was the?:",
        "correct_answer": "immigration of European Jews to Palestine.",
        "distractor1": "defeat of the Ottoman Empire.",
        "distractor2": "formation of the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO).",
        "distractor3": "increased tensions between the superpowers in the Middle East."
    },
    {
        "question": "After 1929, the majority of Jewish emigrants to Palestine came from?:",
        "correct_answer": "Europe (largely Germany and Poland).",
        "distractor1": "the United States.",
        "distractor2": "Russia.",
        "distractor3": "the Arab states."
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Middle East, most of the land suitable for farming is found in the?:",
        "correct_answer": "river valleys.",
        "distractor1": "rain forest.",
        "distractor2": "savanna regions.",
        "distractor3": "mountain areas."
    },
    {
        "question": "A major problem for most nations of the Middle East has been the?:",
        "correct_answer": "lack of fresh water.",
        "distractor1": "long, frigid winters.",
        "distractor2": "monsoon flooding.",
        "distractor3": "lack of mineral resources."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Middle East has many deserts. The main effect of the desert has been?:",
        "correct_answer": "difficulty in raising sufficient food.",
        "distractor1": "an expanding rain forest.",
        "distractor2": "political instability.",
        "distractor3": "a lack of religious unity."
    },
    {
        "question": "A study of the population distribution of the Middle East would show that people?:",
        "correct_answer": "generally settle near water supplies.",
        "distractor1": "are evenly distributed throughout the Middle East.",
        "distractor2": "want to live near the large oil reserves.",
        "distractor3": "generally live in the mountains."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which geographic feature has been most responsible for the population distribution in the Middle East?:",
        "correct_answer": "location of water.",
        "distractor1": "abundance of oil deposits.",
        "distractor2": "presence of high plateaus.",
        "distractor3": "availability of natural harbors."
    },
    {
        "question": "The lands of the Middle East can be studied as one region because they are similar in all of the following ways EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "they are ruled by similar types of governments.",
        "distractor1": "they all have the same kind of climate.",
        "distractor2": "most of the people are Muslims.",
        "distractor3": "they have similar problems."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following countries does NOT lie within the Fertile Crescent?:",
        "correct_answer": "Libya.",
        "distractor1": "Lebanon.",
        "distractor2": "Syria.",
        "distractor3": "Iraq."
    },
    {
        "question": "The most densely populated area of the Middle East today is the?:",
        "correct_answer": "Nile River Delta.",
        "distractor1": "Iranian Plateau.",
        "distractor2": "Jordan River Valley.",
        "distractor3": "Lebanon."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Fertile Crescent is the arc of land that?:",
        "correct_answer": "curves from the Persian Gulf to the Nile Delta.",
        "distractor1": "lies between the Tigris and Euphrates rivers.",
        "distractor2": "lies along the banks of the Nile River.",
        "distractor3": "reaches down to the African kingdom of Axum."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Gupta Empire enjoyed a Golden Age in part because of the?:",
        "correct_answer": "general peace and prosperity of the times.",
        "distractor1": "spread of Buddhism.",
        "distractor2": "invention of the decimal system.",
        "distractor3": "power of the Dehil sultans."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is best supported by a study of the history of South Asia?:",
        "correct_answer": "invaders and local princes battled for control of the northern plain.",
        "distractor1": "the British were the first rulers to unite India.",
        "distractor2": "cultural diversity helped strong Indian leaders unify their kingdoms.",
        "distractor3": "powerful kingdoms in southern India after conquered the Indo-Gangetic Plain."
    },
    {
        "question": "During India\\'s early history, Indian social and family life centered on the?:",
        "correct_answer": "village.",
        "distractor1": "city-state.",
        "distractor2": "mosque.",
        "distractor3": "sultanate."
    },
    {
        "question": "All of the following are true statements about the reign of Asoka EXCEPT that?:",
        "correct_answer": "under his rule, the Gupta Empire reached it greatest size.",
        "distractor1": "he converted to Buddhism during his reign.",
        "distractor2": "he practiced toleration of all religions.",
        "distractor3": "he sent Buddhist missionaries to Southeast Asia."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which region of India was never united by a conqueror?:",
        "correct_answer": "southern India.",
        "distractor1": "the Deccan.",
        "distractor2": "northern India.",
        "distractor3": "eastern India."
    },
    {
        "question": "The plays of the Indian dramatist Kalidasa were known for their?:",
        "correct_answer": "focus on emotions.",
        "distractor1": "use of tragedy as a main theme of each play.",
        "distractor2": "focus on religious themes.",
        "distractor3": "skill with comedic timing."
    },
    {
        "question": "What impact did Gupta mathematicians have on civilization?:",
        "correct_answer": "they developed the Arabic number system and the concept of zero.",
        "distractor1": "they developed basid algebra.",
        "distractor2": "very few advances were made in mathematics during the Gupta dynasty.",
        "distractor3": "they developed Euclidean geometry."
    },
    {
        "question": "One cause of the Maurya Empire\\'s collapse was?:",
        "correct_answer": "popular unrest generated by heavy taxation.",
        "distractor1": "the death of Chandragupta II.",
        "distractor2": "invasions along the northwestern border.",
        "distractor3": "Hindu resentment of pro-Buddhist policies."
    },
    {
        "question": "Throughout most of its history, the political structure of India consisted of?:",
        "correct_answer": "a complex pattern of separate independent states.",
        "distractor1": "a strong centralized government tightly controlling the entire territory.",
        "distractor2": "total domination by Europeans.",
        "distractor3": "control by the rival Chinese empire."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following were examples of the many accomplishments of the Gupta period in Indian history?: 1 - a lunar calandar of 28-day months. 2 - the idea that the earth was round. 3 - the classification of over 500 new viruses. 4 - brain surgery. 5 - the setting of broken bones.",
        "correct_answer": "5 only.",
        "distractor1": "1, 3, 4, and 5.",
        "distractor2": "2, 3, and 4.",
        "distractor3": "1 and 5 only."
    },
    {
        "question": "The primary reason that the Japanese policy of near-isolation ended in 1853-54 was that Japan?:",
        "correct_answer": "was pressured by American naval power to open its ports.",
        "distractor1": "needed additional territory as an outlet for its surplus population.",
        "distractor2": "became involved in a war with China.",
        "distractor3": "needed European markets for its manufactured goods."
    },
    {
        "question": "In an attempt to modernize Japan during the late 1800s, the leaders of the Meiji government decided to?:",
        "correct_answer": "study Western institutions and technology.",
        "distractor1": "established close relations with China.",
        "distractor2": "maintain a policy of isolationism.",
        "distractor3": "end the political power of the Buddhists in the government."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best explains Japan\\'s relationships with other nations since the 1860s?:",
        "correct_answer": "Japan has needed to acquire sufficient raw materials for its industries.",
        "distractor1": "an abundance of natural resources has made Japan self-sufficient.",
        "distractor2": "Japan\\'s island location has discouraged Japanese imperialism.",
        "distractor3": "rejection of foreign technology has forced Japan into isolation."
    },
    {
        "question": "Japan\\'s defeat of Russia in 1905 encouraged natinonalist hopes in Southeast Asia because?:",
        "correct_answer": "an Asian nation defeated a major European power.",
        "distractor1": "Japan promised to supported independence movements in Southeast Asia.",
        "distractor2": "all the Russian colonies in the area became independent.",
        "distractor3": "Japan was China\\'s chief rival in the area."
    },
    {
        "question": "A social reform of the Meiji Restoration was to?:",
        "correct_answer": "make everyone equal before the law.",
        "distractor1": "make Japan a multiparty democracy.",
        "distractor2": "expand Japanese power in Asia.",
        "distractor3": "build factories on western models."
    },
    {
        "question": "Unlike China during the Age of European Imperialism, Japan?:",
        "correct_answer": "modernized rapidly.",
        "distractor1": "had to sign unequal treaties with western nations.",
        "distractor2": "was able to isolate itself from the world.",
        "distractor3": "rejected its Confucian traditions."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following exports financed Japan\\'s economic expansion during the Meiji period?:",
        "correct_answer": "silk.",
        "distractor1": "electronics.",
        "distractor2": "porcelain.",
        "distractor3": "steam locomotive technology."
    },
    {
        "question": "The modernization of Japan during the Meiji Restoration resulted in?:",
        "correct_answer": "the rise of Japan as an imperialistic nation.",
        "distractor1": "a return to a feudal system of government.",
        "distractor2": "an alliance between China, Korea, Russia, and Japan.",
        "distractor3": "a strengthening of Japan\\'s isolationist policies."
    },
    {
        "question": "In the past, the flooding of the Nile River resulted in?:",
        "correct_answer": "the deposit of rich soil along the valley.",
        "distractor1": "huge loss of human lives.",
        "distractor2": "the building of large temples and palaces.",
        "distractor3": "dangerous leaching of the soil."
    },
    {
        "question": "What evidence supports the conclusion that government and religion were closely linked in ancient Egypt?:",
        "correct_answer": "Egyptians believed their ruler was a god.",
        "distractor1": "the people believed in an afterlife.",
        "distractor2": "priests conducted ceremonies to please the gods.",
        "distractor3": "Egyptians were polytheistic."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Rosetta Stone was most useful for?:",
        "correct_answer": "deciphering hieroglyphic writing.",
        "distractor1": "identifying the early gods of the Egyptians.",
        "distractor2": "tracing the wanderings of the Jews.",
        "distractor3": "predicting ancient eclipses."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements about Egyptian society is true?:  1 -- A person was born into his or her social class.  2 -- The majority of Egyptians were peasants.  3 -- Soldiers were more powerful than priests.  4 -- Only slaves learned to read and write.",
        "correct_answer": "1 & 2.",
        "distractor1": "1 only.",
        "distractor2": "2 & 3.",
        "distractor3": "4 only."
    },
    {
        "question": "The need to survey land after the Nile\\'s floods led to the development of?:",
        "correct_answer": "geometry.",
        "distractor1": "astronomy.",
        "distractor2": "navigation.",
        "distractor3": "engineering."
    },
    {
        "question": "The contribution of Menes to the development of Egypt was?:",
        "correct_answer": "to unite Upper and Lower Egypt.",
        "distractor1": "to build the first pyramid.",
        "distractor2": "to develop a system of irrigation.",
        "distractor3": "to organize villags into individual city-states."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Egyptian  Book of the Dead  contains?",
        "correct_answer": "rituals and secret magical formulas to help individuals pass into the afterlife.",
        "distractor1": "the Ten Commandments, which Moses gave to the Israelites.",
        "distractor2": "the story of the pharaoh Akhenaton\\'s worship of Ra, the sun.",
        "distractor3": "all of these choices are correct."
    },
    {
        "question": "How did Egyptians respond to Hatshepsut\\'s rule?:\t",
        "correct_answer": "they were opposed to the concept of having a woman as a ruler.",
        "distractor1": "they welcomed such an able ruler.",
        "distractor2": "they never knew she was a woman because drawings always showed her wearing a beard.",
        "distractor3": "they feared her because they thought she was a sorceress."
    },
    {
        "question": "A comparison of Mesopotamian and Egyptian civilizations shows that both?:",
        "correct_answer": "had a powerful priesthood.",
        "distractor1": "used cuneiform.",
        "distractor2": "had identical river systems.",
        "distractor3": "had rulers who were preceived as omnipotent gods."
    },
    {
        "question": "An Egyptian pharaoh was different from other monarchs of the ancient world in that?:",
        "correct_answer": "he was worshipped as a living god.",
        "distractor1": "he could only marry after the death of his father.",
        "distractor2": "he was considered divine after his death, when he became lord of the underworld.",
        "distractor3": "he was not allowed to marry until his mother had approved his choice for a wife."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Ancient Egypt, the early pharaohs\\' belief in their own divinity led them to?:",
        "correct_answer": "be mummified for their afterlife.",
        "distractor1": "rule with the aid of viziers or personal ministers and advisors.",
        "distractor2": "conquer surrounding peoples.",
        "distractor3": "maintain large standing armies."
    },
    {
        "question": "Compared with other ancient societies, women in ancient Egypt?:",
        "correct_answer": "had far more independence and rights.",
        "distractor1": "had far less independence and fewer rights.",
        "distractor2": "were never seen in public or allowed to work outside the home.",
        "distractor3": "never held political offices."
    },
    {
        "question": "A long-term effect of the Balfour Declaration on the Middle East was the?:",
        "correct_answer": "conflict between the Palestinians and the Israelis.",
        "distractor1": "oppression of the Kurds by the government of Iraq.",
        "distractor2": "strengthening of parliamentary rule in Turkey.",
        "distractor3": "establishment of a two-party system in Lebanon."
    },
    {
        "question": "The main goal of the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO) is to?:",
        "correct_answer": "create an independent Palestinian state.",
        "distractor1": "win parliamentary seats in Israel.",
        "distractor2": "reduce international involvement in Middle Eastern affairs.",
        "distractor3": "strengthen Israeli control over the occupied territories."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Egyptian-Israeli War in 1973 led directly to the?:",
        "correct_answer": "first Arab oil embargo.",
        "distractor1": "freedom of the Palestinian people.",
        "distractor2": "creation of the PLO.",
        "distractor3": "expansion of OPEC."
    },
    {
        "question": "The mass murder of European Jews during the Holocaust directly influenced the growth of which of the following movements?:",
        "correct_answer": "Zionism.",
        "distractor1": "industrialism.",
        "distractor2": "communism.",
        "distractor3": "Pan-Africanism."
    },
    {
        "question": "One factor that has greatly contributed to instability in the Middle East has been the?:",
        "correct_answer": "issue of a Palestinian homeland.",
        "distractor1": "European demand for Mideast oil.",
        "distractor2": "attempt to unify all Arab peoples.",
        "distractor3": "UN peace-keeping forces there."
    },
    {
        "question": "UN Resolution 242 and the Camp David Accords were attempts to?:",
        "correct_answer": "bring about peace in the Middle East.",
        "distractor1": "force Israeli withdrawal from Jerusalem.",
        "distractor2": "settle water rights to the Jordan River.",
        "distractor3": "provide better housing for Palestinian refugees."
    },
    {
        "question": "A goal of the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) is to?:",
        "correct_answer": "control world oil prices.",
        "distractor1": "find alternative fuel for automobiles.",
        "distractor2": "force Syrian troops to leave Lebanon.",
        "distractor3": "stop the production of oil."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Suez Canal and the Persian Gulf are important bodies of water because they are?:",
        "correct_answer": "routes for trade with other regions.",
        "distractor1": "considered holy to Middle Eastern religions.",
        "distractor2": "sources of hydroelectric power.",
        "distractor3": "barriers to invasions of the Middle East."
    },
    {
        "question": "Many Arab nations in the past had conflicts with the nation of Israel because?:",
        "correct_answer": "Israel occupied territory that was formerly held by the Arabs.",
        "distractor1": "the government of Israel was supported by the Soviet Union.",
        "distractor2": "Israel refused to share its technology with those Arab nations.",
        "distractor3": "Israel has tried to convert the Arabs to Judaism."
    },
    {
        "question": "One goal of Islamic fundamentalist governments in the Middle East is to?:",
        "correct_answer": "protect Islamic culture from becoming westernized.",
        "distractor1": "increase Arab trade around the world.",
        "distractor2": "improve economic opportunities for women in Islamic nations.",
        "distractor3": "join the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO)."
    },
    {
        "question": "Of the four Arab-Israeli wars fought since 1948, Jewish forces have won?:",
        "correct_answer": "all.",
        "distractor1": "two.",
        "distractor2": "one.",
        "distractor3": "three."
    },
    {
        "question": "The British, French, and Israelis were forced to withdraw from Egypt by?:",
        "correct_answer": "the United States and the Soviet Union.",
        "distractor1": "Egypt and Syria.",
        "distractor2": "Russia and Egypt.",
        "distractor3": "the Palestinians and Libya."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement concerning the Islamic world is most accurate?:",
        "correct_answer": "significant religious and political differences exist among Islamic sects.",
        "distractor1": "religious unity has led to political unity among Islamic nations.",
        "distractor2": "the only Islamic nations of the world are found in the Middle East.",
        "distractor3": "all Islamic nations are totally committed to the destruction of Israel."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 20c, the governments of Afghanistan and Iran were similar in that both were linked to?:",
        "correct_answer": "incidents of international terrorism.",
        "distractor1": "efforts to separate religion and politics.",
        "distractor2": "advocates of international terrorism.",
        "distractor3": "promotion of democratic principles in Third World nations."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the 1980s, the economic development of Iran and Iraq was disrupted because of?:",
        "correct_answer": "the war fought between these nations.",
        "distractor1": "increased emphasis on agricultural production for export.",
        "distractor2": "Communist revolutionary movements in these nations.",
        "distractor3": "severe drought and famine in the area."
    },
    {
        "question": "The major goal of the Iranian Revolution and of Ayatollah Khomeini was to?:",
        "correct_answer": "create an Islamic Republic.",
        "distractor1": "establish closer ties with Israel.",
        "distractor2": "prevent the expansion of communism into Iraq.",
        "distractor3": "nationalize the oil industry."
    },
    {
        "question": "One cause of the Iranian Revolution was?:",
        "correct_answer": "failure of the Shah\\'s reforms to improve life for many Iranians.",
        "distractor1": "Iran\\'s defeat in the Iran-Iraq War.",
        "distractor2": "the Shah\\'s refusal to modernize the Iranian legal system.",
        "distractor3": "the death of the Ayatollah Khomeini."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Operation Desert Storm, American forces freed Kuwait from occupation by?:",
        "correct_answer": "Iraq.",
        "distractor1": "Iran.",
        "distractor2": "Syria.",
        "distractor3": "Israel."
    },
    {
        "question": "One purpose of the UN sanctions after the Gulf War was to force Saddam Hussein to destroy?:",
        "correct_answer": "chemical weapons.",
        "distractor1": "Iraqi oil reserves.",
        "distractor2": "vital shipping lanes in the Persian Gulf.",
        "distractor3": "illegal poppy fields in northern Iraq."
    },
    {
        "question": "The United States became involved in wars in the Persian Gulf in order to?:",
        "correct_answer": "protect the flow of oil to the West and the rest of the world.",
        "distractor1": "keep the region safe for democracy.",
        "distractor2": "protect the lives of American in the region.",
        "distractor3": "prevent environmental disasters."
    },
    {
        "question": "A major result of Iraq\\'s invasion of Kuwait was?:",
        "correct_answer": "a show if international cooperation under the guise of the United Nations.",
        "distractor1": "the immediate overthrow of Saddam Hussein.",
        "distractor2": "the introduction of Communism into Kuwait.",
        "distractor3": "lasting peace throughout the world."
    },
    {
        "question": "In the aftermath of the Persian Gulf War?:",
        "correct_answer": "the United States was slow in reacting to Hussein\\'s repression of Iraqi Shi\\'ites and Kurds.",
        "distractor1": "Saddam Hussein was overthrown and assassinated as a result of a coup organized and funded by the American CIA.",
        "distractor2": "the Kuwaiti government instituted reforms that turned it into a model of democracy.",
        "distractor3": "the United Nations oversaw the dismantling of Iraq\\'s military establishment and the destruction of its war-making weapons."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Iran under Ayatollah Khomeini and in Afghanistan throughout the 1990s, an effect of the Islamic fundamentalist government has been to?:",
        "correct_answer": "limit rights for women.",
        "distractor1": "produce an agrarian-based economy.",
        "distractor2": "eliminate anti-Israeli terrorist groups within their borders.",
        "distractor3": "create a strong military alliance with the Soviet Union."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Soviet invasion of Afghanistan was similar to United States involvement in the Vietnam War because?:",
        "correct_answer": "both wars were unpopular and sparked protests at home.",
        "distractor1": "the superpowers primarily used guerrilla tactics.",
        "distractor2": "their victories increased their international prestige.",
        "distractor3": "the UN Security Council supported their actions."
    },
    {
        "question": "Compared to the classical cities of the late 4c and 5c of Western Europe, Constantinople?:",
        "correct_answer": "was much larger and more prosperous.",
        "distractor1": "had less protection from invaders.",
        "distractor2": "produced fewer scholars and works of art.",
        "distractor3": "gave people greater freedom of religion and though."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Byzantine emperor Justinian tried to rebuild the Roman Empire by?:",
        "correct_answer": "fighting the Germanic peoples who had invaded the Empire.",
        "distractor1": "defeating the armies of Islam.",
        "distractor2": "recognizing the Pope as the highest authority in the Church.",
        "distractor3": "signing treaties with the Huns."
    },
    {
        "question": "Constantinople\\'s location had all of the following advantages EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "being midway between the Eastern and Western Roman Empires.",
        "distractor1": "being a crossroads for trade by land and sea.",
        "distractor2": "being easy to defend.",
        "distractor3": "having a harbor on a major strait."
    },
    {
        "question": "Byzantine artists made a lasting impact in the areas of?:",
        "correct_answer": "religious art, mosaics, and architecture.",
        "distractor1": "charcoal and watercolors.",
        "distractor2": "sculpture and painting.",
        "distractor3": "carpet weaving and textiles."
    },
    {
        "question": "Under Justinian, the old Roman Empire was?:",
        "correct_answer": "restored almost to its former borders.",
        "distractor1": "conquered by the Persian Empire.",
        "distractor2": "made more democratic.",
        "distractor3": "threatened by Muslim armies."
    },
    {
        "question": "Today, the person most likely to study  Justinian\\'s Code  would be a?:",
        "correct_answer": "legal scholar.",
        "distractor1": "professor of surgery.",
        "distractor2": "mathematician.",
        "distractor3": "philosopher."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Byzantine Empire made its most important contribution to later civilizations by?:",
        "correct_answer": "preserving much of the Greco-Roman heritage.",
        "distractor1": "defeating the Hun invaders.",
        "distractor2": "trading with merchants from the Middle East.",
        "distractor3": "recognizing the Pope as head of the Byzantine Church."
    },
    {
        "question": "A Babylonian schoolboy wrote his lessons on?:",
        "correct_answer": "clay tablets.",
        "distractor1": "block of slate.",
        "distractor2": "papyrus scroll.",
        "distractor3": "stones."
    },
    {
        "question": "The movement of peoples across the Fertile Crescent resulted in the?:",
        "correct_answer": "constant exchange of ideas.",
        "distractor1": "invention of hieroglyphics.",
        "distractor2": "belief in one god.",
        "distractor3": "building of irrigation systems."
    },
    {
        "question": "Sumerians influenced later civilizations through each of the following EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "law codes.",
        "distractor1": "arithmetic and geometry.",
        "distractor2": "architecture.",
        "distractor3": "cuneiform."
    },
    {
        "question": "What important invention is first known to have been used by the Sumerians?:",
        "correct_answer": "the wheel.",
        "distractor1": "the pulley.",
        "distractor2": "paper.",
        "distractor3": "the battering ram."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best describes the principle behind Hammurabi\\'s Code?:",
        "correct_answer": "An eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth.",
        "distractor1": "Church and state must be separate.",
        "distractor2": "Judge not lest you be judged.",
        "distractor3": "Justice must be tempered by mercy."
    },
    {
        "question": "The  Epic of Gilgamesh  is?:",
        "correct_answer": "a poem recounting the adventures of a Sumerian hero.",
        "distractor1": "the story of the Hebrew\\'s flight from Egypt.",
        "distractor2": "an Egyptian folktale.",
        "distractor3": "a tale about King Nebuchadnezzar."
    },
    {
        "question": "Hammurabi\\'s Code provided for different penalties according to?:",
        "correct_answer": "social class.",
        "distractor1": "age.",
        "distractor2": "motive.",
        "distractor3": "the whim of the judge."
    },
    {
        "question": "Sumerian sites such as Ur, Uruk, and Eridu are considered by historians to be?:",
        "correct_answer": "among the world\\'s first cities.",
        "distractor1": "the birthplace of spoken language.",
        "distractor2": "the birthplace of polytheism.",
        "distractor3": "the finest examples of Egyptian architecture."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the rule of King Nebuchadnezzar, Babylon?:",
        "correct_answer": "became known as one of the world\\'s most beautiful cities.",
        "distractor1": "became capital of the Hittite Empire.",
        "distractor2": "was destroyed by the Persians.",
        "distractor3": "was built by the Hebrews."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement about the Fertile Crescent is accurate?:",
        "correct_answer": "rich soil and abundant water, especially in the Tigris-Euphrates Valley made it a center of early civilization.",
        "distractor1": "because it was protected from invasion, strong empires emerged there.",
        "distractor2": "it was located on the Arabian Peninsula and sat atop abundant oil resources.",
        "distractor3": "it stretches in an arc along the southern rim of the Mediterranean Sea."
    },
    {
        "question": "Scholars have included the Akkadians in their study of the advance of civilization because?:",
        "correct_answer": "they built the first empire of the Near East.",
        "distractor1": "Solomon\\'s mines hinted at the magnificence of the culture.",
        "distractor2": "they came close to achieving a monotheistic religion.",
        "distractor3": "they developed the use of iron weapons."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is meant by the tern \"cuneiform?\":",
        "correct_answer": "a script using wedge-shaped marks impressed into clay tablets, first used by the Sumerians, to record spoken language.",
        "distractor1": "the process by which copper and tin are combined to create the more valuable metal bronze.",
        "distractor2": "a mathematical algebraic innovation that enabled people to solve complex problems.",
        "distractor3": "the channels through which water was diverted in order to irrigate the fields of early city-states."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Persians united their vast empire by?:",
        "correct_answer": "developing an excellent system of roads.",
        "distractor1": "forcing all the conquered people to learn cuneiform.",
        "distractor2": "using Hammurabi\\'s code of law.",
        "distractor3": "adopting the achievements of ancient Greek civilization."
    },
    {
        "question": "The ancient land of Persia is known today as?:",
        "correct_answer": "Iran.",
        "distractor1": "Turkey.",
        "distractor2": "Iraq.",
        "distractor3": "Lebanon."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following beliefs did both Zoroastrians and Hebrews hold?:",
        "correct_answer": "on the final judgment day, individuals would be held responsible for their actions.",
        "distractor1": "the gods controlled the forced of nature.",
        "distractor2": "G_d revealed the Ten Commandments to Moses.",
        "distractor3": "every year, the gods came down to earth using the ziggurat as a ladder."
    },
    {
        "question": "The  Zend Avesta  is?:",
        "correct_answer": "a collection of religious hymns and poems.",
        "distractor1": "the law code of the Persian Empire.",
        "distractor2": "an epic poem about Cyrus\\'s accomplishments.",
        "distractor3": "a collection of essays on politics by Cyrus."
    },
    {
        "question": "Zoroaster taught that?:",
        "correct_answer": "life is a constant struggle between good and evil.",
        "distractor1": "humans are mere pawns, manipulated by the gods.",
        "distractor2": "priests should have power over political leaders.",
        "distractor3": "there is only one god."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Persian Empire maintained order through?:",
        "correct_answer": "tolerance and good government.",
        "distractor1": "a policy of terror and oppression.",
        "distractor2": "use of missionaries and public legal proclamations.",
        "distractor3": "belief in one god."
    },
    {
        "question": "A major accomplishment of Sargon I was to?:",
        "correct_answer": "unite the city-states of Mesopotamia.",
        "distractor1": "restore the royal archives at Ebla.",
        "distractor2": "develop a 365-day calendar.",
        "distractor3": "facilitate the spread of the Sumerian language."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following was most characteristic of the Persian Empire?:",
        "correct_answer": "people were especially noted for their interest in astrology.",
        "distractor1": "it did not engage in extensive trade.",
        "distractor2": "it had cruel and intolerant rulers.",
        "distractor3": "its military engineers developed new techniques of war."
    },
    {
        "question": "Under the rule of Cyrus of Persia?:",
        "correct_answer": "local self-rule was permitted under Persian supervision.",
        "distractor1": "the kings of conquered territories were replaced by democracies.",
        "distractor2": "extreme leniency of local rulers was tolerated.",
        "distractor3": "the Hebrews were exterminated."
    },
    {
        "question": "The supreme deity of Zoroastrianism, who personified power, majesty, and of positive ethical principles, was?:",
        "correct_answer": "Ahura-Mazda.",
        "distractor1": "Ahriman.",
        "distractor2": "Zarathustra.",
        "distractor3": "Avesta."
    },
    {
        "question": "Probably the earliest people to use iron were the?:",
        "correct_answer": "Hittites.",
        "distractor1": "Lydians.",
        "distractor2": "Phoenicians.",
        "distractor3": "Hebrews."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Phoenicians were important in history because they?:",
        "correct_answer": "invented the alphabet which eventually was used by the West.",
        "distractor1": "invented the coinage of money.",
        "distractor2": "were the first people to make use of iron.",
        "distractor3": "first developed the idea of monotheism."
    },
    {
        "question": "Ideas were spread throughout the Mediterranean by Phoenician?:",
        "correct_answer": "merchants.",
        "distractor1": "priests.",
        "distractor2": "armies.",
        "distractor3": "kings."
    },
    {
        "question": "The pattern of political rule in Southwest Asia after 900 BCE was one of?:",
        "correct_answer": "a series of empires created by various invaders.",
        "distractor1": "continuous control by one group.",
        "distractor2": "continuous migration, with no one group in full control.",
        "distractor3": "small rival kingdoms fighting for control of the area."
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Phoenician traders develop to help them do business?:",
        "correct_answer": "an alphabet using symbols to represent sounds.",
        "distractor1": "faster ships that could hold more goods.",
        "distractor2": "a sought-after dye called \"Tyrian purple\".",
        "distractor3": "papyrus to make scrolls for books."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Assyrians earned a reputation in the ancient world for?:",
        "correct_answer": "their extreme cruelty.",
        "distractor1": "their seafaring talent.",
        "distractor2": "allowing conquered peoples to retain their customs.",
        "distractor3": "many significant scientific achievements."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which effect did the Mughals have on India during their rule?:",
        "correct_answer": "Muslim culture dominated in parts of India.",
        "distractor1": "parliamentary republics were established.",
        "distractor2": "India became unified under one language.",
        "distractor3": "Hinduism became the dominant religion in northern India."
    },
    {
        "question": "Unlike the Delhi sultans, Akbar believed in?:",
        "correct_answer": "religiouis freedom.",
        "distractor1": "the custom of  suttee. ",
        "distractor2": "no taxes.",
        "distractor3": "Hindu inferiority."
    },
    {
        "question": "Shah Jahan made the people pay high taxes mainly to?:",
        "correct_answer": "finance the building of magnificent palaces.",
        "distractor1": "improve their living conditions.",
        "distractor2": "maintain their right to practice Hinduism.",
        "distractor3": "construct vast irrigation systems."
    },
    {
        "question": "Muslims and Hindus clashed in India because?:",
        "correct_answer": "the Hindu belief in many gods offended Muslims.",
        "distractor1": "Hindus believed all people were equal in the sight of God.",
        "distractor2": "Muslims worshipped sacred animals.",
        "distractor3": "Hindus wanted to change the caste system."
    },
    {
        "question": "Mughal art and literature reflected the?:",
        "correct_answer": "blending of Hindu and Muslim traditions.",
        "distractor1": "importance of the caste system.",
        "distractor2": "growing influence of Christianity.",
        "distractor3": "decline in Islam."
    },
    {
        "question": "Akbar is considered the greatest Mughal ruler because he?:",
        "correct_answer": "tried to ensure peace between Hindus and Muslims.",
        "distractor1": "defeated the Delhi Sultanate.",
        "distractor2": "built the Taj Mahal.",
        "distractor3": "spread Buddist ideas."
    },
    {
        "question": "Unlike Hindus, Muslims in India?:",
        "correct_answer": "preached the equality of all believers.",
        "distractor1": "were tolerant of the religious practices of other peoples.",
        "distractor2": "used music in their worship.",
        "distractor3": "regarded cattle as sacred animals."
    },
    {
        "question": "Aurangzeb\\'s policies toward Hinduism included all of the following EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "appointing Hindus to high office.",
        "distractor1": "taxing Hindus more than Muslims.",
        "distractor2": "destroying Hindu temples.",
        "distractor3": "making India an Islamic state."
    },
    {
        "question": "After Turkish sultans gained control of northern India in 1206, they established?:",
        "correct_answer": "a new regime known as the Delhi sultanate.",
        "distractor1": "Hinduism as the state religion of the Delhi sultanate.",
        "distractor2": "the Ghaznavid Empire.",
        "distractor3": "religious toleration that fostered the growth of Hinduism and Buddhism."
    },
    {
        "question": "A unique aspect of religion in Japan is that?:",
        "correct_answer": "many Japanese practice both Buddhism and Shinto.",
        "distractor1": "most major religions have no formal priesthood.",
        "distractor2": "all Japanese religions are monotheistic.",
        "distractor3": "the current Emperor is regarded as a god."
    },
    {
        "question": "A person who practices the Shinto faith would be most likely to?:",
        "correct_answer": "visit a shrine placed on the shore of a lake.",
        "distractor1": "bathe in the Ganges River.",
        "distractor2": "pray five times a day.",
        "distractor3": "make a pilgrimage to Jerusalem."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was Shintoism\\'s major teaching?:",
        "correct_answer": "reverence for the land.",
        "distractor1": "achievement of human perfection.",
        "distractor2": "love for fellow humans.",
        "distractor3": "reincarnation of the soul."
    },
    {
        "question": "All of the following are characteristics of Shintoism EXCEPT?:",
        "correct_answer": "very elaborate decorations and gawdy architectural styles.",
        "distractor1": "love of beauty.",
        "distractor2": "an emphasis on cleanliness.",
        "distractor3": "animism."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Japan, the traditional arts of flower arranging, haiku poetry, and origami show the Japanese love and respect for?:",
        "correct_answer": "nature.",
        "distractor1": "the family.",
        "distractor2": "the military.",
        "distractor3": "technology."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following did Shintoism and Confucianism have in common in Japan?:",
        "correct_answer": "respect and submission to higher authority.",
        "distractor1": "emphasis on military virtues and the arts of war.",
        "distractor2": "worship of the spirits and deities in nature.",
        "distractor3": "rebellion against the emperor, which both religions permitted under certain circumstances."
    },
    {
        "question": "Shinto beliefs?:",
        "correct_answer": "all of these choices are correct.",
        "distractor1": "were closely integrated with political authority.",
        "distractor2": "held Amaterasu, the female solar deity, as its chief deity.",
        "distractor3": "were animistic."
    },
    {
        "question": "Population density is greatest in the northern part of India because?:",
        "correct_answer": "the major river systems are located in this area.",
        "distractor1": "people tend to settle along the seacoast.",
        "distractor2": "the population centers in China are easy to reach from this area.",
        "distractor3": "families in this area traditionally are larger than families in southern India."
    },
    {
        "question": "The monsoons are important to India mainly because the monsoons?:",
        "correct_answer": "bring needed rainfall.",
        "distractor1": "isolate India from Southeast Asia.",
        "distractor2": "prevent the spread of disease.",
        "distractor3": "are associated with religious values."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Khyber and other passes through the Kindu Kush were important because they?:",
        "correct_answer": "aided the movement of people and goods and established an invasion route.",
        "distractor1": "had fertile farmland.",
        "distractor2": "were the source of India\\'s greatest rivers.",
        "distractor3": "kept invaders from reaching the fertile river valleys."
    },
    {
        "question": "One reason that the Indus, Ganges, and Brahmaputra are important is that they?:",
        "correct_answer": "provide water for irrigation.",
        "distractor1": "form borders between India and its neighbors.",
        "distractor2": "protect India from outside invasions.",
        "distractor3": "link northern and southern India."
    },
    {
        "question": "The climate of India is largely determined by monsoons, which are?:",
        "correct_answer": "seasonal winds.",
        "distractor1": "heavy rains.",
        "distractor2": "large, dark clouds.",
        "distractor3": "typhoons."
    },
    {
        "question": "The level, fertile heartland of India is the?:",
        "correct_answer": "Indo-Gangetic Plain.",
        "distractor1": "Indus Valley.",
        "distractor2": "Deccan Plateau.",
        "distractor3": "Hindu Kush."
    },
    {
        "question": "Floods are an all too common natural disaster in this low-lying river delta subject to wind-driven tidal surges?:",
        "correct_answer": "Bangladesh.",
        "distractor1": "Nepal.",
        "distractor2": "Phutan.",
        "distractor3": "Sikkim."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Deccan Plateau?:",
        "correct_answer": "separated southern India from the rest of the subcontinent.",
        "distractor1": "provided a geographic barrier that prevented foreign invasion of the Indian subcontinent.",
        "distractor2": "was the site of India\\'s earliest civilization.",
        "distractor3": "was the location of major trade routes."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Ghats were?:",
        "correct_answer": "mountain ranges which separate the eastern and western coastal regions from the Deccan Plateau.",
        "distractor1": "the earliest known inhabitants of India.",
        "distractor2": "the two major river systems on the Indian subcontinent.",
        "distractor3": "two culturally different peoples who ilve in the mountain regions of the north."
    },
    {
        "question": "Moral results can only be obtained through moral restraints. -- Mohandas K. Gandhi. This quotation BEST represents the policy of?:\t",
        "correct_answer": "passive resistance.",
        "distractor1": "westernization.",
        "distractor2": "neutrality.",
        "distractor3": "balance of power."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which situation contributed to the success of Mohandas Gandhi\\'s campaign of civil disobedience in India?:",
        "correct_answer": "Great Britain was weakened by World War II.",
        "distractor1": "Pakistan and Bangladesh were involved in civil wars.",
        "distractor2": "the United States came to Gandhi\\'s aid with food and clothing.",
        "distractor3": "Sikhs and Muslims wanted to create a new nation."
    },
    {
        "question": "It has impoverished the dumb millions by a system of progressive exploitation....It has reduced us politically to serfdom. It has sapped the foundation of our culture...and degraded us spiritually. --- Mohandas K. Gandhi, 1930. In the statement, the it referred to by Gandhi is?:",
        "correct_answer": "British imperialism in India.",
        "distractor1": "India\\'s involvement in World War I.",
        "distractor2": "the exploitation of the proletariat by the bourgeoisie.",
        "distractor3": "the British endorsement of apartheid in South Africa."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which action is most consistent with Mohandas Gandhi\\'s ideas about civil disobedience?:",
        "correct_answer": "refusing to pay taxes.",
        "distractor1": "bombing a government office building.",
        "distractor2": "blackmailing a political official.",
        "distractor3": "holding diplomats as hostages."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which action illustrates the ideas of Mohandas K. Gandhi\\'s policy of civil disobedience?:",
        "correct_answer": "accepting a jail sentence for participating in an illegal peaceful protest.",
        "distractor1": "blowing up an airplane to call attention to injustice.",
        "distractor2": "voting in a national election.",
        "distractor3": "kidnapping a government official and demanding ransom."
    },
    {
        "question": "During India\\'s independence movement, Mohandas Gandhi\\'s boycott of British-made goods was effective because the British considered India a major?:",
        "correct_answer": "market for manufactured goods.",
        "distractor1": "shipping center.",
        "distractor2": "industrial center.",
        "distractor3": "source of mineral resources."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which event was used by Mohandas Gandhi to bring world attention to the injustices of British colonialism in India?:",
        "correct_answer": "Salt March.",
        "distractor1": "outbreak of World War I.",
        "distractor2": "formation of India\\'s Parliament.",
        "distractor3": "Sepoy Mutiny."
    },
    {
        "question": "\"Indian National Congress Refuses to Support British War Effort\" \"Indians Answer Call for the Production of Homespun Cloth\" \"Indians Call for Boycott of Imported British Cloth\" These three headlines all refer to?:",
        "correct_answer": "attempts by the native people to gain India\\'s independence.",
        "distractor1": "political reorganization in the British colonial empire.",
        "distractor2": "programs to increase India\\'s standard of living.",
        "distractor3": "the benefits of economic interdependence between Britain and India."
    },
    {
        "question": "Gandhi transformed the Indian independence movement from?:",
        "correct_answer": "an elite to a mass movement.",
        "distractor1": "a previously violent to a non-violent movement.",
        "distractor2": "an urban to a rural movement.",
        "distractor3": "a British to a primarily Indian movement."
    }
]